<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 15:46:00 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Exhaustive Search for Quantum Circuit Optimization using ZX Calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10983</link><description>Quantum computers allow a near-exponential speed-up for specific applications when compared to classical computers. Despite recent advances in the hardware of quantum computers, their practical usage is still severely limited due to a restricted number of available physical qubits and quantum gates, short coherence time, and high error rates. This paper lays the foundation towards a metric independent approach to quantum circuit optimization based on exhaustive search algorithms. This work uses depth-first search and iterative deepening depth-first search. We rely on ZX calculus to represent and optimize quantum circuits through the minimization of a given metric (e.g. the T-gate and edge count). ZX calculus formally guarantees that the semantics of the original circuit is preserved. As ZX calculus is a non-terminating rewriting system, we utilise a novel set of pruning rules to ensure termination while still obtaining high-quality solutions. We provide the first formalization of quantum circuit optimization using ZX calculus and exhaustive search. We extensively benchmark our approach on 100 standard quantum circuits. Finally, our implementation is integrated in the well-known libraries PyZX and Qiskit as a compiler pass to ensure applicability of our results.</description><author>Tobias Fischbach, Pierre Talbot and Pascal Bouvry</author><pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10983</guid></item><item><title>Bridging wire and gate cutting with ZX-calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11494</link><description>Quantum circuit cutting refers to a series of techniques that allow one to partition a quantum computation on a large quantum computer into several quantum computations on smaller devices. This usually comes at the price of a sampling overhead, that is quantified by the $1$-norm of the associated decomposition. The applicability of these techniques relies on the possibility of finding decompositions of the ideal, global unitaries into quantum operations that can be simulated onto each sub-register, which should ideally minimize the $1$-norm. In this work, we show how these decompositions can be obtained diagrammatically using ZX-calculus expanding on the work of Ufrecht et al. [arXiv:2302.00387]. The central idea of our work is that since in ZX-calculus only connectivity matters, it should be possible to cut wires in ZX-diagrams by inserting known decompositions of the identity in standard quantum circuits. We show how, using this basic idea, many of the gate decompositions known in the literature can be re-interpreted as an instance of wire cuts in ZX-diagrams. Furthermore, we obtain improved decompositions for multi-qubit controlled-Z (MCZ) gates with $1$-norm equal to $3$ for any number of qubits and any partition, which we argue to be optimal. Our work gives new ways of thinking about circuit cutting that can be particularly valuable for finding decompositions of large unitary gates. Besides, it sheds light on the question of why exploiting classical communication decreases the 1-norm of a wire cut but does not do so for certain gate decompositions. In particular, using wire cuts with classical communication, we obtain gate decompositions that do not require classical communication.</description><author>Marco Schumann, Tobias Stollenwerk and Alessandro Ciani</author><pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11494</guid></item><item><title>Graphical Stabilizer Decompositions for Multi-Control Toffoli Gate Dense Quantum Circuits</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03798</link><description>In this thesis, we study concepts in quantum computing using graphical languages, specifically using the ZX-calculus. The core of the research revolves around (graphical) stabilizer decompositions. The first major focus is on the decomposition of non-stabilizer states created from star edges. We discuss previous results and then present novel decompositions that yield a theoretical improvement. The second major focus is on weighting algorithms, applied to the special class of multi-control Toffoli gate dense quantum circuits. The representation of the corresponding gates is based on star edges. The applicability of known methods, such as CNOT-grouping, traditionally used for other classes, is examined in the context of this specific class. We then present a novel weighting algorithm that attempts to determine the best vertex to decompose. A refined version is implemented to simulate a known class of quantum querying algorithms, which is used to search for causal configurations of multiloop Feynman diagrams. For this case, as well as for a generalized benchmark consisting of randomly generated quantum circuits, we demonstrate occasional improvements in the final number of terms against traditional methods. These results are discussed by considering different simplification strategies. This thesis also provides a brief but broad outline of the important preliminaries.</description><author>Yves Vollmeier</author><pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03798</guid></item><item><title>Unveiling a Hidden Percolation Transition in Monitored Clifford Circuits: Inroads from ZX-Calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13211</link><description>We revisit the measurement-induced phase transition (MPT) in Clifford circuits, which are both classically simulable and exhibit critical behavior widely believed to be distinct from classical percolation theory, using ZX-calculus. We analyze the MPT in a dynamical model composed of CNOT, SWAP, identity gates, and Bell-pair measurements, respectively, arranged randomly in a brickwork pattern. Our circuits exhibit a transition that is seemingly distinct from classical percolation based on standard arguments, that is in line with the prevailing understanding in the field. In contrast, by employing ZX-calculus based simplification techniques, we unveil a hidden percolation transition within the circuit structure. Over a range of parameters tied to the probabilities for applying different gates, we demonstrate that the classical percolation transition in the ZX-simplified network coincides with the MPT observed through mutual information. Our findings suggest that the MPT in Clifford circuits is, in fact, controlled by a classical percolation transition in disguise.</description><author>Einat Buznach, Debanjan Chowdhury and Jonathan Ruhman</author><pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13211</guid></item><item><title>Diagrammatic Quantum Circuit Compression for Hamiltonian Simulation</title><link>https://dx.doi.org/10.18420/se2025-ws-24</link><description>One of the promising applications for early quantum computers is the simulation of of dynamical quantum systems. Due to the limited coherence time of such devices, the depth-compression of quantum circuits is crucial to facilitate useful results. It has been shown that certain quantum models can even be compressed to constant depth, meaning it is only linearly dependent on the number of qubits, but independent of the simulation time and the number of Trotter steps. This has been done by extracting the circuit structure derived from the model characteristics via Hamiltonian simulation. Based on these results, we present a diagrammatic approach to circuit compression utilizing a powerful technique for reasoning about quantum circuits called ZX-calculus. We demonstrate our approach by deriving constant-depth circuit compressions for quantum models known to be constant-depth, as well as novel models previously unstudied. Our method could serve as a first step toward the development of more advanced circuit compression methods, that could be employed to enable Hamiltonian simulation of a larger variety of quantum models, and beyond.</description><author>Victoria Wadewitz, Aaron Szasz, Daan Camps, Katherine Klymko and Tobias Stollenwerk</author><pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://dl.gi.de/items/55b8918c-cccd-4b39-9b57-889735ea1c31</guid></item><item><title>Efficient Heuristics for Classical Simulation of Quantum Circuits Using ZX-Calculus</title><link>https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/ahmad-thesis.pdf</link><description>Quantum circuits require validation and testing to ensure that they perform as expected. Classical simulation is a powerful tool for this purpose, but it is limited by the exponential growth of complexity with the number of qubits. Nevertheless, using the ZX-calculus, a graphical language for quantum mechanics, we can attempt to reduce how exponential this growth is. Recent developments have allowed focus to be placed on complexity being dependent on the number of T-gates that are in the circuit. Given $t$ T-gates, if the complexity of classically simulating the circuit is $O(2α t)$, the aim is to reduce the value of $α$ as much as possible, where $0 &lt; α &lt; 1$. This thesis presents a heuristic approach toward exploiting the structure of the ZX-diagrams used to represent the quantum circuits, in order to reduce $α$. We conceptualise a formal definition of the heuristic method, applying it to existing approaches, and also develop new heuristics that take advantage of the structure made available in the ZX-diagrams. These heuristics perform well in practice, boosting the number of T-gates that can be simulated classically by up to three times as many on certain classes of circuits</description><author>Wira Azmoon Ahmad</author><pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/ahmad-thesis.pdf</guid></item><item><title>Quantum Computing from Graphs</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17959</link><description>While stabilizer tableaus have proven exceptionally useful as a descriptive tool for additive quantum codes, they offer little guidance for concrete constructions or coding algorithm analysis. We introduce a representation of stabilizer codes as graphs with certain structures. Specifically, the graphs take a semi-bipartite form where input nodes map to output nodes, such that output nodes may connect to each other but input nodes may not. Intuitively, the graph's input-output edges represent information propagation of the encoder, while output-output edges represent the code's entanglement. We prove that this graph representation is in bijection with tableaus and give an efficient compilation algorithm that transforms tableaus into graphs. We show that this map is efficiently invertible, which gives a universal recipe for code construction by finding graphs with nice properties. The graph representation gives insight into both code construction and algorithms. To the former, we argue that graphs provide a flexible platform for building codes. We construct several constant-size codes and several infinite code families. We also use graphs to extend the quantum Gilbert-Varshamov bound to a three-way distance-rate-weight trade-off. To the latter, we show that key coding algorithms, distance approximation, weight reduction, and decoding, are unified as instances of a single optimization game on a graph. Moreover, key code properties such as distance, weight, and encoding circuit depth, are all controlled by the graph degree. We give efficient algorithms for producing encoding circuits whose depths scale with the degree and for implementing certain logical diagonal and Clifford gates with reduced depth. Finally, we find an efficient decoding algorithm for certain classes of graphs. These results give evidence that graphs are useful for the study of quantum computing and its implementations.</description><author>Andrey Boris Khesin</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17959</guid></item><item><title>Pauli web of the $|Yångle$ state surface code injection</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15566</link><description>We employ ZX-calculus and Pauli web to understand the $|Yångle$ state injection on the rotated surface code.</description><author>Kwok Ho Wan and Zhenghao Zhong</author><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15566</guid></item><item><title>Dynamic T-decomposition for classical simulation of quantum circuits</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17182</link><description>It is known that a quantum circuit may be simulated with classical hardware via stabilizer state (T-)decomposition in $O(2^α t)$ time, given $t$ non-Clifford gates and a decomposition efficiency $α$. The past years have seen a number of papers presenting new decompositions of lower $α$ to reduce this runtime and enable simulation of ever larger circuits. More recently, it has been demonstrated that well placed applications of apparently weaker (higher $α$) decompositions can in fact result in better overall efficiency when paired with the circuit simplification strategies of ZX-calculus.   In this work, we take the most generalized T-decomposition (namely vertex cutting), which achieves a poor efficiency of $α=1$, and identify common structures to which applying this can, after simplification via ZX-calculus rewriting, yield very strong effective efficiencies $α_\texteffłl1$. By taking into account this broader scope of the ZX-diagram and incorporating the simplification facilitated by the well-motivated cuts, we derive a handful of efficient T-decompositions whose applicabilities are relatively frequent. In benchmarking these new 'dynamic' decompositions against the existing alternatives, we observe a significant reduction in overall $α$ and hence overall runtime for classical simulation, particularly for certain common circuit classes.</description><author>Wira Azmoon Ahmad and Matthew Sutcliffe</author><pubDate>Sun, 22 Dec 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17182</guid></item><item><title>A Constant Measurement Quantum Algorithm for Graph Connectivity</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2411.15015</link><description>We introduce a novel quantum algorithm for determining graph connectedness using a constant number of measurements. The algorithm can be extended to find connected components with a linear number of measurements. It relies on non-unitary abelian gates taken from ZX calculus. Due to the fusion rule, the two-qubit gates correspond to a large single action on the qubits. The algorithm is general and can handle any undirected graph, including those with repeated edges and self-loops. The depth of the algorithm is variable, depending on the graph, and we derive upper and lower bounds. The algorithm exhibits a state decay that can be remedied with ancilla qubits. We provide a numerical simulation of the algorithm.</description><author>Maximilian Balthasar Mansky, Chonfai Kam and Claudia Linnhoff-Popien</author><pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2411.15015</guid></item></channel></rss>