<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 12:02:23 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Engineering CSS surgery: compiling any CNOT in any code</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01370</link><description>We introduce a framework for implementing logic in CSS-style quantum error correction codes, building on the surgery methods of Cowtan and Burton [CB24]. Our approach offers a systematic methodology for designing and analysing surgery protocols. At the physical level, we introduce the concept of subcodes, which encapsulate all the necessary data for performing surgery. At the logical level, leveraging homological algebra, subcodes enable us to track the logical operations induced by any surgery protocol, regardless of the choice of logical operator basis. In particular, we make no assumptions on the structure of the logical operators of the code, thereby eschewing the irreducibility assumption that has been necessary in other formulations of surgery for CSS codes [Coh+22; Cro+24; ZL24]. As a proof of concept, we develop a surgery protocol inspired by lattice surgery that implements a logical CNOT gate between any two logical qubits. Applicable to any CSS code, this protocol is highly versatile and facilitates the process of fault-tolerant design.</description><author>Clément Poirson, Joschka Roffe and Robert I. Booth</author><pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01370</guid></item><item><title>Clifford and Non-Clifford Splitting in Quantum Circuits: Applications and ZX-Calculus Detection Procedure</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16004</link><description>Classical simulation of quantum circuits is a pivotal part of the quantum computing landscape, specially within the NISQ era, where the constraints imposed by available hardware are unavoidable. The Gottesman-Knill theorem further motivates this argument by accentuating the importance of Clifford circuits and their role on this topic of simulation. In this work, we propose and analyze use cases that come from quantum circuits that can be written as product between a Clifford and a Non-Clifford unitary, these ranging from fully classical emulation, hybrid quantum-classical execution or even quantum algorithm simplification. To further complement this analysis, we make use of ZX-Calculus and its assets to detect a limiting border of these circuits that would allow for a separation between a Clifford section and a Non-Clifford section. To achieve this, we present a novel procedure for parsing ZX diagrams, that not only allows for the detection of this border but also simplifies the circuit extraction process.</description><author>Fernando Lima and Arcesio Castañeda Medina</author><pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16004</guid></item><item><title>Rapidly Trainable and Shallow-Compiled Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm for Maximum Likelihood Detection</title><link>https://dx.doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1016/j.physleta.2025.130541</link><description>In multiple-input and multiple-output (MIMO) systems, the maximum likelihood (ML) detection problem is NP-hard and becomes increasingly complex with more transmitting antennas and symbols. The quantum approximate optimization algorithm (QAOA), a leading candidate algorithm running in the noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices, can show quantum advantage for approximately solving combinatorial optimization problems. In this paper, we propose an improved QAOA based maximum likelihood detection. In the proposed scheme, we use ZX-calculus to prove the parameter symmetry in QAOA circuits, which can be used to reduce the search space and accelerate the training process. Moreover, to run QAOA on quantum devices, an improved qubit mapping method with simultaneous gate absorption is proposed, which can compile the quantum circuit of the QAOA to satisfy the connectivity constraints of real quantum devices with fewer CNOT counts. In numerical experiments, our scheme accelerates parameter training by an average of 29.8% and uses fewer CNOT gates and shallower circuit depth during compilation. This demonstrates that our scheme has significant advantages over the traditional scheme.</description><author>Yuxiang Liu, Yinuo Qian, Lu Wang, Zaichen Zhang and Xutao Yu</author><pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0375960125003214</guid></item><item><title>Fault-tolerant protocols through spacetime concatenation</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08918</link><description>We introduce a framework called spacetime concatenation for fault-tolerant compilation of syndrome extraction circuits of stabilizer codes. Spacetime concatenation enables efficient compilation of syndrome extraction circuits into dynamical codes through structured gadget layouts and encoding matrices, facilitating low-weight measurements while preserving logical information. Our framework uses conditions that are sufficient for fault-tolerance of the dynamical code, including not measuring logical operators and preserving the spacetime distance. We construct explicit examples of dynamical codes using this framework, including the dynamical bivariate bicycle code and a dynamical Haah code, while illustrating their fault-tolerant properties. Furthermore, we analyze the classification and resource trade-offs of dynamical codes, demonstrating their adaptability to hardware constraints, including fabrication defects and qubit dropout scenarios.</description><author>Yichen Xu and Arpit Dua</author><pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08918</guid></item><item><title>Optimizing Quantum Circuits via ZX Diagrams using Reinforcement Learning and Graph Neural Networks</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03429</link><description>Quantum computing is currently strongly limited by the impact of noise, in particular introduced by the application of two-qubit gates. For this reason, reducing the number of two-qubit gates is of paramount importance on noisy intermediate-scale quantum hardware. To advance towards more reliable quantum computing, we introduce a framework based on ZX calculus, graph-neural networks and reinforcement learning for quantum circuit optimization. By combining reinforcement learning and tree search, our method addresses the challenge of selecting optimal sequences of ZX calculus rewrite rules. Instead of relying on existing heuristic rules for minimizing circuits, our method trains a novel reinforcement learning policy that directly operates on ZX-graphs, therefore allowing us to search through the space of all possible circuit transformations to find a circuit significantly minimizing the number of CNOT gates. This way we can scale beyond hard-coded rules towards discovering arbitrary optimization rules. We demonstrate our method's competetiveness with state-of-the-art circuit optimizers and generalization capabilities on large sets of diverse random circuits.</description><author>Alexander Mattick, Maniraman Periyasamy, Christian Ufrecht, Abhishek Y. Dubey, Christopher Mutschler, Axel Plinge and Daniel D. Scherer</author><pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03429</guid></item><item><title>Exhaustive Search for Quantum Circuit Optimization using ZX Calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10983</link><description>Quantum computers allow a near-exponential speed-up for specific applications when compared to classical computers. Despite recent advances in the hardware of quantum computers, their practical usage is still severely limited due to a restricted number of available physical qubits and quantum gates, short coherence time, and high error rates. This paper lays the foundation towards a metric independent approach to quantum circuit optimization based on exhaustive search algorithms. This work uses depth-first search and iterative deepening depth-first search. We rely on ZX calculus to represent and optimize quantum circuits through the minimization of a given metric (e.g. the T-gate and edge count). ZX calculus formally guarantees that the semantics of the original circuit is preserved. As ZX calculus is a non-terminating rewriting system, we utilise a novel set of pruning rules to ensure termination while still obtaining high-quality solutions. We provide the first formalization of quantum circuit optimization using ZX calculus and exhaustive search. We extensively benchmark our approach on 100 standard quantum circuits. Finally, our implementation is integrated in the well-known libraries PyZX and Qiskit as a compiler pass to ensure applicability of our results.</description><author>Tobias Fischbach, Pierre Talbot and Pascal Bouvry</author><pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10983</guid></item><item><title>Bridging wire and gate cutting with ZX-calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11494</link><description>Quantum circuit cutting refers to a series of techniques that allow one to partition a quantum computation on a large quantum computer into several quantum computations on smaller devices. This usually comes at the price of a sampling overhead, that is quantified by the $1$-norm of the associated decomposition. The applicability of these techniques relies on the possibility of finding decompositions of the ideal, global unitaries into quantum operations that can be simulated onto each sub-register, which should ideally minimize the $1$-norm. In this work, we show how these decompositions can be obtained diagrammatically using ZX-calculus expanding on the work of Ufrecht et al. [arXiv:2302.00387]. The central idea of our work is that since in ZX-calculus only connectivity matters, it should be possible to cut wires in ZX-diagrams by inserting known decompositions of the identity in standard quantum circuits. We show how, using this basic idea, many of the gate decompositions known in the literature can be re-interpreted as an instance of wire cuts in ZX-diagrams. Furthermore, we obtain improved decompositions for multi-qubit controlled-Z (MCZ) gates with $1$-norm equal to $3$ for any number of qubits and any partition, which we argue to be optimal. Our work gives new ways of thinking about circuit cutting that can be particularly valuable for finding decompositions of large unitary gates. Besides, it sheds light on the question of why exploiting classical communication decreases the 1-norm of a wire cut but does not do so for certain gate decompositions. In particular, using wire cuts with classical communication, we obtain gate decompositions that do not require classical communication.</description><author>Marco Schumann, Tobias Stollenwerk and Alessandro Ciani</author><pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11494</guid></item><item><title>Graphical Stabilizer Decompositions for Multi-Control Toffoli Gate Dense Quantum Circuits</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03798</link><description>In this thesis, we study concepts in quantum computing using graphical languages, specifically using the ZX-calculus. The core of the research revolves around (graphical) stabilizer decompositions. The first major focus is on the decomposition of non-stabilizer states created from star edges. We discuss previous results and then present novel decompositions that yield a theoretical improvement. The second major focus is on weighting algorithms, applied to the special class of multi-control Toffoli gate dense quantum circuits. The representation of the corresponding gates is based on star edges. The applicability of known methods, such as CNOT-grouping, traditionally used for other classes, is examined in the context of this specific class. We then present a novel weighting algorithm that attempts to determine the best vertex to decompose. A refined version is implemented to simulate a known class of quantum querying algorithms, which is used to search for causal configurations of multiloop Feynman diagrams. For this case, as well as for a generalized benchmark consisting of randomly generated quantum circuits, we demonstrate occasional improvements in the final number of terms against traditional methods. These results are discussed by considering different simplification strategies. This thesis also provides a brief but broad outline of the important preliminaries.</description><author>Yves Vollmeier</author><pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03798</guid></item><item><title>Unveiling a Hidden Percolation Transition in Monitored Clifford Circuits: Inroads from ZX-Calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13211</link><description>We revisit the measurement-induced phase transition (MPT) in Clifford circuits, which are both classically simulable and exhibit critical behavior widely believed to be distinct from classical percolation theory, using ZX-calculus. We analyze the MPT in a dynamical model composed of CNOT, SWAP, identity gates, and Bell-pair measurements, respectively, arranged randomly in a brickwork pattern. Our circuits exhibit a transition that is seemingly distinct from classical percolation based on standard arguments, that is in line with the prevailing understanding in the field. In contrast, by employing ZX-calculus based simplification techniques, we unveil a hidden percolation transition within the circuit structure. Over a range of parameters tied to the probabilities for applying different gates, we demonstrate that the classical percolation transition in the ZX-simplified network coincides with the MPT observed through mutual information. Our findings suggest that the MPT in Clifford circuits is, in fact, controlled by a classical percolation transition in disguise.</description><author>Einat Buznach, Debanjan Chowdhury and Jonathan Ruhman</author><pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13211</guid></item><item><title>Diagrammatic Quantum Circuit Compression for Hamiltonian Simulation</title><link>https://dx.doi.org/10.18420/se2025-ws-24</link><description>One of the promising applications for early quantum computers is the simulation of of dynamical quantum systems. Due to the limited coherence time of such devices, the depth-compression of quantum circuits is crucial to facilitate useful results. It has been shown that certain quantum models can even be compressed to constant depth, meaning it is only linearly dependent on the number of qubits, but independent of the simulation time and the number of Trotter steps. This has been done by extracting the circuit structure derived from the model characteristics via Hamiltonian simulation. Based on these results, we present a diagrammatic approach to circuit compression utilizing a powerful technique for reasoning about quantum circuits called ZX-calculus. We demonstrate our approach by deriving constant-depth circuit compressions for quantum models known to be constant-depth, as well as novel models previously unstudied. Our method could serve as a first step toward the development of more advanced circuit compression methods, that could be employed to enable Hamiltonian simulation of a larger variety of quantum models, and beyond.</description><author>Victoria Wadewitz, Aaron Szasz, Daan Camps, Katherine Klymko and Tobias Stollenwerk</author><pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://dl.gi.de/items/55b8918c-cccd-4b39-9b57-889735ea1c31</guid></item></channel></rss>