<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 16:14:22 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Optimization and Synthesis of Quantum Circuits with Global Gates</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2507.20694</link><description>Compiling quantum circuits to account for hardware restrictions is an essential part of the quantum computing stack. Circuit compilation allows us to adapt algorithm descriptions into a sequence of operations supported by real quantum hardware, and has the potential to significantly improve their performance when optimization techniques are added to the process. One such optimization technique is reducing the number of quantum gates that are needed to execute a circuit. For instance, methods for reducing the number of non-Clifford gates or CNOT gates from a circuit is an extensive research area that has gathered significant interest over the years. For certain hardware platforms such as ion trap quantum computers, we can leverage some of their special properties to further reduce the cost of executing a quantum circuit in them. In this work we use global interactions, such as the Global Mølmer-Sørensen gate present in ion trap hardware, to optimize and synthesize quantum circuits. We design and implement an algorithm that is able to compile an arbitrary quantum circuit into another circuit that uses global gates as the entangling operation, while optimizing the number of global interactions needed. The algorithm is based on the ZX-calculus and uses an specialized circuit extraction routine that groups entangling gates into Global Mølmer-Sørensen gates. We benchmark the algorithm in a variety of circuits, and show how it improves their performance under state-of-the-art hardware considerations in comparison to a naive algorithm and the Qiskit optimizer.</description><author>Alejandro Villoria, Henning Basold and Alfons Laarman</author><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2507.20694</guid></item><item><title>Quantum Circuit Optimization Based on Dynamic Grouping and ZX-Calculus for Reducing 2-Qubit Gate Count</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14434</link><description>In the noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) era, two-qubit gates in quantum circuits are more susceptible to noise than single-qubit gates. Therefore, reducing the number of two-qubit gates is crucial for improving circuit efficiency and reliability. As quantum circuits scale up, the optimization search space becomes increasingly complex, leading to challenges such as low efficiency and suboptimal solutions. To address these issues, this paper proposes a quantum circuit optimization approach based on dynamic grouping and ZX-calculus. First, a random strategy-based dynamic grouping method partitions the circuit into multiple subcircuits. Second, a ZX-calculus guided k-step lookahead search performs equivalent subcircuit filtering to minimize two-qubit gate counts. Third, a delay-aware placement method optimizes the recombined circuit to reduce the overall gate count. Finally, simulated annealing iteratively updates the grouping strategy to achieve an optimized two-qubit gate count. Experimental results on benchmark datasets demonstrate the effectiveness and superiority of the proposed method in reducing two-qubit gates. Compared to the original circuits, the approach achieves an average reduction of 18% in two-qubit gates. It outperforms classical methods with up to 25% reduction, especially on gf circuits, and shows a 4% average improvement over heuristic ZX-calculus-based methods, validating its efficiency.</description><author>Kai Chen, Wen Liu, GuoSheng Xu, Yangzhi Li, Maoduo Li and Shouli He</author><pubDate>Sat, 19 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14434</guid></item><item><title>Growing Sparse Quantum Codes from a Seed</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13496</link><description>It is generally unclear whether smaller codes can be "concatenated" to systematically create quantum LDPC codes or their sparse subsystem code cousins where the degree of the Tanner graph remains bounded while increasing the code distance. In this work, we use a slight generalization of concatenation called conjoining introduced by the quantum lego formalism. We show that by conjoining only quantum repetition codes, one can construct quantum LDPC codes. More generally, we provide an efficient iterative algorithm for constructing sparse subsystem codes with a distance guarantee that asymptotically saturates $kd^2=O(n)$ in the worst case. Furthermore, we show that the conjoining of even just two-qubit quantum bit-flip and phase-flip repetition codes is quite powerful as they can create any CSS code. Therefore, more creative combinations of these basic code blocks will be sufficient for generating good quantum codes, including good quantum LDPC codes.</description><author>ChunJun Cao and Brad Lackey</author><pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13496</guid></item><item><title>Fault Tolerance by Construction</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17181</link><description>A key challenge in fault-tolerant quantum computing is synthesising and optimising circuits in a noisy environment, as traditional techniques often fail to account for the effect of noise on circuits. In this work, we propose a framework for designing fault-tolerant quantum circuits that are correct by construction. The framework starts with idealised specifications of fault-tolerant gadgets and refines them using provably sound basic transformations.   To reason about manipulating circuits while preserving their error correction properties, we define fault equivalence; two circuits are considered fault-equivalent if all undetectable faults on one circuit have a corresponding fault on the other. This guarantees that the effect of undetectable faults on both circuits is the same. We argue that fault equivalence is a concept that is already implicitly present in the literature. Many problems, such as state preparation and syndrome extraction, can be naturally expressed as finding an implementable circuit that is fault-equivalent to an idealised specification.   To utilize fault equivalence in a computationally tractable manner, we adapt the ZX calculus, a diagrammatic language for quantum computing. We restrict its rewrite system to not only preserve the underlying linear map but also fault equivalence, i.e. the circuit's behaviour under noise. Enabled by our framework, we verify, optimise and synthesise new and efficient circuits for syndrome extraction and cat state preparation. We anticipate that fault equivalence can capture and unify different approaches in fault-tolerant quantum computing, paving the way for an end-to-end circuit compilation framework.</description><author>Benjamin Rodatz, Boldizsár Poór and Aleks Kissinger</author><pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17181</guid></item><item><title>Blocklet concatenation: Low-overhead fault-tolerant protocols for fusion-based quantum computation</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13619</link><description>We introduce a construction for protocols for fault-tolerant quantum computing based on code concatenation and transversal gates. These protocols can be interpreted as families of quantum circuits of low-weight stabilizer measurements without strict locality constraints, effectively implementing concatenated codes. However, we primarily study these protocols in the context of photonic fusion-based quantum computing (FBQC), where they yield families of fusion networks with constant-sized resource states. Their high erasure thresholds relative to their resource-state cost establish them as promising candidates to replace surface codes in the context of FBQC. Examples include protocol families using 8-, 10- and 12-qubit resource states, with erasure thresholds of 13.8%, 19.1% and 11.5%, and footprint-per-logical-qubit scaling as $\mathcalO(d)$, $\mathcalO(d^1.46)$ and $\mathcalO(d^0.58)$, respectively, where $d$ is the code distance. We also present techniques for performing logical operations, decoding, and implementing the protocols in photonic hardware. Although we focus on photonic FBQC, these ideas may also be of interest in other settings.</description><author>Daniel Litinski</author><pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13619</guid></item><item><title>Roughening Transition in Quantum Circuits</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2506.11187</link><description>We explore a roughening phase transition that occurs in the entanglement dynamics of certain quantum circuits. Viewing entanglement as the free energy of a membrane in a circuit-defined random environment, there is a competition between membrane smoothing due to lattice pinning and roughening due to disorder in the circuit. In particular, we investigate the randomness-induced roughening transition of the entanglement membrane in a (3+1)-dimensional Clifford circuit model, by calculating the entanglement entropy for various bipartitions. We further construct a scaling theory for membranes tilted away from lattice planes, uncovering new scaling forms and a crossover to a previously unexplored critical "tilted regime".</description><author>Hyunsoo Ha, David A. Huse and Grace M. Sommers</author><pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2506.11187</guid></item><item><title>Optimizing State Preparation for Variational Quantum Regression on NISQ Hardware</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17713</link><description>The execution of quantum algorithms on modern hardware is often constrained by noise and qubit decoherence, limiting the circuit depth and the number of gates that can be executed. Circuit optimization techniques help mitigate these limitations, enhancing algorithm feasibility. In this work, we implement, optimize, and execute a variational quantum regression algorithm using a novel state preparation method. By leveraging ZX-calculus-based optimization techniques, such as Pauli pushing, phase folding, and Hadamard pushing, we achieve a more efficient circuit design. Our results demonstrate that these optimizations enable the successful execution of the quantum regression algorithm on current hardware. Furthermore, the techniques presented are broadly applicable to other quantum circuits requiring arbitrary real-valued state preparation, advancing the practical implementation of quantum algorithms.</description><author>Frans Perkkola, Ilmo Salmeperä, Arianne Meijer-van de Griend, C. -C. Joseph Wang, Ryan S. Bennink and Jukka K. Nurminen</author><pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17713</guid></item><item><title>Dynamical codes for hardware with noisy readouts</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07658</link><description>Dynamical stabilizer codes may offer a practical route to large-scale quantum computation. Such codes are defined by a schedule of error-detecting measurements, which allows for flexibility in their construction. In this work, we ask how best to optimise the measurement schedule of dynamically condensed colour codes in various limits of noise bias. We take a particular focus on the setting where measurements introduce more noise than unitary and idling operations - a noise model relevant to some hardware proposals. For measurement-biased noise models, we improve code performance by strategically repeating measurements within the schedule. For unbiased or $Z$-biased noise models, we find repeating measurements offers little improvement - somewhat contrary to our expectations - and investigate why this is. To perform this analysis, we generalise a metric called the teraquop footprint to the teraquop volume. This is the product of the number of qubits and number of rounds of measurements required such that the probability of a spacelike or timelike logical error occurring is less than $10^-12$. In most cases, we find differences in performance are primarily due to the number of rounds of measurements required, rather than the number of qubits - emphasising the importance of using the teraquop volume in the analysis. Additionally, our results provide another example of the importance of making use of correlated errors when decoding, in that using belief matching rather than minimum-weight perfect matching can turn a worst-performing code under a given noise model into a best-performing code.</description><author>Peter-Jan H. S. Derks, Alex Townsend-Teague, Jens Eisert, Markus S. Kesselring, Oscar Higgott and Benjamin J. Brown</author><pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07658</guid></item><item><title>From Fermions to Qubits: A ZX-Calculus Perspective</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06212</link><description>Mapping fermionic systems to qubits on a quantum computer is often the first step for algorithms in quantum chemistry and condensed matter physics. However, it is difficult to reconcile the many different approaches that have been proposed, such as those based on binary matrices, ternary trees, and stabilizer codes. This challenge is further exacerbated by the many ways to describe them -- transformation of Majorana operators, action on Fock states, encoder circuits, and stabilizers of local encodings -- making it challenging to know when the mappings are equivalent. In this work, we present a graphical framework for fermion-to-qubit mappings that streamlines and unifies various representations through the ZX-calculus.   To start, we present the correspondence between linear encodings of the Fock basis and phase-free ZX-diagrams. The commutation rules of scalable ZX-calculus allows us to convert the fermionic operators to Pauli operators under any linear encoding. Next, we give a translation from ternary tree mappings to scalable ZX-diagrams, which not only directly represents the encoder map as a CNOT circuit, but also retains the same structure as the tree. Consequently, we graphically prove that ternary tree transformations are equivalent to linear encodings, a recent result by Chiew et al. The scalable ZX representation moreover enables us to construct an algorithm to directly compute the binary matrix for any ternary tree mapping. Lastly, we present the graphical representation of local fermion-to-qubit encodings. Its encoder ZX-diagram has the same connectivity as the interaction graph of the fermionic Hamiltonian and also allows us to easily identify stabilizers of the encoding.</description><author>Haytham McDowall-Rose, Razin A. Shaikh and Lia Yeh</author><pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06212</guid></item><item><title>2D Quon Language: Unifying Framework for Cliffords, Matchgates, and Beyond</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06336</link><description>Simulating generic quantum states and dynamics is practically intractable using classical computers. However, certain special classes -- namely Clifford and matchgate circuits -- permit efficient computation. They provide invaluable tools for studying many-body physics, quantum chemistry, and quantum computation. While both play foundational roles across multiple disciplines, the origins of their tractability seem disparate, and their relationship remain unclear. A deeper understanding of such tractable classes could expand their scope and enable a wide range of new applications. In this work, we make progress toward the unified understanding of the Clifford and matchgate -- these two classes are, in fact, distinct special cases of a single underlying structure. Specifically, we introduce the 2D Quon language, which combines Majorana worldlines with their underlying spacetime topology to diagrammatically represent quantum processes and tensor networks. In full generality, the 2D Quon language is universal -- capable of representing arbitrary quantum states, dynamics, or tensor networks -- yet they become especially powerful in describing Clifford and matchgate classes. Each class can be efficiently characterized in a visually recognizable manner using the Quon framework. This capability naturally gives rise to several families of efficiently computable tensor networks introduced in this work: punctured matchgates, hybrid Clifford-matchgate-MPS, and ansatze generated from factories of tractable networks. All of these exhibit high non-Cliffordness, high non-matchgateness, and large bipartite entanglement entropy. We discuss a range of applications of our approach, from recovering well-known results such as the Kramers-Wannier duality and the star-triangle relation of the Ising model, to enabling variational optimization with novel ansatz states.</description><author>Byungmin Kang, Chen Zhao, Zhengwei Liu, Xun Gao and Soonwon Choi</author><pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06336</guid></item></channel></rss>