<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 14:37:21 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Graphical Symplectic Algebra</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2401.07914</link><description>We give complete presentations for the dagger-compact props of affine Lagrangian and coisotropic relations over an arbitrary field. This provides a unified family of graphical languages for both affinely constrained classical mechanical systems, as well as odd-prime-dimensional stabiliser quantum circuits. To this end, we present affine Lagrangian relations by a particular class of undirected coloured graphs. In order to reason about composite systems, we introduce a powerful scalable notation where the vertices of these graphs are themselves coloured by graphs. In the setting of stabiliser quantum mechanics, this scalable notation gives an extremely concise description of graph states, which can be composed via ``phased spider fusion.'' Likewise, in the classical mechanical setting of electrical circuits, we show that impedance matrices for reciprocal networks are presented in essentially the same way.</description><author>Robert I. Booth, Titouan Carette and Cole Comfort</author><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2401.07914</guid></item><item><title>Nonunitary gates using measurements only</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2312.17325</link><description>Measurement-based quantum computation (MBQC) is a universal platform to realize unitary gates, only using measurements which act on a pre-prepared entangled resource state. By deforming the measurement bases, as well as the geometry of the resource state, we show that MBQC circuits always transmit and act on the input state but generally realize nonunitary logical gates. In contrast to the stabilizer formalism which is often used for unitary gates, we find that ZX calculus is an ideal computation method of these nonunitary gates. As opposed to unitary gates, nonunitary gates can not be applied with certainty, due to the randomness of quantum measurements. We maximize the success probability of realizing nonunitary gates, and discuss applications including imaginary time evolution, which we demonstrate on a noisy intermediate scale quantum device.</description><author>Daniel Azses, Jonathan Ruhman and Eran Sela</author><pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2312.17325</guid></item><item><title>Graphical CSS Code Transformation Using ZX Calculus</title><link>https://uwspace.uwaterloo.ca/bitstream/handle/10012/20193/Li_SarahMeng.pdf?sequence=1&amp;isAllowed=y</link><description>In this work, we present a generic approach to transform CSS codes by building upon their equivalence to phase-free ZX diagrams. Using the ZX calculus, we demonstrate diagrammatic transformations between encoding maps associated with different codes. As a motivating example, we give explicit transformations between the Steane code and the quantum Reed-Muller code, since by switching between these two codes, one can obtain a fault-tolerant universal gate set. To this end, we propose a bidirectional rewrite rule to find a (not necessarily transversal) physical implementation for any logical ZX diagram in any CSS code. We then focus on two code transformation techniques: code morphing, a procedure that transforms a code while retaining its fault-tolerant gates, and gauge fixing, where complimentary codes can be obtained from a common subsystem code (e.g., the Steane and the quantum Reed-Muller codes from the J15, 1, 3, 3K code). We provide explicit graphical derivations for these techniques and show how ZX and graphical encoder maps relate several equivalent perspectives on these code-transforming operations</description><author>Sarah Meng Li</author><pubDate>Sat, 23 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://uwspace.uwaterloo.ca/bitstream/handle/10012/20193/Li_SarahMeng.pdf?sequence=1&amp;isAllowed=y</guid></item><item><title>The Geometry of Quantum Computing</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2312.14807</link><description>In this expository paper we present a brief introduction to the geometrical modeling of some quantum computing problems. After a brief introduction to establish the terminology, we focus on quantum information geometry and ZX-calculus, establishing a connection between quantum computing questions and quantum groups, i.e. Hopf algebras.</description><author>E. Ercolessi, R. Fioresi and T. Weber</author><pubDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2312.14807</guid></item><item><title>Reinforcement Learning Based Quantum Circuit Optimization via ZX-Calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2312.11597</link><description>We propose a novel Reinforcement Learning (RL) method for optimizing quantum circuits using the graph-like representation of a ZX-diagram. The agent, trained using the Proximal Policy Optimization (PPO) algorithm, employs Graph Neural Networks to approximate the policy and value functions. We test our approach for two differentiated circuit size regimes of increasing relevance, and benchmark it against the best-performing ZX-calculus based algorithm of the PyZX library, a state-of-the-art tool for circuit optimization in the field. We demonstrate that the agent can generalize the strategies learned from 5-qubit circuits to 20-qubit circuits of up to 450 Clifford gates, with enhanced compressions with respect to its counterpart while remaining competitive in terms of computational performance.</description><author>Jordi Riu, Jan Nogué, Gerard Vilaplana, Artur Garcia-Saez and Marta P. Estarellas</author><pubDate>Mon, 18 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2312.11597</guid></item><item><title>Quantum Picturalism: Learning Quantum Theory in High School</title><link>https://dx.doi.org/10.1109/QCE57702.2023.20321</link><description>Quantum theory is often regarded as challenging to learn and teach, with advanced mathematical prerequisites ranging from complex numbers and probability theory to matrix multiplication, vector space algebra and symbolic manipulation within the Hilbert space formalism. It is traditionally considered an advanced undergraduate or graduate-level subject.   In this work, we challenge the conventional view by proposing "Quantum Picturalism" as a new approach to teaching the fundamental concepts of quantum theory and computation. We establish the foundations and methodology for an ongoing educational experiment to investigate the question "From what age can students learn quantum theory if taught using a diagrammatic approach?". We anticipate that the primary benefit of leveraging such a diagrammatic approach, which is conceptually intuitive yet mathematically rigorous, will be eliminating some of the most daunting barriers to teaching and learning this subject while enabling young learners to reason proficiently about high-level problems. We posit that transitioning from symbolic presentations to pictorial ones will increase the appeal of STEM education, attracting more diverse audience.</description><author>Selma Dündar-Coecke, Lia Yeh, Caterina Puca, Sieglinde M. -L. Pfaendler, Muhammad Hamza Waseem, Thomas Cervoni, Aleks Kissinger, Stefano Gogioso and Bob Coecke</author><pubDate>Wed, 06 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2312.03653</guid></item><item><title>Causal flow preserving optimisation of quantum circuits in the ZX-calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2312.02793</link><description>Optimising quantum circuits to minimise resource usage is crucial, particularly in the context of near term hardware which is limited by quantum volume. This paper introduces an optimisation algorithm which aims to minimise non-Clifford gate count and two-qubit gate count by building on ZX-calculus-based strategies. By translating a circuit into a ZX-diagram it can be simplified before being extracted back into a circuit. I assert that simplifications preserve a graph-theoretic property called causal flow. This has the advantage that qubit lines are well defined throughout, permitting a trivial extraction procedure and in turn enabling the calculation of an individual transformation's impact on the resulting circuit. A general procedure for a decision strategy is introduced, inspired by an existing heuristic based method. Both phase teleportation and the neighbour unfusion rule are generalised. In particular, allowing unfusion of multiple neighbours is shown to lead to significant improvements in optimisation. When run on a set of benchmark circuits, the algorithm developed reduces the two-qubit gate count by an average of 19.6%, beating both the previous best ZX-based strategy (14.2%) and non-ZX strategy (18.9%). This lays a foundation for multiple avenues of improvement. A particularly effective strategy for optimising QFT circuits is also noted, resulting in exactly one two-qubit gate per non-Clifford gate.</description><author>Calum Holker</author><pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2312.02793</guid></item><item><title>Optimizing ZX-Diagrams with Deep Reinforcement Learning</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2311.18588</link><description>ZX-diagrams are a powerful graphical language for the description of quantum processes with applications in fundamental quantum mechanics, quantum circuit optimization, tensor network simulation, and many more. The utility of ZX-diagrams relies on a set of local transformation rules that can be applied to them without changing the underlying quantum process they describe. These rules can be exploited to optimize the structure of ZX-diagrams for a range of applications. However, finding an optimal sequence of transformation rules is generally an open problem. In this work, we bring together ZX-diagrams with reinforcement learning, a machine learning technique designed to discover an optimal sequence of actions in a decision-making problem and show that a trained reinforcement learning agent can significantly outperform other optimization techniques like a greedy strategy or simulated annealing. The use of graph neural networks to encode the policy of the agent enables generalization to diagrams much bigger than seen during the training phase.</description><author>Maximilian Nägele and Florian Marquardt</author><pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2311.18588</guid></item><item><title>VyZX: Formal Verification of a Graphical Quantum Language</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2311.11571</link><description>Mathematical representations of graphs often resemble adjacency matrices or lists, representations that facilitate whiteboard reasoning and algorithm design. In the realm of proof assistants, inductive representations effectively define semantics for formal reasoning. This highlights a gap where algorithm design and proof assistants require a fundamentally different structure of graphs, particularly for process theories which represent programs using graphs. To address this gap, we present VyZX, a verified library for reasoning about inductively defined graphical languages. These inductive constructs arise naturally from category theory definitions. A key goal for VyZX is to Verify the ZX-calculus, a graphical language for reasoning about quantum computation. The ZX-calculus comes with a collection of diagrammatic rewrite rules that preserve the graph's semantic interpretation. We show how inductive graphs in VyZX are used to prove the correctness of the ZX-calculus rewrite rules and apply them in practice using standard proof assistant techniques. VyZX integrates easily with the proof engineer's workflow through visualization and automation.</description><author>Adrian Lehmann, Ben Caldwell, Bhakti Shah and Robert Rand</author><pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2311.11571</guid></item><item><title>Minimal Equational Theories for Quantum Circuits</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2311.07476</link><description>We introduce the first minimal and complete equational theory for quantum circuits. Hence, we show that any true equation on quantum circuits can be derived from simple rules, all of them being standard except a novel but intuitive one which states that a multi-control $2π$ rotation is nothing but the identity. Our work improves on the recent complete equational theories for quantum circuits, by getting rid of several rules including a fairly unpractical one. One of our main contributions is to prove the minimality of the equational theory, i.e. none of the rules can be derived from the other ones. More generally, we demonstrate that any complete equational theory on quantum circuits (when all gates are unitary) requires rules acting on an unbounded number of qubits. Finally, we also simplify the complete equational theories for quantum circuits with ancillary qubits and/or qubit discarding.</description><author>Alexandre Clément, Noé Delorme and Simon Perdrix</author><pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2311.07476</guid></item></channel></rss>