<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 11:32:39 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Optimization of fault-tolerant quantum computing by the ZX-calculus</title><link>https://inspirehep.net/files/1b9b518d03054c5810e04caaa89b6626</link><description>This thesis tackles some of these compilation challenges in the context of large-scale quantum computing. We present efficient algorithms, automated procedures, and formal methods for optimizing fault-tolerant quantum computing. To achieve this, we utilize a wide range of models for representing quantum computation, spanning from abstract formalisms to low-level representations. These models include high-level representations of some quantum operators, the quantum circuit model, and the ZX-calculus, a rigorous graphical language developed for reasoning about quantum processes. Using these diverse representations allows us to design optimization strategies that target different levels of abstraction in the quantum compilation pipeline, thereby contributing to the development of a comprehensive and performant compilation toolchain for fault-tolerant quantum computing.
The results of this thesis are presented in the order in which they would intervene in this compilation toolchain, following the natural flow from high-level quantum operations to hardwareexecutable instructions. The first step considered is quantum circuit synthesis. A quantum circuit is a model for quantum computation that represents quantum operations as a sequence of elementary operations called quantum gates and measurements. These quantum gates are the building blocks of quantum computation, analogous to classical logic gates but operating on quantum bits (qubits). While some classical gates, like AND and OR, perform irreversible operations on classical bits, quantum gates are unitary operations that reversibly transform quantum states. They can create and manipulate quantum phenomena such as superposition and entanglement, which have no classical counterparts. The process of quantum circuit synthesis consists in translating abstract quantum operations, often expressed in mathematical form, into sequences of elementary quantum gates. The synthesis phase establishes the baseline implementation that will serve as input to subsequent optimization procedures.</description><author>Vivien Vandaele</author><pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://inspirehep.net/files/1b9b518d03054c5810e04caaa89b6626</guid></item><item><title>Lattice surgery with Bell measurements: Modular fault-tolerant quantum computation at low entanglement cost</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13541</link><description>Modular architectures are a promising approach to scaling quantum computers to fault tolerance. Small, low-noise quantum processors connected through relatively noisy quantum links are capable of fault-tolerant operation as long as the noise can be confined to the interface. Finding protocols that implement the quantum links between modules as efficiently as possible is essential because inter-module entanglement is challenging to produce at a similar rate and fidelity as local entanglement. We introduce a protocol for lattice surgery on surface codes in which all non-local operations are Bell measurements. The protocol simultaneously confines the link noise and requires only half as many module-crossing gates as previously proposed protocols. To mitigate distance-reducing hook errors, we introduce a strategy of alternating the gate sequence between rounds of syndrome measurement, which prevents multiple hooks from simultaneously aligning with a logical operator in the code. We evaluate our protocol's performance when two logical qubits on separate modules are prepared in a logical Bell state. Circuit-level simulations under depolarizing noise show that the logical error suppression for a given entanglement rate between modules is consistently stronger compared to the best-performing alternative protocols for a wide range of link noise, with a typical 40% entanglement resource saving for a constant logical error rate. Our approach to protocol design is applicable to any quantum circuit that must be divided across processor modules and can therefore guide development of resource-efficient modular quantum computation beyond the surface code.</description><author>Trond Hjerpekjøn Haug, Timo Hillmann, Anton Frisk Kockum and Raphaël Van Laer</author><pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13541</guid></item><item><title>Nonlinear photonic architecture for fault-tolerant quantum computing</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06890</link><description>We propose a novel architecture for fault-tolerant quantum computing that incorporates strong single-photon nonlinearities into a photonic GHZ-measurement-based architecture. The nonlinearities substantially reduce resource overheads compared to conventional linear-optics-based architectures, which require significant redundancy to accommodate probabilistic photon generation and probabilistic entangling operations. By removing linear-optical failure modes, our nonlinear architecture can also tolerate much higher optical losses than linear approaches, with a baseline loss tolerance of $∼$12% using a 32-photon resource state and a foliated surface code. Our results show how introducing a nonlinear primitive enables dramatic improvements in practical implementations of fault-tolerant quantum computing.</description><author>Maike Ostmann, Joshua Nunn and Alex Jones</author><pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06890</guid></item><item><title>A Review on Quantum Circuit Optimization using ZX-Calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20663</link><description>Quantum computing promises significant speed-ups for certain algorithms but the practical use of current noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) era computers remains limited by resources constraints (e.g., noise, qubits, gates, and circuit depth). Quantum circuit optimization is a key mitigation strategy. In this context, ZX-calculus has emerged as an alternative framework that allows for semantics-preserving quantum circuit optimization.   We review ZX-based optimization of quantum circuits, categorizing them by optimization techniques, target metrics and intended quantum computing architecture. In addition, we outline critical challenges and future research directions, such as multi-objective optimization, scalable algorithms, and enhanced circuit extraction methods. This survey is valuable for researchers in both combinatorial optimization and quantum computing. For researchers in combinatorial optimization, we provide the background to understand a new challenging combinatorial problem: ZX-based quantum circuit optimization. For researchers in quantum computing, we classify and explain existing circuit optimization techniques.</description><author>Tobias Fischbach, Pierre Talbot and Pascal Bourvry</author><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20663</guid></item><item><title>How to simulate magic state cultivation with around $8$ Clifford terms on average</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08658</link><description>Building upon [arXiv:2509.01224], we present a sketch on how to simulate the non-Clifford $d=5$ magic state cultivation circuits [arXiv:2409.17595] with a sum of $≈ 8$ Clifford ZX-diagrams on average, at $0.1%$ noise. Compared to a magic cat state stabiliser decomposition of all $53$ non-Clifford spiders ($6,377,292$ terms required), this is more than $7 \times 10^5$ times reduction in the number of terms. Our stabiliser decomposition has the advantage of representing the final non-Clifford state (in light of circuit errors) as a sum of Clifford ZX-diagrams. This will be useful in simulating the escape stage of magic state cultivation, where one need to port the resultant state of cultivation into a larger Clifford circuit with many more qubits. Still, it's necessary to only track $≈ 8$ Clifford terms. Our result sheds light on the simulability of operationally relevant, high $T$-count quantum circuits with some internal structure.</description><author>Kwok Ho Wan and Zhenghao Zhong</author><pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08658</guid></item><item><title>Quantum architecture search with neural predictor based on ZX-calculus</title><link>https://dx.doi.org/10.1140/epjqt/s40507-025-00410-w</link><description>With the ongoing advances in noisy intermediate-scale quantum hardware, variational quantum algorithms have demonstrated significant potential in a range of quantum applications. However, obtaining high-performance, shallow-parameterized quantum circuits typically requires repeated optimization of the gate parameters over a large set of candidate circuits, resulting in prohibitively high evaluation costs. To address this challenge, this study proposes a novel predictor-based quantum architecture search (PQAS-ZX) method that leverages ZX-calculus. In this approach, a quantum circuit is first represented as a ZX diagram that supports multi-step equivalent simplifications at the diagram level. By applying these equivalence transformations, multiple circuit variants that share the same performance metric are generated, thereby significantly expanding the training dataset and enhancing the ability of the predictor to manage diverse circuit structures. ZX diagrams offer more flexible characterizations of multi-qubit entanglement and phase interactions, as well as higher-level equivalent transformations, compared with the state-of-the-art predictor-based quantum architecture search with graph measures (PQAS-GM). Numerical simulations of three variational quantum eigensolver tasks, namely the transverse-field Ising, Heisenberg, and BeH2 molecular models, demonstrated that PQAS-ZX required only approximately 80.9%, 82.9%, and 76.1% of the queries required by PQAS-GM, respectively, to achieve the same probability of reaching the target ground-state energy. These results highlight the advantage of using ZX diagrams to identify high-quality circuits efficiently and alleviate the evaluation burden of quantum architecture searches.</description><author>Shanchuan Li, Daisuke Tsukayama, Jun-ichi Shirakashi, Tetsuo Shibuya and Hiroshi Imai</author><pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://epjquantumtechnology.springeropen.com/articles/10.1140/epjqt/s40507-025-00410-w</guid></item><item><title>Cutting stabiliser decompositions of magic state cultivation with ZX-calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01224</link><description>We apply the cutting stabiliser decomposition techniques [arXiv:2403.10964] to the quantum states generated from magic state cultivation [arXiv:2409.17595], post-selected upon all $+1$ measured values for simplicity. The resultant states to the $d=3$ and $d=5$ variant magic state cultivation circuits can be expressed as a sum of $4$ and $8$ Clifford ZX-digrams respectively. Modifications to existing ZX-calculus stabiliser decomposition methods may enable better simulation of non-Clifford circuits containing a moderate number of $T$ gates in the context of quantum error correction.</description><author>Kwok Ho Wan and Zhenghao Zhong</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01224</guid></item><item><title>Inserting Planar-Measured Qubits into MBQC Patterns while Preserving Flow</title><link>https://dx.doi.org/10.4204/EPTCS.426.4</link><description>In the one-way model of measurement-based quantum computation (MBQC), computation proceeds via single-qubit measurements on a resource state. Flow conditions ensure that the overall computation is deterministic in a suitable sense, and are required for efficient translation into quantum circuits. Procedures that rewrite MBQC patterns – e.g. for optimisation, or adapting to hardware constraints – thus need to preserve the existence of flow. Most previous work has focused on rewrites that reduce the number of qubits in the computation, or that introduce new Pauli-measured qubits. Here, we consider the insertion of planar-measured qubits into MBQC patterns, i.e. arbitrary measurements in a plane of the Bloch sphere spanned by a pair of Pauli operators; such measurements are necessary for universal MBQC. We extend the definition of causal flow, previously restricted to XY -measurements only, to also permit YZ-measurements and derive the conditions under which a YZ-insertion preserves causal flow. Then we derive conditions for YZ-insertion into patterns with gflow or Pauli flow, in which case the argument straightforwardly extends to XZ-insertions as well. We also show that the 'vertex splitting' or 'neighbour unfusion' rule previously used in the literature can be derived from YZ-insertion and pivoting. This work contributes to understanding the broad properties of flow-preserving rewriting in MBQC and in the ZX-calculus more broadly, and it will enable more efficient optimisation, obfuscation, or routing.</description><author>Miriam Backens and Thomas Perez</author><pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14671</guid></item><item><title>String Diagrams for Defect-Based Surface Code Computing</title><link>https://dx.doi.org/10.4204/EPTCS.426.6</link><description>Surface codes are a popular choice for implementing fault-tolerant quantum computing. Two-qubit gates may be realised in these codes using only nearest-neighbour interactions, either by lattice surgery or by braiding defects around each other. The effect of lattice surgery operations may be simply described using the ZX-calculus: a graphical language that has proven effective for program design and optimisation. In this work, we formalise a similar description via the ZX-calculus of defect braiding, as it is conventionally described. We define a graphical calculus KNOT, denoting the logical effects (in the absence of byproduct operations) of defect braiding in surface codes: we show how these effects may be described via a fragment of ZX-calculus which we call the (0, pi)-fragment. We then use a doubling construction to define a subtheory of KNOT, more specialised to standard encoding techniques in the defect braiding literature. Within this subtheory, we encompass standard braiding techniques by families of ribbon-like and tangle-like diagrams, each with semantics distinct from KNOT, in terms of the (0, pi)-fragment of ZX diagrams (again in the absence of byproducts). These subtheories may be used interoperably, and are each sound and complete for the (0, pi)-fragment of ZX diagrams. This provides a starting point to use the formal diagrammatics to analyse the operational effects of defect braiding procedures.</description><author>Mateusz Kupper, Dominic Horsman, Chris Heunen and Niel de Beaudrap</author><pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14672</guid></item><item><title>Novel Methods for Classical Simulation of Quantum Circuits via ZX-Calculus</title><link>https://ora.ox.ac.uk/objects/uuid:54d6e7f4-b845-4275-98cd-cf6749530d9b/files/d9s1616869</link><description>With the limitations of today’s 'NISQ era' quantum hardware, classical simulation of quantum computations is an essential tool for understanding the quantum advantage and optimising quantum algorithms and systems. However, without the features unique to quantum computers, simulating such computations with classical hardware is (believed to be) a necessarily inefficient endeavour. For a general class of quantum circuits, any classical simulator requires a resource overhead which grows exponentially with one metric or another. Two notable and widely used techniques are tensor contraction and stabiliser decomposition. The former suffers from both space and time complexities that scale exponentially with the interconnectedness (or treewidth) of the circuit, while the latter is limited by a time complexity that scales exponentially with the number of 'non-Clifford' gates in the circuit. Recent years have seen the graphical language of ZX-calculus applied to this problem, with a particular growing body of research utilising its benefits to discover more efficient stabiliser decompositions. This in turn reduces the growth rate of the exponential time complexity, thereby rendering ever larger and more complex quantum circuits classically simulable. This thesis expands upon this literature by presenting various new techniques and approaches by which the ZX-calculus may be used to classically simulate quantum circuits with improved efficiencies. This work includes a new perspective on optimising stabiliser decomposition strategies, focusing on improved heuristics and decomposition patterns rather than on discovering wholly new decompositions. Also included is extensive use of GPU hardware to parallelise the workload, particularly used in conjunction with a parameterisation of the ZX-calculus which allows large sets of similar circuits to be reasoned upon as single entities. Lastly, this thesis features a hybrid method of classical simulation which leverages of the strengths of both tensor contraction and stabiliser decomposition approaches, optimising a balance between these techniques. Ultimately, the chapters ahead demonstrate how these new techniques can greatly increase the scope of classical simulation by reducing the runtime of this task by orders of magnitude and providing a foundation for further research.</description><author>Matthew Sutcliffe</author><pubDate>Sun, 10 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ora.ox.ac.uk/objects/uuid:54d6e7f4-b845-4275-98cd-cf6749530d9b/files/d9s1616869</guid></item></channel></rss>