<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 15:55:43 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Graph Rewriting Language as a Platform for Quantum Diagrammatic Calculi</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15581</link><description>Systematic discovery of optimization paths in quantum circuit simplification remains a challenge. Today, ZX-calculus, a computing model for quantum circuit transformation, is attracting attention for its highly abstract graph-based approach. Whereas existing tools such as PyZX and Quantomatic offer domain-specific support for quantum circuit optimization, visualization and theorem-proving, we present a complementary approach using LMNtal, a general-purpose hierarchical graph rewriting language, to establish a diagrammatic transformation and verification platform with model checking. Our methodology shows three advantages: (1) manipulation of ZX-diagrams through native graph transformation rules, enabling direct implementation of basic rules; (2) quantified pattern matching via QLMNtal extensions, greatly simplifying rule specification; and (3) interactive visualization and validation of optimization paths through state space exploration. Through case studies, we demonstrate how our framework helps understand optimization paths and design new algorithms and strategies. This suggests that the declarative language LMNtal and its toolchain could serve as a new platform to investigate quantum circuit transformation from a different perspective.</description><author>Kayo Tei, Haruto Mishina, Naoki Yamamoto and Kazunori Ueda</author><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15581</guid></item><item><title>ZX-DB: A Graph Database for Quantum Circuit Simplification and Rewriting via the ZX-Calculus</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13033</link><description>Quantum computing is an emerging computational paradigm with the potential to outperform classical computers in solving a variety of problems. To achieve this, quantum programs are typically represented as quantum circuits, which must be optimized and adapted for target hardware through quantum circuit compilation. We introduce ZX-DB, a data-driven system that performs quantum circuit simplification and rewriting inside a graph database using ZX-calculus, a complete graphical formalism for quantum mechanics. ZX-DB encodes ZX-calculus rewrite rules as standard openCypher queries and executes them on an example graph database engine, Memgraph, enabling efficient, database-native transformations of large-scale quantum circuits. ZX-DB integrates correctness validation via tensor and graph equivalence checks and is evaluated against the state-of-the-art PyZX framework. Experimental results show that ZX-DB achieves up to an order-of-magnitude speedup for independent rewrites, while exposing pattern-matching bottlenecks in current graph database engines. By uniting quantum compilation and graph data management, ZX-DB opens a new systems direction toward scalable, database-supported quantum computing pipelines.</description><author>Valter Uotila, Cong Yu and Bo Zhao</author><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13033</guid></item><item><title>Ultra Low Overhead Syndrome Extraction for the Steane code</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13700</link><description>We establish a new performance benchmark for the fault-tolerant syndrome extraction of [[7, 1, 3]] Steane code with a dynamic protocol. Our method is built on two highly optimized circuits derived using fault-equivalent ZX-rewrites: a primary fault-tolerant circuit with 14 CNOTs and an efficient non-fault-tolerant recovery circuit with 11 CNOTs. The protocol uses an adaptive response to internal faults, discarding flagged measurements and falling back to the recovery circuit to correct potentially detrimental errors. Monte Carlo simulations confirm the efficiency of our protocol, reducing the logical error rate per cycle by an average of ~14.3% relative to the optimized Steane method [arXiv:2506.17181] and ~17.7% compared to the Reichardt's three-qubit method [arXiv:1804.06995], the leading prior techniques.</description><author>Boldizsár Poór, Benjamin Rodatz and Aleks Kissinger</author><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13700</guid></item><item><title>Simulating Clifford Circuits with Gaussian Elimination</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06127</link><description>Quantum circuits are considered more powerful than classical circuits and require exponential resources to simulate classically. Clifford circuits are a special class of quantum circuits that can be simulated in polynomial time but still show important quantum effects such as entanglement. In this work, we present an algorithm that simulates Clifford circuits by performing Gaussian elimination on a modified adjacency matrix derived from the circuit structure. Our work builds on an ZX-calculus tensor network representation of Clifford circuits that reduces to quantum graph states. We give a concise formula of amplitudes of graph states based on the LDL decomposition of matrices over GF(2), and use it to get efficient algorithms for strong and weak simulation of Clifford circuits using tree-decomposition-based fast LDL algorithm. The complexity of our algorithm matches the state of art for weak graph state simulation and improves the state of art for strong graph state simulation by taking advantage of Strassen-like fast matrix multiplication. Our algorithm is also efficient when computing many amplitudes or samples of a Clifford circuit. Further, our amplitudes formula provides a new characterization of locally Clifford equivalent graph states as well as an efficient protocol to learn graph states with low-rank adjacency matrices.</description><author>Yuchen Pang and Edgar Solomonik</author><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06127</guid></item><item><title>Beyond Penrose tensor diagrams with the ZX calculus: Applications to quantum computing, quantum machine learning, condensed matter physics, and quantum gravity</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06012</link><description>We introduce the Spin-ZX calculus as an elevation of Penrose's diagrams and associated binor calculus to the level of a formal diagrammatic language. The power of doing so is illustrated by the variety of scientific areas we apply it to: permutational quantum computing, quantum machine learning, condensed matter physics, and quantum gravity. Respectively, we analyse permutational computing transition amplitudes, evaluate barren plateaus for SU(2) symmetric ansätze, study properties of AKLT states, and derive the minimum quantised volume in loop quantum gravity.   Our starting point is the mixed-dimensional ZX calculus, a purely diagrammatic language that has been proven to be complete for finite-dimensional Hilbert spaces. That is, any equation that can be derived in the Hilbert space formalism, can also be derived in the mixed-dimensional ZX calculus. We embed the Spin-ZX calculus inside the mixed-dimensional ZX calculus, rendering it a quantum information flavoured diagrammatic language for the quantum theory of angular momentum, i.e. SU(2) representation theory. We diagrammatically derive the fundamental spin coupling objects - such as Clebsch-Gordan coefficients, symmetrising mappings between qubits and spin spaces, and spin Hamiltonians - under this embedding.   Our results establish the Spin-ZX calculus as a powerful tool for representing and computing with SU(2) systems graphically, offering new insights into foundational relationships and paving the way for new diagrammatic algorithms for theoretical physics.</description><author>Quanlong Wang, Richard East, Razin Shaikh, Lia Yeh, Boldizsár Poór and Bob Coecke</author><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06012</guid></item><item><title>Optimization of fault-tolerant quantum computing by the ZX-calculus</title><link>https://inspirehep.net/files/1b9b518d03054c5810e04caaa89b6626</link><description>This thesis tackles some of these compilation challenges in the context of large-scale quantum computing. We present efficient algorithms, automated procedures, and formal methods for optimizing fault-tolerant quantum computing. To achieve this, we utilize a wide range of models for representing quantum computation, spanning from abstract formalisms to low-level representations. These models include high-level representations of some quantum operators, the quantum circuit model, and the ZX-calculus, a rigorous graphical language developed for reasoning about quantum processes. Using these diverse representations allows us to design optimization strategies that target different levels of abstraction in the quantum compilation pipeline, thereby contributing to the development of a comprehensive and performant compilation toolchain for fault-tolerant quantum computing.
The results of this thesis are presented in the order in which they would intervene in this compilation toolchain, following the natural flow from high-level quantum operations to hardwareexecutable instructions. The first step considered is quantum circuit synthesis. A quantum circuit is a model for quantum computation that represents quantum operations as a sequence of elementary operations called quantum gates and measurements. These quantum gates are the building blocks of quantum computation, analogous to classical logic gates but operating on quantum bits (qubits). While some classical gates, like AND and OR, perform irreversible operations on classical bits, quantum gates are unitary operations that reversibly transform quantum states. They can create and manipulate quantum phenomena such as superposition and entanglement, which have no classical counterparts. The process of quantum circuit synthesis consists in translating abstract quantum operations, often expressed in mathematical form, into sequences of elementary quantum gates. The synthesis phase establishes the baseline implementation that will serve as input to subsequent optimization procedures.</description><author>Vivien Vandaele</author><pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://inspirehep.net/files/1b9b518d03054c5810e04caaa89b6626</guid></item><item><title>Lattice surgery with Bell measurements: Modular fault-tolerant quantum computation at low entanglement cost</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13541</link><description>Modular architectures are a promising approach to scaling quantum computers to fault tolerance. Small, low-noise quantum processors connected through relatively noisy quantum links are capable of fault-tolerant operation as long as the noise can be confined to the interface. Finding protocols that implement the quantum links between modules as efficiently as possible is essential because inter-module entanglement is challenging to produce at a similar rate and fidelity as local entanglement. We introduce a protocol for lattice surgery on surface codes in which all non-local operations are Bell measurements. The protocol simultaneously confines the link noise and requires only half as many module-crossing gates as previously proposed protocols. To mitigate distance-reducing hook errors, we introduce a strategy of alternating the gate sequence between rounds of syndrome measurement, which prevents multiple hooks from simultaneously aligning with a logical operator in the code. We evaluate our protocol's performance when two logical qubits on separate modules are prepared in a logical Bell state. Circuit-level simulations under depolarizing noise show that the logical error suppression for a given entanglement rate between modules is consistently stronger compared to the best-performing alternative protocols for a wide range of link noise, with a typical 40% entanglement resource saving for a constant logical error rate. Our approach to protocol design is applicable to any quantum circuit that must be divided across processor modules and can therefore guide development of resource-efficient modular quantum computation beyond the surface code.</description><author>Trond Hjerpekjøn Haug, Timo Hillmann, Anton Frisk Kockum and Raphaël Van Laer</author><pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13541</guid></item><item><title>Completeness for Fault Equivalence of Clifford ZX Diagrams</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08477</link><description>Two circuits are considered to be equivalent under noise if the effect of faults on one circuit is no worse than the effect of faults on the other circuit. We call this relationship fault equivalence. Fault equivalence offers a way to transform circuits while provably preserving their fault-tolerant properties, enabling a framework for fault-tolerant circuit synthesis and optimisation that is correct by construction. The ZX calculus, a set of graphical rewrite rules for quantum computations, provides a useful tool for manipulating circuits while preserving fault equivalence. For this, the usual set of ZX rewrites has to be restricted to not only preserve the underlying linear map represented by the diagram but also fault equivalence.   In this work, we provide a set of ZX rewrites that are sound and complete for fault equivalence of Clifford ZX diagrams. This means that any equivalence that can be derived using the proposed rules is certain to be correct, and any correct equivalence can be derived using only these rules. For this, we utilise diagrammatic constructions called fault gadgets to reason about arbitrary, possibly correlated Pauli faults in ZX diagrams. Fault gadgets allow us to separate the diagram into a fault-free part, which captures the noise-free behaviour of a diagram, and a noisy part that enumerates the effects of all possible faults. Using this, we provide a unique normal form for ZX diagrams under noise and show that any diagram can be brought into this normal form using our proposed rule set.</description><author>Maximilian Rüsch, Benjamin Rodatz and Aleks Kissinger</author><pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08477</guid></item><item><title>Nonlinear photonic architecture for fault-tolerant quantum computing</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06890</link><description>We propose a novel architecture for fault-tolerant quantum computing that incorporates strong single-photon nonlinearities into a photonic GHZ-measurement-based architecture. The nonlinearities substantially reduce resource overheads compared to conventional linear-optics-based architectures, which require significant redundancy to accommodate probabilistic photon generation and probabilistic entangling operations. By removing linear-optical failure modes, our nonlinear architecture can also tolerate much higher optical losses than linear approaches, with a baseline loss tolerance of $∼$12% using a 32-photon resource state and a foliated surface code. Our results show how introducing a nonlinear primitive enables dramatic improvements in practical implementations of fault-tolerant quantum computing.</description><author>Maike Ostmann, Joshua Nunn and Alex Jones</author><pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06890</guid></item><item><title>A Review on Quantum Circuit Optimization using ZX-Calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20663</link><description>Quantum computing promises significant speed-ups for certain algorithms but the practical use of current noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) era computers remains limited by resources constraints (e.g., noise, qubits, gates, and circuit depth). Quantum circuit optimization is a key mitigation strategy. In this context, ZX-calculus has emerged as an alternative framework that allows for semantics-preserving quantum circuit optimization.   We review ZX-based optimization of quantum circuits, categorizing them by optimization techniques, target metrics and intended quantum computing architecture. In addition, we outline critical challenges and future research directions, such as multi-objective optimization, scalable algorithms, and enhanced circuit extraction methods. This survey is valuable for researchers in both combinatorial optimization and quantum computing. For researchers in combinatorial optimization, we provide the background to understand a new challenging combinatorial problem: ZX-based quantum circuit optimization. For researchers in quantum computing, we classify and explain existing circuit optimization techniques.</description><author>Tobias Fischbach, Pierre Talbot and Pascal Bourvry</author><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20663</guid></item></channel></rss>