<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Apr 2024 14:16:06 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Zero-temperature entanglement membranes in quantum circuits</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02975</link><description>In chaotic quantum systems, the entanglement of a region $A$ can be described in terms of the surface tension of a spacetime membrane pinned to the boundary of $A$. Here, we interpret the tension of this entanglement membrane in terms of the rate at which information "flows" across it. For any orientation of the membrane, one can define (generically nonunitary) dynamics across the membrane; we explore this dynamics in various space-time translation-invariant (STTI) stabilizer circuits in one and two spatial dimensions. We find that the flux of information across the membrane in these STTI circuits reaches a steady state. In the cases where this dynamics is nonunitary and the steady state flux is nonzero, this occurs because the dynamics across the membrane is unitary in a subspace of extensive entropy. This generalized unitarity is present in a broad class of STTI stabilizer circuits, and is also present in some special non-stabilizer models. The existence of multiple unitary (or generalized unitary) directions forces the entanglement membrane tension to be a piecewise linear function of the orientation of the membrane; in this respect, the entanglement membrane behaves like an interface in a zero-temperature classical lattice model. We argue that entanglement membranes in random stabilizer circuits that produce volume-law entanglement are also effectively at zero temperature.</description><author>Grace M. Sommers, Sarang Gopalakrishnan, Michael J. Gullans and David A. Huse</author><pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02975</guid></item><item><title>Measurement-Based Quantum Approximate Optimization</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11514</link><description>Parameterized quantum circuits are attractive candidates for potential quantum advantage in the near term and beyond. At the same time, as quantum computing hardware not only continues to improve but also begins to incorporate new features such as mid-circuit measurement and adaptive control, opportunities arise for innovative algorithmic paradigms. In this work we focus on measurement-based quantum computing protocols for approximate optimization, in particular related to quantum alternating operator ansätze (QAOA), a popular quantum circuit model approach to combinatorial optimization. For the construction and analysis of our measurement-based protocols we demonstrate that diagrammatic approaches, specifically ZX-calculus and its extensions, are effective for adapting such algorithms to the measurement-based setting. In particular we derive measurement patterns for applying QAOA to the broad and important class of QUBO problems. We further outline how for constrained optimization, hard problem constraints may be directly incorporated into our protocol to guarantee the feasibility of the solution found and avoid the need for dealing with penalties. Finally we discuss the resource requirements and tradeoffs of our approach to that of more traditional quantum circuits.</description><author>Tobias Stollenwerk and Stuart Hadfield</author><pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11514</guid></item><item><title>Multi-controlled Phase Gate Synthesis with ZX-calculus applied to Neutral Atom Hardware</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10864</link><description>Quantum circuit synthesis describes the process of converting arbitrary unitary operations into a gate sequence of a fixed universal gate set, usually defined by the operations native to a given hardware platform. Most current synthesis algorithms are designed to synthesize towards a set of single qubit rotations and an additional entangling two qubit gate, such as CX, CZ, or the Molmer Sorensen gate. However, with the emergence of neutral atom based hardware and their native support for gates with more than two qubits, synthesis approaches tailored to these new gate sets become necessary. In this work, we present an approach to synthesize multi controlled phase gates using ZX calculus. By representing quantum circuits as graph like ZX diagrams, one can utilize the distinct graph structure of diagonal gates to identify multi controlled phase gates inherently present in some quantum circuits even if none were explicitly defined in the original circuit. We evaluate the approach on a wide range of benchmark circuits and compare them to the standard Qiskit synthesis regarding its circuit execution time for neutral atom based hardware with native support of multi controlled gates. Our results show possible advantages for current state of the art hardware and represent the first exact synthesis algorithm supporting arbitrary sized multi controlled phase gates.</description><author>Korbinian Staudacher, Ludwig Schmid, Johannes Zeiher, Robert Wille and Dieter Kranzlmüller</author><pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10864</guid></item><item><title>Procedurally Optimised ZX-Diagram Cutting for Efficient T-Decomposition in Classical Simulation</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10964</link><description>A quantum circuit may be strongly classically simulated with the aid of ZX-calculus by decomposing its $t$ T-gates into a sum of $2^α t$ classically computable stabiliser terms. In this paper, we introduce a general procedure to find an optimal pattern of vertex cuts in a ZX-diagram to maximise its T-count reduction at the cost of the fewest cuts. Rather than reducing a Clifford+T diagram based on a fixed routine of decomposing its T-gates directly (as is the conventional approach), we focus instead on taking advantage of certain patterns and structures common to such circuits to, in effect, design by automatic procedure an arrangement of spider decompositions that is optimised for the particular circuit. In short, this works by assigning weights to vertices based on how many T-like gates they are blocking from fusing/cancelling and then appropriately propagating these weights through any neighbours which are then blocking weighted vertices from fusing, and so on. Ultimately, this then provides a set of weightings on relevant nodes, which can then each be cut, starting from the highest weighted down. While this is a heuristic approach, we show that, for circuits small enough to verify, this method achieves the most optimal set of cuts possible $71%$ of the time. Furthermore, there is no upper bound for the efficiency achieved by this method, allowing, in principle, an effective decomposition efficiency $αi̊ghtarrow0$ for highly structured circuits. Even applied to random pseudo-structured circuits (produced from CNOTs, phase gates, and Toffolis), we record the number of stabiliser terms required to reduce all T-gates, via our method as compared to that of the more conventional T-decomposition approaches (with $α≈0.47$), and show consistent improvements of orders of magnitude, with an effective efficiency $0.1łesssimαłesssim0.2$.</description><author>Matthew Sutcliffe and Aleks Kissinger</author><pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10964</guid></item><item><title>Complete equational theories for classical and quantum Gaussian relations</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10479</link><description>We give generators and relations for the hypergraph props of Gaussian relations and positive affine Lagrangian relations. The former extends Gaussian probabilistic processes by completely-uninformative priors, and the latter extends Gaussian quantum mechanics with infinitely-squeezed states. These presentations are given by adding a generator to the presentation of real affine relations and of real affine Lagrangian relations which freely codiscards effects, as well as certain rotations.   The presentation of positive affine Lagrangian relations provides a rigorous justification for many common yet informal calculations in the quantum physics literature involving infinite-squeezing. Our presentation naturally extends Menicucci et al.'s graph-theoretic representation of Gaussian quantum states with a representation for Gaussian transformations. We interpret the LOv-calculus, a diagrammatic calculus for reasoning about passive linear-optical quantum circuits in our presentation of positive affine Lagrangian relations. Moreover, we show how our presentation allows for additional optical operations such as active squeezing.</description><author>Robert I. Booth, Titouan Carette and Cole Comfort</author><pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10479</guid></item><item><title>Fast classical simulation of quantum circuits via parametric rewriting in the ZX-calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06777</link><description>The ZX-calculus is an algebraic formalism that allows quantum computations to be simplified via a small number of simple graphical rewrite rules. Recently, it was shown that, when combined with a family of "sum-over-Cliffords" techniques, the ZX-calculus provides a powerful tool for classical simulation of quantum circuits. However, for several important classical simulation tasks, such as computing the probabilities associated with many measurement outcomes of a single quantum circuit, this technique results in reductions over many very similar diagrams, where much of the same computational work is repeated. In this paper, we show that the majority of this work can be shared across branches, by developing reduction strategies that can be run parametrically on diagrams with boolean free parameters. As parameters only need to be fixed after the bulk of the simplification work is already done, we show that it is possible to perform the final stage of classical simulation quickly utilising a high degree of GPU parallelism. Using these methods, we demonstrate speedups upwards of 100x for certain classical simulation tasks vs. the non-parametric approach.</description><author>Matthew Sutcliffe and Aleks Kissinger</author><pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06777</guid></item><item><title>A Complete Graphical Language for Linear Optical Circuits with Finite-Photon-Number Sources and Detectors</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2402.17693</link><description>Linear optical circuits can be used to manipulate the quantum states of photons as they pass through components including beam splitters and phase shifters. Those photonic states possess a particularly high level of expressiveness, as they reside within the bosonic Fock space, an infinite-dimensional Hilbert space. However, in the domain of linear optical quantum computation, these basic components may not be sufficient to efficiently perform all computations of interest, such as universal quantum computation. To address this limitation it is common to add auxiliary sources and detectors, which enable projections onto auxiliary photonic states and thus increase the versatility of the processes. In this paper, we introduce the $\textbfLO_fi$-calculus, a graphical language to reason on the infinite-dimensional bosonic Fock space with circuits composed of four core elements of linear optics: the phase shifter, the beam splitter, and auxiliary sources and detectors with bounded photon number. We present an equational theory that we prove to be complete: two $\textbfLO_fi$-circuits represent the same quantum process if and only if one can be transformed into the other with the rules of the $\textbfLO_fi$-calculus. We give a unique and compact universal form for such circuits.</description><author>Nicolas Heurtel</author><pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2402.17693</guid></item><item><title>All graph state verification protocols are composably secure</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2402.01445</link><description>Graph state verification protocols allow multiple parties to share a graph state while checking that the state is honestly prepared, even in the presence of malicious parties. Since graph states are the starting point of numerous quantum protocols, it is crucial to ensure that graph state verification protocols can safely be composed with other protocols, this property being known as composable security. Previous works [YDK21] conjectured that such a property could not be proven within the abstract cryptography framework: we disprove this conjecture by showing that all graph state verification protocols can be turned into a composably secure protocol with respect to the natural functionality for graph state preparation. Moreover, we show that any unchanged graph state verification protocols can also be considered as composably secure for a slightly different, yet useful, functionality. Finally, we show that these two results are optimal, in the sense that any such generic result, considering arbitrary black-box protocols, must either modify the protocol or consider a different functionality.   Along the way, we show a protocol to generalize entanglement swapping to arbitrary graph states that might be of independent interest.</description><author>Léo Colisson, Damian Markham and Raja Yehia</author><pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2402.01445</guid></item><item><title>Minimality in Finite-Dimensional ZW-Calculi</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2401.16225</link><description>The ZW-calculus is a graphical language capable of representing 2-dimensional quantum systems (qubit) through its diagrams, and manipulating them through its equational theory. We extend the formalism to accommodate finite dimensional Hilbert spaces beyond qubit systems. First we define a qudit version of the language, where all systems have the same arbitrary finite dimension d, and show that the provided equational theory is both complete -- i.e. semantical equivalence is entirely captured by the equations -- and minimal -- i.e. none of the equations are consequences of the others. We then extend the graphical language further to accommodate all finite dimensional Hilbert spaces at the same time. We again show the completeness of the provided equational theory.</description><author>Marc de Visme and Renaud Vilmart</author><pubDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2401.16225</guid></item><item><title>Optimal compilation of parametrised quantum circuits</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2401.12877</link><description>Parametrised quantum circuits contain phase gates whose phase is determined by a classical algorithm prior to running the circuit on a quantum device. Such circuits are used in variational algorithms like QAOA and VQE. In order for these algorithms to be as efficient as possible it is important that we use the fewest number of parameters. We show that, while the general problem of minimising the number of parameters is NP-hard, when we restrict to circuits that are Clifford apart from parametrised phase gates and where each parameter is used just once, we can efficiently find the optimal parameter count. We show that when parameter transformations are required to be sufficiently well-behaved that the only rewrites that reduce parameters correspond to simple 'fusions'. Using this we find that a previous circuit optimisation strategy by some of the authors [Kissinger, van de Wetering. PRA (2019)] finds the optimal number of parameters. Our proof uses the ZX-calculus. We also prove that the standard rewrite rules of the ZX-calculus suffice to prove any equality between parametrised Clifford circuits.</description><author>John van de Wetering, Richie Yeung, Tuomas Laakkonen and Aleks Kissinger</author><pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2401.12877</guid></item></channel></rss>