<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2023 13:22:16 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>The Algebra for Stabilizer Codes</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.10584</link><description>There is a bijection between odd prime dimensional qudit pure stabilizer states modulo invertible scalars and affine Lagrangian subspaces of finite dimensional symplectic $픽_p$-vector spaces. In the language of the stabilizer formalism, full rank stabilizer tableaus are exactly the bases for affine Lagrangian subspaces. This correspondence extends to an isomorphism of props where the composition of stabilizer circuits becomes the relational composition of affine subspaces and the tensor product becomes the direct sum. In this paper, we extend this correspondence between stabilizer circuits and tableaus to the mixed setting; by regarding stabilizer codes as affine coisotropic susbspaces (again only in odd prime qudit dimension/for qubit CSS codes). We show that by splitting the projector for a stabilizer code we recover the error detection protocol and the error correction protocol with affine classical processing power.</description><author>Cole Comfort</author><pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.10584</guid></item><item><title>A ZX-Calculus Approach to Concatenated Graph Codes</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.08363</link><description>Quantum Error-Correcting Codes (QECCs) are vital for ensuring the reliability of quantum computing and quantum communication systems. Among QECCs, stabilizer codes, particularly graph codes, have attracted considerable attention due to their unique properties and potential applications. Concatenated codes, whichcombine multiple layers of quantum codes, offer a powerful technique for achieving high levels of error correction with a relatively low resource overhead. In this paper, we examine the concatenation of graph codes using the powerful and versatile graphical language of ZX-calculus. We establish a correspondence between the encoding map and ZX-diagrams, and provide a simple proof of the equivalence between encoding maps in the Pauli X basis and the graphic operation "generalized local complementation" (GLC) as previously demonstrated in [J. Math. Phys. 52, 022201]. Our analysis reveals that the resulting concatenated code remains a graph code only when the encoding qubits of the same inner code are not directly connected. When they are directly connected, additional Clifford operations are necessary to transform the concatenated code into a graphcode, thus generalizing the results in [J. Math. Phys. 52, 022201]. We further explore concatenated graph codesin different bases, including the examination of holographic codes as concatenated graph codes. Our findings showcase the potential of ZX-calculus in advancing the field of quantum error correction.</description><author>Zipeng Wu, Song Cheng and Bei Zeng</author><pubDate>Mon, 17 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.08363</guid></item><item><title>Flow-preserving ZX-calculus rewrite rules for optimisation and obfuscation</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.08166</link><description>In the one-way model of measurement-based quantum computation (MBQC), computation proceeds via measurements on a resource state. So-called flow conditions ensure that the overall computation is deterministic in a suitable sense, with Pauli flow being the most general of these. Computations, represented as measurement patterns, may be rewritten to optimise resource use and for other purposes. Such rewrites need to preserve the existence of flow to ensure the new pattern can still be implemented deterministically. The majority of existing work in this area has focused on rewrites that reduce the number of qubits, yet it can be beneficial to increase the number of qubits for certain kinds of optimisation, as well as for obfuscation.   In this work, we introduce several ZX-calculus rewrite rules that increase the number of qubits and preserve the existence of Pauli flow. These rules can be used to transform any measurement pattern into a pattern containing only (general or Pauli) measurements within the XY-plane. We also give the first flow-preserving rewrite rule that allows measurement angles to be changed arbitrarily, and use this to prove that the `neighbour unfusion' rule of Staudacher et al. preserves the existence of Pauli flow. This implies it may be possible to reduce the runtime of their two-qubit-gate optimisation procedure by removing the need to regularly run the costly gflow-finding algorithm.</description><author>Tommy McElvanney and Miriam Backens</author><pubDate>Mon, 17 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.08166</guid></item><item><title>Simple ZX and ZH calculi for arbitrary finite dimensions, via discrete integrals</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.03310</link><description>The ZX calculus and the ZH calculus use diagrams to denote and to compute properties of quantum operations, and other multi-linear operators described by tensor networks. These calculi involve 'rewrite rules', which are algebraic manipulations of the tensor networks through transformations of diagrams. The way in which diagrams denote tensor networks is through a semantic map, which assigns a meaning to each diagram in a compositional way. Slightly different semantic maps, which may prove more convenient for one purpose or another (e.g., analysing unitary circuits versus analysing counting complexity), give rise to slightly different rewrite systems. Through a simple application of measure theory on discrete sets, we describe a semantic map for ZX and ZH diagrams for qudits of any dimension D&gt;1, well-suited to represent unitary circuits, and admitting simple rewrite rules. In doing so, we reproduce the 'well-tempered' semantics of [arXiv:2006.02557] for ZX and ZH diagrams in the case D=2. We demonstrate rewrite rules for the 'stabiliser fragment' of the ZX calculus and a 'multicharacter fragment' of the ZH calculus; and demonstrate relationships which would allow the two calculi to be used interoperably as a single 'ZXH calculus'.</description><author>Niel de Beaudrap and Richard D. P. East</author><pubDate>Thu, 06 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.03310</guid></item><item><title>Picturing counting reductions with the ZH-calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.02524</link><description>Counting the solutions to Boolean formulae defines the problem #SAT, which is complete for the complexity class #P. We use the ZH-calculus, a universal and complete graphical language for linear maps which naturally encodes counting problems in terms of diagrams, to give graphical reductions from #SAT to several related counting problems. Some of these graphical reductions, like to #2SAT, are substantially simpler than known reductions via the matrix permanent. Additionally, our approach allows us to consider the case of counting solutions modulo an integer on equal footing. Finally, since the ZH-calculus was originally introduced to reason about quantum computing, we show that the problem of evaluating ZH-diagrams in the fragment corresponding to the Clifford+T gateset, is in $FP^#P$. Our results show that graphical calculi represent an intuitive and useful framework for reasoning about counting problems.</description><author>Tuomas Laakkonen, Konstantinos Meichanetzidis and John van de Wetering</author><pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.02524</guid></item><item><title>A recursively partitioned approach to architecture-aware ZX Polynomial synthesis and optimization</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.17366</link><description>The synthesis of quantum circuits from phase gadgets in the ZX-calculus facilitates quantum circuit optimization. Our work provides an alternative formulation for the architecture-aware synthesis algorithm of PauliOpt by replacing the stochastic approach of PauliOpt with a heuristic based search and utilizes a divide and conquer method to synthesize an optimized circuit from a ZX polynomial. We provide a comparison of our algorithm with PauliOpt and other state-of-the-art optimization libraries. While we note poorer performance for highly structured circuits, as in the QAOA formulation for Max-Cut, we demonstrate a significant advantage for randomized circuits, which highlights the advantages of utilizing an architecture-aware methodology.</description><author>David Winderl, Qunsheng Huang and Christian B. Mendl</author><pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.17366</guid></item><item><title>The Zeta Calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.17399</link><description>We propose a quantum programming language that generalizes the $łambda$-calculus. The language is non-linear; duplicated variables denote, not cloning of quantum data, but sharing a qubit's state; that is, producing an entangled pair of qubits whose amplitudes are identical with respect to a chosen basis. The language has two abstraction operators, $ζ$ and $ξ$, corresponding to the Z- and X-bases; each abstraction operator is also parameterised by a phase, indicating a rotation that is applied to the input before it is shared. We give semantics for the language in the ZX-calculus and prove its equational theory sound. We show how this language can provide a good representation of higher-order functions in the quantum world.</description><author>Nicklas Botö and Fabian Forslund</author><pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.17399</guid></item><item><title>Unifying flavors of fault tolerance with the ZX calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08829</link><description>There are several models of quantum computation which exhibit shared fundamental fault-tolerance properties. This article makes commonalities explicit by presenting these different models in a unifying framework based on the ZX calculus. We focus on models of topological fault tolerance - specifically surface codes - including circuit-based, measurement-based and fusion-based quantum computation, as well as the recently introduced model of Floquet codes. We find that all of these models can be viewed as different flavors of the same underlying stabilizer fault-tolerance structure, and sustain this through a set of local equivalence transformations which allow mapping between flavors. We anticipate that this unifying perspective will pave the way to transferring progress among the different views of stabilizer fault-tolerance and help researchers familiar with one model easily understand others.</description><author>Hector Bombin, Daniel Litinski, Naomi Nickerson, Fernando Pastawski and Sam Roberts</author><pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08829</guid></item><item><title>Modular decoding: parallelizable real-time decoding for quantum computers</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.04846</link><description>Universal fault-tolerant quantum computation will require real-time decoding algorithms capable of quickly extracting logical outcomes from the stream of data generated by noisy quantum hardware. We propose modular decoding, an approach capable of addressing this challenge with minimal additional communication and without sacrificing decoding accuracy. We introduce the edge-vertex decomposition, a concrete instance of modular decoding for lattice-surgery style fault-tolerant blocks which is remarkably effective. This decomposition of the global decoding problem into sub-tasks mirrors the logical-block-network structure of a fault-tolerant quantum circuit. We identify the buffering condition as a key requirement controlling decoder quality; it demands a sufficiently large separation (buffer) between a correction committed by a decoding sub-task and the data unavailable to it. We prove that the fault distance of the protocol is preserved if the buffering condition is satisfied. Finally, we implement edge-vertex modular decoding and apply it on a variety of quantum circuits, including the Clifford component of the 15-to-1 magic-state distillation protocol. Monte Carlo simulations on a range of buffer sizes provide quantitative evidence that buffers are both necessary and sufficient to guarantee decoder accuracy. Our results show that modular decoding meets all the practical requirements necessary to support real-world fault-tolerant quantum computers.</description><author>Héctor Bombín, Chris Dawson, Ye-Hua Liu, Naomi Nickerson, Fernando Pastawski and Sam Roberts</author><pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.04846</guid></item><item><title>Simple Complete Equational Theories for Quantum Circuits with Ancillae or Partial Trace</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.03117</link><description>Although quantum circuits have been ubiquitous for decades in quantum computing, the first complete equational theory for quantum circuits has only recently been introduced. Completeness guarantees that any true equation on quantum circuits can be derived from the equational theory. Our contribution is twofold: (i) We simplify this equational theory by proving that several rules can be derived from the remaining ones. In particular, two out of the three most intricate rules are removed, the third one being slightly simplified. (ii) We extend the complete equational theory to quantum circuits with ancillae or qubit discarding, to represent respectively quantum computations using an additional workspace, and hybrid quantum computations. We show that the remaining intricate rule can be greatly simplified in these more expressive settings. The development of simple and complete equational theories for expressive quantum circuit models opens new avenues for reasoning about quantum circuits. It provides strong formal foundations for various compiling tasks such as circuit optimisation, hardware constraint satisfaction and verification.</description><author>Alexandre Clément, Noé Delorme, Simon Perdrix and Renaud Vilmart</author><pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.03117</guid></item></channel></rss>