<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 10:52:20 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Dynamic T-decomposition for classical simulation of quantum circuits</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17182</link><description>It is known that a quantum circuit may be simulated with classical hardware via stabilizer state (T-)decomposition in $O(2^α t)$ time, given $t$ non-Clifford gates and a decomposition efficiency $α$. The past years have seen a number of papers presenting new decompositions of lower $α$ to reduce this runtime and enable simulation of ever larger circuits. More recently, it has been demonstrated that well placed applications of apparently weaker (higher $α$) decompositions can in fact result in better overall efficiency when paired with the circuit simplification strategies of ZX-calculus.   In this work, we take the most generalized T-decomposition (namely vertex cutting), which achieves a poor efficiency of $α=1$, and identify common structures to which applying this can, after simplification via ZX-calculus rewriting, yield very strong effective efficiencies $α_\texteffłl1$. By taking into account this broader scope of the ZX-diagram and incorporating the simplification facilitated by the well-motivated cuts, we derive a handful of efficient T-decompositions whose applicabilities are relatively frequent. In benchmarking these new 'dynamic' decompositions against the existing alternatives, we observe a significant reduction in overall $α$ and hence overall runtime for classical simulation, particularly for certain common circuit classes.</description><author>Wira Azmoon Ahmad and Matthew Sutcliffe</author><pubDate>Sun, 22 Dec 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17182</guid></item><item><title>Towards Faster Quantum Circuit Simulation Using Graph Decompositions, GNNs and Reinforcement Learning</title><link>https://openreview.net/pdf?id=54060pbCKY</link><description>In this work, we train a graph neural network with reinforcement learning to more efficiently simulate quantum circuits using the ZX-calculus. Our experiments show a marked improvement in simulation efficiency using the trained model over existing methods that do not incorporate AI. In this way, we demonstrate a machine learning model that can reason effectively within a mathematical framework such that it enhances scientific research in the important domain of quantum computing.</description><author>Alex Koziell-Pipe, Richie Yeung and Matthew Sutcliffe</author><pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://openreview.net/pdf?id=54060pbCKY</guid></item><item><title>Floquetifying stabiliser codes with distance-preserving rewrites</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17240</link><description>The ZX calculus is a graphical language for representing and rewriting quantum circuits. While its graphical rewrite rules preserve semantics, they may not preserve other features. For example, applying rewrites to a circuit that implements an error-correcting code can change its distance. Here, we define the notion of distance-preserving rewrites that enables the transformation of error-correcting codes without changing their distance. Using these rewrites, we propose an algorithm that transforms a high-weight Pauli measurement into an equivalent quantum circuit with only single- and two-qubit operations. Since we only use distance-preserving rewrites, we guarantee that errors in the low-weight implementation do not propagate to create multiple data errors. Going further, we generalise the Floquetification procedure of [arXiv:2308.15489] to arbitrary stabiliser codes. Given a stabiliser code, we synthesise a new quantum error-correcting code which encodes the same number of qubits with at least the same distance. The number of additional qubits this method requires is linearly dependent on the weight or the largest Pauli measurement. This creates a tradeoff between easily implementable low-weight Pauli measurements at the cost of additional physical qubits.</description><author>Benjamin Rodatz, Boldizsár Poór and Aleks Kissinger</author><pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17240</guid></item><item><title>Dynamical weight reduction of Pauli measurements</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12527</link><description>Many routines that one might want to run on a quantum computer can benefit from adaptive circuits, relying on mid-circuit measurements and feed-forward operations. Any such measurement has to be compiled into a sequence of elementary gates involving only a small number of qubits. In this work, we formalize dynamical weight reduction (DWR) schemes in which a high-weight Pauli measurement is decomposed into a sequence of measurements of smaller weight at the cost of adding additional auxiliary qubits. We first present our main method, deforming a ZX diagram that represents the measurement we want to compile. We then construct a general recipe that constructs a DWR on a given connectivity whenever the underlying connectivity graph fulfills certain necessary conditions. Further, we construct a family of DWR schemes using a given number of auxiliary qubits with indications that the schemes we present are optimal in terms of spacetime resource overheads needed for a DWR. We highlight three examples that achieve a constant time or a constant space overhead, respectively. Finally, we discuss different trade-offs of space and time overhead and how they might be chosen differently on different levels of abstraction within a (fault-tolerant) quantum computation. This work showcases the flexibility in compiling a measurement circuit in terms of lower-weight measurements using deformations of ZX diagrams and can find applications in quantum error correction, quantum simulation as well as near-term quantum computing tasks where the quality of a computation highly depends on the physical implementation of a given logical operation.</description><author>Julio C. Magdalena de la Fuente</author><pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12527</guid></item><item><title>Generalized flow for hypergraph measurement patterns</title><link>https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/vanijcken-thesis.pdf</link><description>This dissertation explores the development of an analogue to generalized flow (gflow) for hypergraph measurement patterns using the ZH-calculus framework. The ZH-calculus, extends the ZX-calculus by efficiently describing Toffoli gates and multi-controlled Z gates. While the ZX-calculus and its gflow conditions are well-understood for graph states, no such analogue exists for hypergraphs. This dissertation establishes a necessary and sufficient condition for hypergraph measurement patterns to be deterministic. The new gflow criteria, analogous to those in graphs but adapted for hypergraphs, ensure that corrections are available for potential undesired measurements that may occur during execution of a measurement pattern.</description><author>Martin van IJcken</author><pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/vanijcken-thesis.pdf</guid></item><item><title>Categorical quantum theory and percolation methods for measurement-based quantum computing</title><link>https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/george-thesis.pdf</link><description>This dissertation explores the development of an analogue to generalized flow (gflow) for hypergraph measurement patterns using the ZH-calculus framework. The ZH-calculus, extends the ZX-calculus by efficiently describing Toffoli gates and multi-controlled Z gates. While the ZX-calculus and its gflow conditions are well-understood for graph states, no such analogue exists for hypergraphs. This dissertation establishes a necessary and sufficient condition for hypergraph measurement patterns to be deterministic. The new gflow criteria, analogous to those in graphs but adapted for hypergraphs, ensure that corrections are available for potential undesired measurements that may occur during execution of a measurement pattern.</description><author>Joe Bacchus George</author><pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/george-thesis.pdf</guid></item><item><title>Fusion and flow: formal protocols to reliably build photonic graph states</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.13541</link><description>Photonics offers a promising platform for implementations of measurement-based quantum computing. Recently proposed fusion-based architectures aim to achieve universality and fault-tolerance. In these approaches, computation is carried out by performing fusion and single-qubit measurements on a resource graph state. The verification of these architectures requires linear algebraic, probabilistic, and control flow structures to be combined in a unified formal language. This paper develops a framework for photonic quantum computing by bringing together linear optics, ZX calculus, and dataflow programming. We characterize fusion measurements that induce Pauli errors and show that they are correctable using a novel flow structure for fusion networks. We prove the correctness of new repeat-until-success protocols for the realization of arbitrary fusions and provide a graph-theoretic proof of universality for linear optics with entangled photon sources. The proposed framework paves the way for the development of compilation algorithms for photonic quantum computing.</description><author>Giovanni de Felice, Boldizsár Poór, Lia Yeh and William Cashman</author><pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.13541</guid></item><item><title>Parallel Quantum Circuit Extraction from MBQC-Patterns</title><link>https://dx.doi.org/10.1109/IPDPSW63119.2024.00179</link><description>In the model of measurement-based quantum computing (MBQC), computations are performed via sequential measurements on a highly entangled graph state. MBQC is a natural model for photonic quantum computing and has been shown to be useful for tasks like optimization and verification of general quantum computations. Therefore, it is often necessary to translate between MBQC and the predominantly used quantum circuit model in a fast and reliable way. While there are algorithms with linear complexity to extract quantum circuits from measurement patterns using additional ancilla qubits, efficient ancilla-free extraction has shown to be more costly. We develop strategies to parallelize an existing extraction algorithm based on ZX-calculus by exploiting the graph structure of measurement patterns and evaluate the performance on patterns obtained from a benchmark set of quantum circuits. Our results suggest that possible parallelization speedups are closely related to the graph structure of a pattern.</description><author>Marcel Quanz, Korbinian Staudacher and Karl Fürlinger</author><pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/stamp/stamp.jsp?arnumber=10596505&amp;casa_token=IvO5I8HAAmsAAAAA:s1XrQZcpF079508i5_tYXIbnybpxOWLWMuGULR-iMG0gI6LUZh9bw2OHBsaAOUYTySpqIi-jHwo&amp;tag=1</guid></item><item><title>Smarter k-Partitioning of ZX-Diagrams for Improved Quantum Circuit Simulation</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.00828</link><description>We introduce a novel method for strong classical simulation of quantum circuits based on optimally k-partitioning ZX-diagrams, reducing each part individually, and then efficiently cross-referencing their results to conclude the overall probability amplitude of the original circuit. We then analyse how this method fares against the alternatives for circuits of various size, shape, and interconnectedness and demonstrate how it is often liable to outperform those alternatives in speed by orders of magnitude.</description><author>Matthew Sutcliffe</author><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.00828</guid></item><item><title>Magic of the Heisenberg Picture</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16047</link><description>Magic quantifies the non-Clifford operations required for preparing a state on quantum processors and sets bounds on the classical computational complexity of simulating quantum dynamics. We study a magic resource theory for operators, which is dual to that describing states. We identify that the stabilizer Rényi entropy analog in operator space is a good magic monotone satisfying the usual conditions, while inheriting efficient computability properties and providing a tight lower-bound to the minimum number of non-Clifford gates in a circuit. It is operationally well-defined as quantifying how well one can approximate an operator with one that has only few Pauli strings; analogous to the relation between entanglement entropy and tensor-network truncation. An immediate advantage is that the operator stabilizer entropies exhibit inherent locality through a Lieb-Robinson bound, making them particularly suited for studying local dynamic magic generation in many-body systems. We compute this quantity analytically in two distinct regimes. First, we show that random evolution or circuits typically have approximately maximal magic in the Heisenberg picture for all R\ńyi indices, and evaluate the Page correction. Second, harnessing both dual unitarity and ZX graphical calculus, we compute the operator stabilizer entropy evolution for an interacting integrable XXZ circuit. In this case, magic quickly saturates to a constant; a distinct Heisenberg picture phenomena and suggestive of a connection to integrability. We argue that this efficiently computable operator magic monotone reveals structural properties of many-body magic generation, and can inspire novel Clifford-assisted tensor network methods.</description><author>Neil Dowling, Pavel Kos and Xhek Turkeshi</author><pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16047</guid></item></channel></rss>