<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 15:00:30 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Minimality in Finite-Dimensional ZW-Calculi</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2401.16225</link><description>The ZW-calculus is a graphical language capable of representing 2-dimensional quantum systems (qubit) through its diagrams, and manipulating them through its equational theory. We extend the formalism to accommodate finite dimensional Hilbert spaces beyond qubit systems. First we define a qudit version of the language, where all systems have the same arbitrary finite dimension d, and show that the provided equational theory is both complete -- i.e. semantical equivalence is entirely captured by the equations -- and minimal -- i.e. none of the equations are consequences of the others. We then extend the graphical language further to accommodate all finite dimensional Hilbert spaces at the same time. We again show the completeness of the provided equational theory.</description><author>Marc de Visme and Renaud Vilmart</author><pubDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2401.16225</guid></item><item><title>Optimal compilation of parametrised quantum circuits</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2401.12877</link><description>Parametrised quantum circuits contain phase gates whose phase is determined by a classical algorithm prior to running the circuit on a quantum device. Such circuits are used in variational algorithms like QAOA and VQE. In order for these algorithms to be as efficient as possible it is important that we use the fewest number of parameters. We show that, while the general problem of minimising the number of parameters is NP-hard, when we restrict to circuits that are Clifford apart from parametrised phase gates and where each parameter is used just once, we can efficiently find the optimal parameter count. We show that when parameter transformations are required to be sufficiently well-behaved that the only rewrites that reduce parameters correspond to simple 'fusions'. Using this we find that a previous circuit optimisation strategy by some of the authors [Kissinger, van de Wetering. PRA (2019)] finds the optimal number of parameters. Our proof uses the ZX-calculus. We also prove that the standard rewrite rules of the ZX-calculus suffice to prove any equality between parametrised Clifford circuits.</description><author>John van de Wetering, Richie Yeung, Tuomas Laakkonen and Aleks Kissinger</author><pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2401.12877</guid></item><item><title>Graphical Symplectic Algebra</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2401.07914</link><description>We give complete presentations for the dagger-compact props of affine Lagrangian and coisotropic relations over an arbitrary field. This provides a unified family of graphical languages for both affinely constrained classical mechanical systems, as well as odd-prime-dimensional stabiliser quantum circuits. To this end, we present affine Lagrangian relations by a particular class of undirected coloured graphs. In order to reason about composite systems, we introduce a powerful scalable notation where the vertices of these graphs are themselves coloured by graphs. In the setting of stabiliser quantum mechanics, this scalable notation gives an extremely concise description of graph states, which can be composed via ``phased spider fusion.'' Likewise, in the classical mechanical setting of electrical circuits, we show that impedance matrices for reciprocal networks are presented in essentially the same way.</description><author>Robert I. Booth, Titouan Carette and Cole Comfort</author><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2401.07914</guid></item><item><title>Differentiation of Linear Optical Circuits</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2401.07997</link><description>Experimental setups based on linear optical circuits and single photon sources offer a promising platform for near-term quantum machine learning. However, current applications are all based on support vector machines and gradient-free optimization methods. Differentiating an optical circuit over a phase parameter poses difficulty because it results in an operator on the Fock space which is not unitary. In this paper, we show that the derivative of the expectation values of a linear optical circuit can be computed by sampling from a larger circuit, using one additional photon. In order to express the derivative in terms of expectation values, we develop a circuit extraction procedure based on unitary dilation. We end by showing that the full gradient of a universal programmable interferometer can be estimated using polynomially many queries to a boson sampling device. This is in contrast to the qubit setting, where exponentially many parameters are needed to cover the space of unitaries. Our algorithm enables applications of photonic technologies to machine learning, quantum chemistry and optimization, powered by gradient descent.</description><author>Giovanni de Felice and Christopher Cortlett</author><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2401.07997</guid></item><item><title>Nonunitary gates using measurements only</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2312.17325</link><description>Measurement-based quantum computation (MBQC) is a universal platform to realize unitary gates, only using measurements which act on a pre-prepared entangled resource state. By deforming the measurement bases, as well as the geometry of the resource state, we show that MBQC circuits always transmit and act on the input state but generally realize nonunitary logical gates. In contrast to the stabilizer formalism which is often used for unitary gates, we find that ZX calculus is an ideal computation method of these nonunitary gates. As opposed to unitary gates, nonunitary gates can not be applied with certainty, due to the randomness of quantum measurements. We maximize the success probability of realizing nonunitary gates, and discuss applications including imaginary time evolution, which we demonstrate on a noisy intermediate scale quantum device.</description><author>Daniel Azses, Jonathan Ruhman and Eran Sela</author><pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2312.17325</guid></item><item><title>Graphical CSS Code Transformation Using ZX Calculus</title><link>https://uwspace.uwaterloo.ca/bitstream/handle/10012/20193/Li_SarahMeng.pdf?sequence=1&amp;isAllowed=y</link><description>In this work, we present a generic approach to transform CSS codes by building upon their equivalence to phase-free ZX diagrams. Using the ZX calculus, we demonstrate diagrammatic transformations between encoding maps associated with different codes. As a motivating example, we give explicit transformations between the Steane code and the quantum Reed-Muller code, since by switching between these two codes, one can obtain a fault-tolerant universal gate set. To this end, we propose a bidirectional rewrite rule to find a (not necessarily transversal) physical implementation for any logical ZX diagram in any CSS code. We then focus on two code transformation techniques: code morphing, a procedure that transforms a code while retaining its fault-tolerant gates, and gauge fixing, where complimentary codes can be obtained from a common subsystem code (e.g., the Steane and the quantum Reed-Muller codes from the J15, 1, 3, 3K code). We provide explicit graphical derivations for these techniques and show how ZX and graphical encoder maps relate several equivalent perspectives on these code-transforming operations</description><author>Sarah Meng Li</author><pubDate>Sat, 23 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://uwspace.uwaterloo.ca/bitstream/handle/10012/20193/Li_SarahMeng.pdf?sequence=1&amp;isAllowed=y</guid></item><item><title>The Geometry of Quantum Computing</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2312.14807</link><description>In this expository paper we present a brief introduction to the geometrical modeling of some quantum computing problems. After a brief introduction to establish the terminology, we focus on quantum information geometry and ZX-calculus, establishing a connection between quantum computing questions and quantum groups, i.e. Hopf algebras.</description><author>E. Ercolessi, R. Fioresi and T. Weber</author><pubDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2312.14807</guid></item><item><title>Reinforcement Learning Based Quantum Circuit Optimization via ZX-Calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2312.11597</link><description>We propose a novel Reinforcement Learning (RL) method for optimizing quantum circuits using the graph-like representation of a ZX-diagram. The agent, trained using the Proximal Policy Optimization (PPO) algorithm, employs Graph Neural Networks to approximate the policy and value functions. We test our approach for two differentiated circuit size regimes of increasing relevance, and benchmark it against the best-performing ZX-calculus based algorithm of the PyZX library, a state-of-the-art tool for circuit optimization in the field. We demonstrate that the agent can generalize the strategies learned from 5-qubit circuits to 20-qubit circuits of up to 450 Clifford gates, with enhanced compressions with respect to its counterpart while remaining competitive in terms of computational performance.</description><author>Jordi Riu, Jan Nogué, Gerard Vilaplana, Artur Garcia-Saez and Marta P. Estarellas</author><pubDate>Mon, 18 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2312.11597</guid></item><item><title>Quantum Picturalism: Learning Quantum Theory in High School</title><link>https://dx.doi.org/10.1109/QCE57702.2023.20321</link><description>Quantum theory is often regarded as challenging to learn and teach, with advanced mathematical prerequisites ranging from complex numbers and probability theory to matrix multiplication, vector space algebra and symbolic manipulation within the Hilbert space formalism. It is traditionally considered an advanced undergraduate or graduate-level subject.   In this work, we challenge the conventional view by proposing "Quantum Picturalism" as a new approach to teaching the fundamental concepts of quantum theory and computation. We establish the foundations and methodology for an ongoing educational experiment to investigate the question "From what age can students learn quantum theory if taught using a diagrammatic approach?". We anticipate that the primary benefit of leveraging such a diagrammatic approach, which is conceptually intuitive yet mathematically rigorous, will be eliminating some of the most daunting barriers to teaching and learning this subject while enabling young learners to reason proficiently about high-level problems. We posit that transitioning from symbolic presentations to pictorial ones will increase the appeal of STEM education, attracting more diverse audience.</description><author>Selma Dündar-Coecke, Lia Yeh, Caterina Puca, Sieglinde M. -L. Pfaendler, Muhammad Hamza Waseem, Thomas Cervoni, Aleks Kissinger, Stefano Gogioso and Bob Coecke</author><pubDate>Wed, 06 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2312.03653</guid></item><item><title>Causal flow preserving optimisation of quantum circuits in the ZX-calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2312.02793</link><description>Optimising quantum circuits to minimise resource usage is crucial, particularly in the context of near term hardware which is limited by quantum volume. This paper introduces an optimisation algorithm which aims to minimise non-Clifford gate count and two-qubit gate count by building on ZX-calculus-based strategies. By translating a circuit into a ZX-diagram it can be simplified before being extracted back into a circuit. I assert that simplifications preserve a graph-theoretic property called causal flow. This has the advantage that qubit lines are well defined throughout, permitting a trivial extraction procedure and in turn enabling the calculation of an individual transformation's impact on the resulting circuit. A general procedure for a decision strategy is introduced, inspired by an existing heuristic based method. Both phase teleportation and the neighbour unfusion rule are generalised. In particular, allowing unfusion of multiple neighbours is shown to lead to significant improvements in optimisation. When run on a set of benchmark circuits, the algorithm developed reduces the two-qubit gate count by an average of 19.6%, beating both the previous best ZX-based strategy (14.2%) and non-ZX strategy (18.9%). This lays a foundation for multiple avenues of improvement. A particularly effective strategy for optimising QFT circuits is also noted, resulting in exactly one two-qubit gate per non-Clifford gate.</description><author>Calum Holker</author><pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2312.02793</guid></item></channel></rss>