<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Dec 2023 11:13:07 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Quantum Picturalism: Learning Quantum Theory in High School</title><link>https://dx.doi.org/10.1109/QCE57702.2023.20321</link><description>Quantum theory is often regarded as challenging to learn and teach, with advanced mathematical prerequisites ranging from complex numbers and probability theory to matrix multiplication, vector space algebra and symbolic manipulation within the Hilbert space formalism. It is traditionally considered an advanced undergraduate or graduate-level subject.   In this work, we challenge the conventional view by proposing "Quantum Picturalism" as a new approach to teaching the fundamental concepts of quantum theory and computation. We establish the foundations and methodology for an ongoing educational experiment to investigate the question "From what age can students learn quantum theory if taught using a diagrammatic approach?". We anticipate that the primary benefit of leveraging such a diagrammatic approach, which is conceptually intuitive yet mathematically rigorous, will be eliminating some of the most daunting barriers to teaching and learning this subject while enabling young learners to reason proficiently about high-level problems. We posit that transitioning from symbolic presentations to pictorial ones will increase the appeal of STEM education, attracting more diverse audience.</description><author>Selma Dündar-Coecke, Lia Yeh, Caterina Puca, Sieglinde M. -L. Pfaendler, Muhammad Hamza Waseem, Thomas Cervoni, Aleks Kissinger, Stefano Gogioso and Bob Coecke</author><pubDate>Wed, 06 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2312.03653</guid></item><item><title>Causal flow preserving optimisation of quantum circuits in the ZX-calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2312.02793</link><description>Optimising quantum circuits to minimise resource usage is crucial, particularly in the context of near term hardware which is limited by quantum volume. This paper introduces an optimisation algorithm which aims to minimise non-Clifford gate count and two-qubit gate count by building on ZX-calculus-based strategies. By translating a circuit into a ZX-diagram it can be simplified before being extracted back into a circuit. I assert that simplifications preserve a graph-theoretic property called causal flow. This has the advantage that qubit lines are well defined throughout, permitting a trivial extraction procedure and in turn enabling the calculation of an individual transformation's impact on the resulting circuit. A general procedure for a decision strategy is introduced, inspired by an existing heuristic based method. Both phase teleportation and the neighbour unfusion rule are generalised. In particular, allowing unfusion of multiple neighbours is shown to lead to significant improvements in optimisation. When run on a set of benchmark circuits, the algorithm developed reduces the two-qubit gate count by an average of 19.6%, beating both the previous best ZX-based strategy (14.2%) and non-ZX strategy (18.9%). This lays a foundation for multiple avenues of improvement. A particularly effective strategy for optimising QFT circuits is also noted, resulting in exactly one two-qubit gate per non-Clifford gate.</description><author>Calum Holker</author><pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2312.02793</guid></item><item><title>Optimizing ZX-Diagrams with Deep Reinforcement Learning</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2311.18588</link><description>ZX-diagrams are a powerful graphical language for the description of quantum processes with applications in fundamental quantum mechanics, quantum circuit optimization, tensor network simulation, and many more. The utility of ZX-diagrams relies on a set of local transformation rules that can be applied to them without changing the underlying quantum process they describe. These rules can be exploited to optimize the structure of ZX-diagrams for a range of applications. However, finding an optimal sequence of transformation rules is generally an open problem. In this work, we bring together ZX-diagrams with reinforcement learning, a machine learning technique designed to discover an optimal sequence of actions in a decision-making problem and show that a trained reinforcement learning agent can significantly outperform other optimization techniques like a greedy strategy or simulated annealing. The use of graph neural networks to encode the policy of the agent enables generalization to diagrams much bigger than seen during the training phase.</description><author>Maximilian Nägele and Florian Marquardt</author><pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2311.18588</guid></item><item><title>VyZX: Formal Verification of a Graphical Quantum Language</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2311.11571</link><description>Mathematical representations of graphs often resemble adjacency matrices or lists, representations that facilitate whiteboard reasoning and algorithm design. In the realm of proof assistants, inductive representations effectively define semantics for formal reasoning. This highlights a gap where algorithm design and proof assistants require a fundamentally different structure of graphs, particularly for process theories which represent programs using graphs. To address this gap, we present VyZX, a verified library for reasoning about inductively defined graphical languages. These inductive constructs arise naturally from category theory definitions. A key goal for VyZX is to Verify the ZX-calculus, a graphical language for reasoning about quantum computation. The ZX-calculus comes with a collection of diagrammatic rewrite rules that preserve the graph's semantic interpretation. We show how inductive graphs in VyZX are used to prove the correctness of the ZX-calculus rewrite rules and apply them in practice using standard proof assistant techniques. VyZX integrates easily with the proof engineer's workflow through visualization and automation.</description><author>Adrian Lehmann, Ben Caldwell, Bhakti Shah and Robert Rand</author><pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2311.11571</guid></item><item><title>Minimal Equational Theories for Quantum Circuits</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2311.07476</link><description>We introduce the first minimal and complete equational theory for quantum circuits. Hence, we show that any true equation on quantum circuits can be derived from simple rules, all of them being standard except a novel but intuitive one which states that a multi-control $2π$ rotation is nothing but the identity. Our work improves on the recent complete equational theories for quantum circuits, by getting rid of several rules including a fairly unpractical one. One of our main contributions is to prove the minimality of the equational theory, i.e. none of the rules can be derived from the other ones. More generally, we demonstrate that any complete equational theory on quantum circuits (when all gates are unitary) requires rules acting on an unbounded number of qubits. Finally, we also simplify the complete equational theories for quantum circuits with ancillary qubits and/or qubit discarding.</description><author>Alexandre Clément, Noé Delorme and Simon Perdrix</author><pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2311.07476</guid></item><item><title>Enriching Diagrams with Algebraic Operations</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2310.11288</link><description>In this paper, we extend diagrammatic reasoning in monoidal categories with algebraic operations and equations. We achieve this by considering monoidal categories that are enriched in the category of Eilenberg-Moore algebras for a monad. Under the condition that this monad is monoidal and affine, we construct an adjunction between symmetric monoidal categories and symmetric monoidal categories enriched over algebras for the monad. This allows us to devise an extension, and its semantics, of the ZX-calculus with probabilistic choices by freely enriching over convex algebras, which are the algebras of the finite distribution monad. We show how this construction can be used for diagrammatic reasoning of noise in quantum systems.</description><author>Alejandro Villoria, Henning Basold and Alfons Laarman</author><pubDate>Tue, 17 Oct 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2310.11288</guid></item><item><title>Flexible entangled state generation in linear optics</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2310.06832</link><description>Fault-tolerant quantum computation can be achieved by creating constant-sized, entangled resource states and performing entangling measurements on subsets of their qubits. Linear optical quantum computers can be designed based on this approach, even though entangling operations at the qubit level are non-deterministic in this platform. Probabilistic generation and measurement of entangled states must be pushed beyond the required threshold by some combination of scheme optimisation, introduction of redundancy and auxiliary state assistance. We report progress in each of these areas. We explore multi-qubit fusion measurements on dual-rail photonic qubits and their role in measurement-based resource state generation, showing that it is possible to boost the success probability of photonic GHZ state analysers with single photon auxiliary states. By incorporating generators of basic entangled "seed" states, we provide a method that simplifies the process of designing and optimising generators of complex, encoded resource states by establishing links to ZX diagrams.</description><author>Brendan Pankovich, Alex Neville, Angus Kan, Srikrishna Omkar, Kwok Ho Wan and Kamil Brádler</author><pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2310.06832</guid></item><item><title>Completeness of qufinite ZXW calculus, a graphical language for mixed-dimensional quantum computing</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2309.13014</link><description>Finite-dimensional quantum theory serves as the theoretical foundation for quantum information and computation based on 2-dimensional qubits, d-dimensional qudits, and their interactions. The qufinite ZX calculus has been used as a framework for mixed-dimensional quantum computing; however, it lacked the crucial property of completeness, which ensures that the calculus incorporates a set of rules rich enough to prove any equation. The ZXW calculus is a complete language for qudit quantum computing with applications previously unreachable solely with the ZX or ZW calculus. In this paper, we introduce the qufinite ZXW calculus, a unification of all qudit ZXW calculi in a single framework for mixed-dimensional quantum computing. We provide a set of rewrite rules and a unique normal form that make the calculus complete for finite-dimensional quantum theory. This work paves the way for the optimization of mixed dimensional circuits and tensor networks appearing in different areas of quantum computing including quantum chemistry, compilation, and quantum many-body systems.</description><author>Quanlong Wang and Boldizsár Poór</author><pubDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2309.13014</guid></item><item><title>Reinforcement Learning based Circuit Compilation via ZX-calculus</title><link>https://diposit.ub.edu/dspace/bitstream/2445/202911/1/Memoria_TFM-JanNogue.pdf</link><description>ZX-calculus is a formalism that can be used for quantum circuit compilation and optimization. We developed a Reinforcement Learning approach for enhanced circuit optimization via the ZX-diagram graph representation of the quantum circuit. The agent is trained using the well-established Proximal Policy Optimization (PPO) algorithm, and it uses Conditional Action Trees to perform Invalid Action Masking to reduce the space of actions available to the agent and speed up its training. Additionally, we also design and implement a Genetic Algorithm for the same task. Both the genetic algorithm and the most widely used ZX-calculus-based library for circuit optimization, the PyZX library, are used to benchmark our RL approach. We find our RL algorithm to be competitive against both approaches, but further exploration is required.</description><author>Jan Nogué Gómez</author><pubDate>Mon, 28 Aug 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://diposit.ub.edu/dspace/bitstream/2445/202911/1/Memoria_TFM-JanNogue.pdf</guid></item><item><title>Fault-tolerant complexes</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2308.07844</link><description>Fault-tolerant complexes describe surface-code fault-tolerant protocols from a single geometric object. We first introduce fusion complexes that define a general family of fusion-based quantum computing (FBQC) fault-tolerant quantum protocols based on surface codes. We show that any 3-dimensional cell complex where each edge has four incident faces gives a valid fusion complex. This construction enables an automated search for fault tolerance schemes, allowing us to identify 627 examples within a moderate search time. We implement this using the open-source software tool Gavrog and present threshold results for a variety of schemes, finding fusion networks with higher erasure and Pauli thresholds than those existing in the literature. We then define more general structures we call fault-tolerant complexes that provide a homological description of fault tolerance from a large family of low-level error models, which include circuit-based computation, floquet-based computation, and FBQC with multi-qubit measurements. This extends the applicability of homological descriptions of fault tolerance, and enables the generation of many new schemes which have not been previously identified. We also define families of fault-tolerant complexes for color codes and 3d single-shot subsystem codes, which enables similar constructive methods, and we present several new examples of each.</description><author>Hector Bombin, Chris Dawson, Terry Farrelly, Yehua Liu, Naomi Nickerson, Mihir Pant, Fernando Pastawski and Sam Roberts</author><pubDate>Tue, 15 Aug 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2308.07844</guid></item></channel></rss>