<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Aug 2023 12:07:23 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Fault-tolerant complexes</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2308.07844</link><description>Fault-tolerant complexes describe surface-code fault-tolerant protocols from a single geometric object. We first introduce fusion complexes that define a general family of fusion-based quantum computing (FBQC) fault-tolerant quantum protocols based on surface codes. We show that any 3-dimensional cell complex where each edge has four incident faces gives a valid fusion complex. This construction enables an automated search for fault tolerance schemes, allowing us to identify 627 examples within a moderate search time. We implement this using the open-source software tool Gavrog and present threshold results for a variety of schemes, finding fusion networks with higher erasure and Pauli thresholds than those existing in the literature. We then define more general structures we call fault-tolerant complexes that provide a homological description of fault tolerance from a large family of low-level error models, which include circuit-based computation, floquet-based computation, and FBQC with multi-qubit measurements. This extends the applicability of homological descriptions of fault tolerance, and enables the generation of many new schemes which have not been previously identified. We also define families of fault-tolerant complexes for color codes and 3d single-shot subsystem codes, which enables similar constructive methods, and we present several new examples of each.</description><author>Hector Bombin, Chris Dawson, Terry Farrelly, Yehua Liu, Naomi Nickerson, Mihir Pant, Fernando Pastawski and Sam Roberts</author><pubDate>Tue, 15 Aug 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2308.07844</guid></item><item><title>Rewriting and Completeness of Sum-Over-Paths in Dyadic Fragments of Quantum Computing</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2307.14223</link><description>The "Sum-Over-Paths" formalism is a way to symbolically manipulate linear maps that describe quantum systems, and is a tool that is used in formal verification of such systems. We give here a new set of rewrite rules for the formalism, and show that it is complete for "Toffoli-Hadamard", the simplest approximately universal fragment of quantum mechanics. We show that the rewriting is terminating, but not confluent (which is expected from the universality of the fragment). We do so using the connection between Sum-over-Paths and graphical language ZH-calculus, and also show how the axiomatisation translates into the latter. We provide generalisations of the presented rewrite rules, that can prove useful when trying to reduce terms in practice, and we show how to graphically make sense of these new rules. We show how to enrich the rewrite system to reach completeness for the dyadic fragments of quantum computation, used in particular in the Quantum Fourier Transform, and obtained by adding phase gates with dyadic multiples of $π$ to the Toffoli-Hadamard gate-set. Finally, we show how to perform sums and concatenation of arbitrary terms, something which is not native in a system designed for analysing gate-based quantum computation, but necessary when considering Hamiltonian-based quantum computation.</description><author>Renaud Vilmart</author><pubDate>Wed, 26 Jul 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2307.14223</guid></item><item><title>Floquetifying the Colour Code</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2307.11136</link><description>Floquet codes are a recently discovered type of quantum error correction code. They can be thought of as generalising stabilizer codes and subsystem codes, by allowing the logical Pauli operators of the code to vary dynamically over time. In this work, we use the ZX-calculus to create new Floquet codes that are in a definable sense equivalent to known stabilizer codes. In particular, we find a Floquet code that is equivalent to the colour code, but has the advantage that all measurements required to implement it are of weight one or two. Notably, the qubits can even be laid out on a square lattice. This circumvents current difficulties with implementing the colour code fault-tolerantly, while preserving its advantages over other well-studied codes, and could furthermore allow one to benefit from extra features exclusive to Floquet codes. On a higher level, as in arXiv:2303.08829, this work shines a light on the relationship between 'static' stabilizer and subsystem codes and 'dynamic' Floquet codes; at first glance the latter seems a significant generalisation of the former, but in the case of the codes that we find here, the difference is essentially just a few basic ZX-diagram deformations.</description><author>Alex Townsend-Teague, Julio Magdalena de la Fuente and Markus Kesselring</author><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2307.11136</guid></item><item><title>The Qudit ZH-Calculus: Generalised Toffoli+Hadamard and Universality</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2307.10095</link><description>We introduce the qudit ZH-calculus and show how to generalise the phase-free qubit rules to qudits. We prove that for prime dimensions $d$, the phase-free qudit ZH-calculus is universal for matrices over the ring $ℤ[e^2π i/d]$. For qubits, there is a strong connection between phase-free ZH-diagrams and Toffoli+Hadamard circuits, a computationally universal fragment of quantum circuits. We generalise this connection to qudits, by finding that the two-qudit $|0ångle$-controlled $X$ gate can be used to construct all classical reversible qudit logic circuits in any odd qudit dimension, which for qubits requires the three-qubit Toffoli gate. We prove that our construction is asymptotically optimal up to a logarithmic term. Twenty years after the celebrated result by Shi proving universality of Toffoli+Hadamard for qubits, we prove that circuits of $|0\n̊gle$-controlled $X$ and Hadamard gates are approximately universal for qudit quantum computing for any odd prime $d$, and moreover that phase-free ZH-diagrams correspond precisely to such circuits allowing postselections.</description><author>Patrick Roy, John van de Wetering and Lia Yeh</author><pubDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2307.10095</guid></item><item><title>Graphical CSS Code Transformation Using ZX Calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2307.02437</link><description>In this work, we present a generic approach to transform CSS codes by building upon their equivalence to phase-free ZX diagrams. Using the ZX calculus, we demonstrate diagrammatic transformations between encoding maps associated with different codes. As a motivating example, we give explicit transformations between the Steane code and the quantum Reed-Muller code, since by switching between these two codes, one can obtain a fault-tolerant universal gate set. To this end, we propose a bidirectional rewrite rule to find a (not necessarily transversal) physical implementation for any logical ZX diagram in any CSS code.   We then focus on two code transformation techniques: $\textitcode morphing$, a procedure that transforms a code while retaining its fault-tolerant gates, and $\textitgauge fixing$, where complimentary codes can be obtained from a common subsystem code (e.g., the Steane and the quantum Reed-Muller codes from the [[15,1,3,3]] code). We provide explicit graphical derivations for these techniques and show how ZX and graphical encoder maps relate several equivalent perspectives on these code transforming operations.</description><author>Jiaxin Huang, Sarah Meng Li, Lia Yeh, Aleks Kissinger, Michele Mosca and Michael Vasmer</author><pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2307.02437</guid></item><item><title>Speedy Contraction of ZX Diagrams with Triangles via Stabiliser Decompositions</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2307.01803</link><description>Recent advances in classical simulation of Clifford+T circuits make use of the ZX calculus to iteratively decompose and simplify magic states into stabiliser terms. We improve on this method by studying stabiliser decompositions of ZX diagrams involving the triangle operation. We show that this technique greatly speeds up the simulation of quantum circuits involving multi-controlled gates which can be naturally represented using triangles. We implement our approach in the QuiZX library and demonstrate a significant simulation speed-up (up to multiple orders of magnitude) for random circuits and a variation of previously used benchmarking circuits. Furthermore, we use our software to contract diagrams representing the gradient variance of parametrised quantum circuits, which yields a tool for the automatic numerical detection of the barren plateau phenomenon in ansätze used for quantum machine learning. Compared to traditional statistical approaches, our method yields exact values for gradient variances and only requires contracting a single diagram. The performance of this tool is competitive with tensor network approaches, as demonstrated with benchmarks against the quimb library.</description><author>Mark Koch, Richie Yeung and Quanlong Wang</author><pubDate>Tue, 04 Jul 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2307.01803</guid></item><item><title>Dynamic Quantum Circuit Optimization by ZX-calculus using Qsyn</title><link>https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/roy-thesis.pdf</link><description>Quantum circuit optimization plays a crucial role in improving the efficiency and performance of quantum computing systems. In this thesis, we present a comprehensive study on optimizing quantum circuits by integrating decomposition level adjustment and dynamic reduction algorithms. To facilitate the implementation and analysis of these algorithms, we have developed a novel quantum circuit optimization framework called Qsyn in CH. Qsyn is very efficient in terms of the execution time and provides the flexibilities in exploring various optimization strategies. We demonstrate the effectiveness of our approach by applying it to a diverse set of test cases. Our experimental results show that our algorithm can lead to significant Improvements in quantum circuit gate count, 2-qubit-gate count, and circuit depth. The reduction rate are 11.5%, 10.5%, and 14.8%, respectively, when compared to the existing approaches. Furthermore, Qsyn is much faster than the widely used quantum circuit optimization tool, PyZX, particularly for large-scale circuits. The results highlight the superiority of Qsyn and its suitability for optimizing quantum circuits in both quality and computational efficiency. Overall, this thesis contributes to the field of quantum circuit optimization by providing a powerful tool and an optimized workflow that enable more effective and scalable quantum circuit optimization.</description><author>Cheng-Hua (Anita) Lu</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/roy-thesis.pdf</guid></item><item><title>Complete equational theories for the sum-over-paths with unbalanced amplitudes</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.16369</link><description>Vilmart recently gave a complete equational theory for the balanced sum-over-paths over Toffoli-Hadamard circuits, and by extension Clifford+$\mathrmdiag(1, ζ_2^k)$ circuits. Their theory is based on the phase-free ZH-calculus which crucially omits the average rule of the full ZH-calculus, dis-allowing the local summation of amplitudes. Here we study the question of completeness in unbalanced path sums which naturally support local summation. We give a concrete syntax for the unbalanced sum-over-paths and show that, together with symbolic multilinear algebra and the interference rule, various formulations of the average and ortho rules of the ZH-calculus are sufficient to give complete equational theories over arbitrary rings and fields.</description><author>Matthew Amy</author><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.16369</guid></item><item><title>Three-qubit Deutsch-Jozsa in measurement-based quantum computing</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.13372</link><description>Measurement-based quantum computing (MBQC), an alternate paradigm for formulating quantum algorithms, can lead to potentially more flexible and efficient implementations as well as to theoretical insights on the role of entanglement in a quantum algorithm. Using the recently developed ZX-calculus, we outline a general scheme for reformulating quantum circuits as MBQC implementations. After illustrating the method using the two-qubit Deutsch-Jozsa algorithm, we derive a ZX graph-diagram that encodes a general MBQC implementation for the three-qubit Deutsch-Jozsa algorithm. This graph describes an 11-qubit cluster state on which single-qubit measurements are used to execute the algorithm. Particular sets of choices of the axes for the measurements can be used to implement any realization of the oracle. In addition, we derive an equivalent lattice cluster state for the algorithm.</description><author>M. Schwetz and R. M. Noack</author><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jun 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.13372</guid></item><item><title>The Qupit Stabiliser ZX-travaganza: Simplified Axioms, Normal Forms and Graph-Theoretic Simplification</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.05204</link><description>We present a smorgasbord of results on the stabiliser ZX-calculus for odd prime-dimensional qudits (i.e. qupits). We derive a simplified rule set that closely resembles the original rules of qubit ZX-calculus. Using these rules, we demonstrate analogues of the spider-removing local complementation and pivoting rules. This allows for efficient reduction of diagrams to the affine with phases normal form. We also demonstrate a reduction to a unique form, providing an alternative and simpler proof of completeness. Furthermore, we introduce a different reduction to the graph state with local Cliffords normal form, which leads to a novel layered decomposition for qupit Clifford unitaries. Additionally, we propose a new approach to handle scalars formally, closely reflecting their practical usage. Finally, we have implemented many of these findings in DiZX, a new open-source Python library for qudit ZX-diagrammatic reasoning.</description><author>Boldizsár Poór, Robert I. Booth, Titouan Carette, John van de Wetering and Lia Yeh</author><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.05204</guid></item></channel></rss>