<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 12:15:43 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Preserving MWPM Decodability in Fault-Equivalent Rewrites</title><link>https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/schweikart-thesis.pdf</link><description>For the successful application of quantum computers, the suppression of noise has often been dubbed as the most critical problem. Quantum Error Correction (QEC) codes encode the state of logical qubits onto a higher number of physical qubits, adding reduncancy to make limited amounts of noise detectable and correctable in theory. However, computing the right correction for a given syndrome is generally N P-complete. Yet, corrections must be performed at a high frequency to suppress noise successfully. For the surface code, the decoding problem is guaranteed to have a specific structure that enables efficient decoding through the Minimum-Weight Perfect Matching (MWPM) decoder. This property can be lost when constructing implementations for the detector measurements, making the decoding problem hard again. In this work, we take a circuit-centric perspective to define matchability-preserving rewrites. Based on the ZX calculus and the recently introduced fault-equivalent rewrites, we formalise how the decoding problem changes through the application of ZX rewrites to a given diagram and detector basis. This allows us to analyse whether given ZX rewrites preserve the property that enabled efficient MWPM decoding. We demonstrate a set of matchability-preserving rewrites that can be used to build fault-tolerant syndrome measurements for surface codes.</description><author>Maximilian Schweikart</author><pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/schweikart-thesis.pdf</guid></item><item><title>Optyx: A ZX-based Python library for networked quantum architectures</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09648</link><description>Distributed, large-scale quantum computing will need architectures that combine matter-based qubits with photonic links, but today's software stacks target either gate-based chips or linear-optical devices in isolation. We introduce Optyx, an open-source Python framework offering a unified language to program, simulate, and prototype hybrid, networked systems: users create experiments that mix qubit registers, discrete-variable photonic modes, lossy channels, heralded measurements, and real-time feedback; Optyx compiles them via ZX/ZW calculus into optimised tensor-network forms, and executes with state-of-the-art contraction schedulers based on Quimb and Cotengra. Benchmarking on exact multi-photon circuit simulations shows that, versus permanent-based methods, tensor network contraction can deliver speedups of orders of magnitude for low-depth circuits and entangled photon sources, and natively supports loss and distinguishability -- establishing it as both a high-performance simulator and a rapid-prototyping environment for next-generation photonic-network experiments.</description><author>Mateusz Kupper, Richie Yeung, Boldizsár Poór, Alexis Toumi, William Cashman and Giovanni de Felice</author><pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09648</guid></item><item><title>Exploiting Movable Logical Qubits for Lattice Surgery Compilation</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04169</link><description>Lattice surgery with two-dimensional quantum error correcting codes is among the leading schemes for fault-tolerant quantum computation, motivated by superconducting hardware architectures. In conventional lattice surgery compilation schemes, logical circuits are compiled following a place-and-route paradigm, where logical qubits remain statically fixed in space throughout the computation. In this work, we introduce a paradigm shift by exploiting movable logical qubits via teleportation during the logical lattice surgery CNOT gate. Focusing on lattice surgery with the color code, we propose a proof-of-concept compilation scheme that leverages this capability. Numerical simulations show that the proposed approach can substantially reduce the routed circuit depth compared to standard place-and-route compilation techniques. Our results demonstrate that optimizations based on movable logical qubits are not limited to architectures with physically movable qubits, such as neutral atoms or trapped ions - they are also readily applicable to superconducting quantum hardware. An open-source implementation of our method is available on GitHub https://github.com/munich-quantum-toolkit/qecc.</description><author>Laura Herzog, Lucas Berent, Aleksander Kubica and Robert Wille</author><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04169</guid></item><item><title>Weighted Projective Line ZX Calculus: Quantized Orbifold Geometry for Quantum Compilation</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00682</link><description>We develop a unified geometric framework for quantum circuit compilation based on quantized orbifold phases and their diagrammatic semantics. Physical qubit platforms impose heterogeneous phase resolutions, anisotropic Bloch-ball contractions, and hardware-dependent $2π$ winding behavior. We show that these effects admit a natural description on the weighted projective line $ℙ(a,b)$, whose orbifold points encode discrete phase grids and whose monodromy captures winding accumulation under realistic noise channels.   Building on this geometry, we introduce the WPL--ZX calculus, an extension of the standard ZX formalism in which each spider carries a weight--phase--winding triple $(a,α,k)$. We prove soundness of LCM-based fusion and normalization rules, derive curvature predictors for phase-grid compatibility, and present the Weighted ZX Circuit Compression (WZCC) algorithm, which performs geometry-aware optimization on heterogeneous phase lattices.   To connect circuit-level structure with fault-tolerant architectures, we introduce Monodromy-Aware Surface-Code Decoding (MASD), a winding-regularized modification of minimum-weight matching on syndrome graphs. MASD incorporates orbifold-weighted edge costs, producing monotone decoder-risk metrics and improved robustness across phase-quantized noise models.   All results are validated through symbolic and numerical simulations, demonstrating that quantized orbifold geometry provides a coherent and hardware-relevant extension of diagrammatic quantum compilation.</description><author>Gunhee Cho, Jason Cheng and Evelyn Li</author><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00682</guid></item><item><title>High schoolers excel at Oxford quantum course using pictorial mathematics</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00141</link><description>We are at the dawn of the second quantum revolution, where our ability to create and control individual quantum systems is poised to drive transformative advancements in basic science, computation, and everyday life. However, quantum theory has long been conceived as notoriously hard to learn, creating a significant barrier to workforce development, informed decision-making by stakeholders and policymakers, and broader public understanding.   This paper is concerned with Quantum Picturalism, a novel visual mathematical language for quantum physics. Originally developed over two decades ago to explore the foundational structure of quantum theory, this rigorous diagrammatic framework has since been adopted in both academia and industry as a powerful tool for quantum computing research and software development. Here, we demonstrate its potential as a transformative educational methodology.   We report the findings from a pilot study involving 54 UK high school students, randomly selected from a pool of 734 volunteers across the UK. Despite the absence of advanced mathematical prerequisites, these students demonstrated a strong conceptual grasp of key quantum principles and operations. On an assessment comprising university graduate-level exam questions, participants achieved an 82% pass rate, with 48% obtaining a distinction-level grade.   These results pave the way for making quantum more inclusive, lowering traditional cognitive and demographic barriers to quantum learning. This approach has the potential to broaden participation in the field and provide a promising new entry point for stakeholders, future experts, and the general public.</description><author>Bob Coecke, Aleks Kissinger, Stefano Gogioso, Selma Dündar-Coecke, Caterina Puca, Lia Yeh, Muhammad Hamza Waseem, Emmanuel Pothos, Sieglinde Pfaendler, Vincent Wang-Mascianica, Thomas Cervoni, Ferdi Tomassini, Vincent Anandraj, Peter Sigrist and Ilyas Khan</author><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00141</guid></item><item><title>Untangling Surface Codes: Bridging Braids and Lattice Surgery</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22290</link><description>We present a systematic method for translating fault-tolerant quantum circuits between their braiding and lattice surgery (LS) representations within the surface code. Our approach employs the ZX calculus to establish an equivalence between these two paradigms, enabling verified, bidirectional conversion of arbitrary surface-code-level circuits. We show that both braiding and LS operations can be uniformly expressed as compositions of multibody measurements and demonstrate that the Raussendorf compression rule encompasses all known braid and bridge optimizations. We also introduce a novel CNOT circuit with LS. Our framework provides a foundation for the automated verification, compilation, and benchmarking of large-scale surface code computations, advancing toward a unified formal language for topological quantum computation.</description><author>Alexandru Paler</author><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22290</guid></item><item><title>Making sense of quantum teleportation: An intervention study on students' conceptions using a diagrammatic approach</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21443</link><description>Quantum physics education at the upper-secondary level traditionally follows a historical approach, rarely extending beyond early 20th-century ideas, leaving students unprepared for comprehending modern quantum technologies central to everyday life and many facets of modern industry. To address this gap, we investigated how upper-secondary students and pre-service teachers understand quantum teleportation when taught with a simplified diagrammatic formalism based on the ZX-calculus, which represents quantum processes as diagrams of wires and boxes. Through phenomenographic analysis of video-recorded group work sessions, written responses to exercises, and a group interview, with a total of n=21 participants, we identified an outcome space consisting of four qualitatively different, hierarchically ordered categories of description encapsulating the different ways of experiencing quantum teleportation. The categories revealed that a conceptual progression depends on how one understands the temporality in quantum processes, the role of entanglement in quantum teleportation, the active nature of quantum measurements, and interpretations of mathematical operations in the diagrams. Our findings demonstrate that while a simplified diagrammatic formalism for teaching quantum physics provides an accessible entry point at the upper-secondary level, it does not automatically resolve fundamental conceptual challenges, and requires careful consideration in terms of developing teaching and learning sequences. Finally, these results provide educators with a deeper understanding of conceptual affordances and challenges for designing and improving instruction, whilst also highlighting the need for further exploring how students and teachers alike understand quantum phenomena.</description><author>Sebastian Kilde-Westberg, Andreas Johansson, Anna Pearson and Jonas Enger</author><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21443</guid></item><item><title>Graph Rewriting Language as a Platform for Quantum Diagrammatic Calculi</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15581</link><description>Systematic discovery of optimization paths in quantum circuit simplification remains a challenge. Today, ZX-calculus, a computing model for quantum circuit transformation, is attracting attention for its highly abstract graph-based approach. Whereas existing tools such as PyZX and Quantomatic offer domain-specific support for quantum circuit optimization, visualization and theorem-proving, we present a complementary approach using LMNtal, a general-purpose hierarchical graph rewriting language, to establish a diagrammatic transformation and verification platform with model checking. Our methodology shows three advantages: (1) manipulation of ZX-diagrams through native graph transformation rules, enabling direct implementation of basic rules; (2) quantified pattern matching via QLMNtal extensions, greatly simplifying rule specification; and (3) interactive visualization and validation of optimization paths through state space exploration. Through case studies, we demonstrate how our framework helps understand optimization paths and design new algorithms and strategies. This suggests that the declarative language LMNtal and its toolchain could serve as a new platform to investigate quantum circuit transformation from a different perspective.</description><author>Kayo Tei, Haruto Mishina, Naoki Yamamoto and Kazunori Ueda</author><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15581</guid></item><item><title>ZX-DB: A Graph Database for Quantum Circuit Simplification and Rewriting via the ZX-Calculus</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13033</link><description>Quantum computing is an emerging computational paradigm with the potential to outperform classical computers in solving a variety of problems. To achieve this, quantum programs are typically represented as quantum circuits, which must be optimized and adapted for target hardware through quantum circuit compilation. We introduce ZX-DB, a data-driven system that performs quantum circuit simplification and rewriting inside a graph database using ZX-calculus, a complete graphical formalism for quantum mechanics. ZX-DB encodes ZX-calculus rewrite rules as standard openCypher queries and executes them on an example graph database engine, Memgraph, enabling efficient, database-native transformations of large-scale quantum circuits. ZX-DB integrates correctness validation via tensor and graph equivalence checks and is evaluated against the state-of-the-art PyZX framework. Experimental results show that ZX-DB achieves up to an order-of-magnitude speedup for independent rewrites, while exposing pattern-matching bottlenecks in current graph database engines. By uniting quantum compilation and graph data management, ZX-DB opens a new systems direction toward scalable, database-supported quantum computing pipelines.</description><author>Valter Uotila, Cong Yu and Bo Zhao</author><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13033</guid></item><item><title>Ultra Low Overhead Syndrome Extraction for the Steane code</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13700</link><description>We establish a new performance benchmark for the fault-tolerant syndrome extraction of [[7, 1, 3]] Steane code with a dynamic protocol. Our method is built on two highly optimized circuits derived using fault-equivalent ZX-rewrites: a primary fault-tolerant circuit with 14 CNOTs and an efficient non-fault-tolerant recovery circuit with 11 CNOTs. The protocol uses an adaptive response to internal faults, discarding flagged measurements and falling back to the recovery circuit to correct potentially detrimental errors. Monte Carlo simulations confirm the efficiency of our protocol, reducing the logical error rate per cycle by an average of ~14.3% relative to the optimized Steane method [arXiv:2506.17181] and ~17.7% compared to the Reichardt's three-qubit method [arXiv:1804.06995], the leading prior techniques.</description><author>Boldizsár Poór, Benjamin Rodatz and Aleks Kissinger</author><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13700</guid></item></channel></rss>