<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2024 15:52:21 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Equivalence Classes of Quantum Error-Correcting Codes</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12083</link><description>Quantum error-correcting codes (QECC's) are needed to combat the inherent noise affecting quantum processes. Using ZX calculus, we represent QECC's in a form called a ZX diagram, consisting of a tensor network. In this paper, we present canonical forms for CSS codes and CSS states (which are CSS codes with 0 inputs), and we show the resulting canonical forms for the toric code and certain surface codes. Next, we introduce the notion of prime code diagrams, ZX diagrams of codes that have a single connected component with the property that no sequence of rewrite rules can split such a diagram into two connected components. We also show the Fundamental Theorem of Clifford Codes, proving the existence and uniqueness of the prime decomposition of Clifford codes. Next, we tabulate equivalence classes of ZX diagrams under a different definition of equivalence that allows output permutations and any local operations on the outputs. Possible representatives of these equivalence classes are analyzed. This work expands on previous works in exploring the canonical forms of QECC's in their ZX diagram representations.</description><author>Andrey Boris Khesin and Alexander Li</author><pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12083</guid></item><item><title>The Focked-up ZX Calculus: Picturing Continuous-Variable Quantum Computation</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02905</link><description>While the ZX and ZW calculi have been effective as graphical reasoning tools for finite-dimensional quantum computation, the possibilities for continuous-variable quantum computation (CVQC) in infinite-dimensional Hilbert space are only beginning to be explored. In this work, we formulate a graphical language for CVQC. Each diagram is an undirected graph made of two types of spiders: the Z spider from the ZX calculus defined on the reals, and the newly introduced Fock spider defined on the natural numbers. The Z and X spiders represent functions in position and momentum space respectively, while the Fock spider represents functions in the discrete Fock basis. In addition to the Fourier transform between Z and X, and the Hermite transform between Z and Fock, we present exciting new graphical rules capturing heftier CVQC interactions.   We ensure this calculus is complete for all of Gaussian CVQC interpreted in infinite-dimensional Hilbert space, by translating the completeness in affine Lagrangian relations by Booth, Carette, and Comfort. Applying our calculus for quantum error correction, we derive graphical representations of the Gottesman-Kitaev-Preskill (GKP) code encoder, syndrome measurement, and magic state distillation of Hadamard eigenstates. Finally, we elucidate Gaussian boson sampling by providing a fully graphical proof that its circuit samples submatrix hafnians.</description><author>Razin A. Shaikh, Lia Yeh and Stefano Gogioso</author><pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02905</guid></item><item><title>The Qudit ZH Calculus for Arbitrary Finite Fields: Universality and Application</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02219</link><description>We propose a generalization of the graphical ZH calculus to qudits of prime-power dimensions $q = p^t$, implementing field arithmetic in arbitrary finite fields. This is an extension of a previous result by Roy which implemented arithmetic of prime-sized fields; and an alternative to a result by de Beaudrap which extended the ZH to implement cyclic ring arithmetic in $\mathbb Z / q\mathbb Z$ rather than field arithmetic in $\mathbb F_q$. We show this generalized ZH calculus to be universal over matrices $\mathbb C^q^n \to \mathbb C^q^m$ with entries in the ring $\mathbb Z[ømega]$ where $ømega$ is a $p$th root of unity. As an illustration of the necessity of such an extension of ZH for field rather than cyclic ring arithmetic, we offer a graphical description and proof for a quantum algorithm for polynomial interpolation. This algorithm relies on the invertibility of multiplication, and therefore can only be described in a graphical language that implements field, rather than ring, multiplication.</description><author>Dichuan Gao</author><pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02219</guid></item><item><title>Application of ZX-calculus to Quantum Architecture Search</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01095</link><description>This paper presents a novel approach to quantum architecture search by integrating the techniques of ZX-calculus with Genetic Programming (GP) to optimize the structure of parameterized quantum circuits employed in Quantum Machine Learning (QML). Recognizing the challenges in designing efficient quantum circuits for QML, we propose a GP framework that utilizes mutations defined via ZX-calculus, a graphical language that can simplify visualizing and working with quantum circuits. Our methodology focuses on evolving quantum circuits with the aim of enhancing their capability to approximate functions relevant in various machine learning tasks. We introduce several mutation operators inspired by the transformation rules of ZX-calculus and investigate their impact on the learning efficiency and accuracy of quantum circuits. The empirical analysis involves a comparative study where these mutations are applied to a diverse set of quantum regression problems, measuring performance metrics such as the percentage of valid circuits after the mutation, improvement of the objective, as well as circuit depth and width. Our results indicate that certain ZX-calculus-based mutations perform significantly better than others for Quantum Architecture Search (QAS) in all metrics considered. They suggest that ZX-diagram based QAS results in shallower circuits and more uniformly allocated gates than crude genetic optimization based on the circuit model.</description><author>Tom Ewen, Ivica Turkalj, Patrick Holzer and Mark-Oliver Wolf</author><pubDate>Mon, 03 Jun 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01095</guid></item><item><title>ZX-calculus is Complete for Finite-Dimensional Hilbert Spaces</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10896</link><description>The ZX-calculus is a graphical language for reasoning about quantum computing and quantum information theory. As a complete graphical language, it incorporates a set of axioms rich enough to derive any equation of the underlying formalism. While completeness of the ZX-calculus has been established for qubits and the Clifford fragment of prime-dimensional qudits, universal completeness beyond two-level systems has remained unproven until now. In this paper, we present a proof establishing the completeness of finite-dimensional ZX-calculus, incorporating only the mixed-dimensional Z-spider and the qudit X-spider as generators. Our approach builds on the completeness of another graphical language, the finite-dimensional ZW-calculus, with direct translations between these two calculi. By proving its completeness, we lay a solid foundation for the ZX-calculus as a versatile tool not only for quantum computation but also for various fields within finite-dimensional quantum theory.</description><author>Boldizsár Poór, Razin A. Shaikh and Quanlong Wang</author><pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10896</guid></item><item><title>ZX Graphical Calculus for Continuous-Variable Quantum Processes</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2405.07246</link><description>Continuous-variable (CV) quantum information processing is a promising candidate for large-scale fault-tolerant quantum computation. However, analysis of CV quantum process relies mostly on direct computation of the evolution of operators in the Heisenberg picture, and the features of CV space has yet to be thoroughly investigated in an intuitive manner. One key ingredient for further exploration of CV quantum computing is the construction of a computational model that brings visual intuition and new tools for analysis. In this paper, we delve into a graphical computational model, inspired by a similar model for qubit-based systems called the ZX calculus, that enables the representation of arbitrary CV quantum process as a simple directed graph. We demonstrate the utility of our model as a graphical tool to comprehend CV processes intuitively by showing how equivalences between two distinct quantum processes can be proven as a sequence of diagrammatic transformations in certain cases. We also examine possible applications of our model, such as measurement-based quantum computing, characterization of Gaussian and non-Gaussian processes, and circuit optimization.</description><author>Hironari Nagayoshi, Warit Asavanant, Ryuhoh Ide, Kosuke Fukui, Atsushi Sakaguchi, Jun-ichi Yoshikawa, Nicolas C. Menicucci and Akira Furusawa</author><pubDate>Sun, 12 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2405.07246</guid></item><item><title>Exact solution of long-range stabilizer Rényi entropy in the dual-unitary XXZ model</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04448</link><description>Quantum systems can not be efficiently simulated classically due to the presence of entanglement and nonstabilizerness, also known as quantum magic. Here we study the generation of magic under evolution by a quantum circuit. To be able to provide exact solutions, we focus on the dual-unitary XXZ model and a measure of magic called stabilizer Rényi entropy (SRE). Moreover, we focus also on long-range SRE, which cannot be removed by short-depth quantum circuits. To obtain exact solutions we use a ZX-calculus representation and graphical rules for the evaluation of the required expressions. We obtain exact results for SRE after short-time evolution in the thermodynamic limit and for long-range SRE for all times and all R\ńyi parameters for a particular partition of the state. Since the numerical evaluation of these quantities is exponentially costly in the R\'ýi parameter, we verify this numerically for low R\'eí parameters and accessible system sizes and provide numerical results for the long-range SRE in other bipartitions.</description><author>Jordi Arnau Montañà López and Pavel Kos</author><pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04448</guid></item><item><title>EPOC: A Novel Pulse Generation Framework Incorporating Advanced Synthesis Techniques for Quantum Circuits</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2405.03804</link><description>In this paper we propose EPOC, an efficient pulse generation framework for quantum circuits that combines ZX-Calculus, circuit partitioning, and circuit synthesis to accelerate pulse generation. Unlike previous works that focus on generating pulses from unitary matrices without exploring equivalent representations, EPOC employs a finer granularity approach by grouping quantum gates and decomposing the resulting unitary matrices into smaller ones using synthesis techniques. This enables increased parallelism and decreased latency in quantum pulses. EPOC also continuously optimizes the circuit by identifying equivalent representations, leading to further reductions in circuit latency while minimizing the computational overhead associated with quantum optimal control. We introduce circuit synthesis into the workflow of quantum optimal control for the first time and achieve a 31.74% reduction in latency compared to previous work and a 76.80% reduction compared to the gate-based method for creating pulses. The approach demonstrates the potential for significant performance improvements in quantum circuits while minimizing computational overhead.</description><author>Jinglei Cheng, Yuchen Zhu, Yidong Zhou, Hang Ren, Zhixin Song and Zhiding Liang</author><pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2405.03804</guid></item><item><title>[Video] The how and why of translating between the circuit model and the one-way model of quantum computing &amp;#127909;</title><link>https://pirsa.org/24050004</link><description>In the one-way model of measurement based quantum computing, unlike the quantum circuit model, a computation is driven not by unitary gates but by successive adaptive single-qubit measurements on an entangled resource state. So-called flow properties ensure that a one-way computation, described by a measurement pattern, is deterministic overall (up to Pauli corrections on output qubits). Translations between quantum circuits and measurement patterns have been used to show universality of the one-way model, verify measurement patterns, optimise quantum circuits, and more. Yet while it is straightforward to translate a circuit into a measurement pattern, the question of algorithmic "circuit extraction" -- how to translate general measurement patterns with flow to ancilla-free circuits -- had long remained open for all but the simplest type of flow. In this talk, we will recap the one-way model of quantum computing and then explain how the problem of circuit extraction was resolved using the ZX-calculus as a common language for circuits and measurement patterns. We also discuss applications.</description><author>Miriam Backens</author><pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pirsa.org/24050004</guid></item><item><title>A SAT Scalpel for Lattice Surgery: Representation and Synthesis of Subroutines for Surface-Code Fault-Tolerant Quantum Computing</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18369</link><description>Quantum error correction is necessary for large-scale quantum computing. A promising quantum error correcting code is the surface code. For this code, fault-tolerant quantum computing (FTQC) can be performed via lattice surgery, i.e., splitting and merging patches of code. Given the frequent use of certain lattice-surgery subroutines (LaS), it becomes crucial to optimize their design in order to minimize the overall spacetime volume of FTQC. In this study, we define the variables to represent LaS and the constraints on these variables. Leveraging this formulation, we develop a synthesizer for LaS, LaSsynth, that encodes a LaS construction problem into a SAT instance, subsequently querying SAT solvers for a solution. Starting from a baseline design, we can gradually invoke the solver with shrinking spacetime volume to derive more compact designs. Due to our foundational formulation and the use of SAT solvers, LaSsynth can exhaustively explore the design space, yielding optimal designs in volume. For example, it achieves 8% and 18% volume reduction respectively over two states-of-the-art human designs for the 15-to-1 T-factory, a bottleneck in FTQC.</description><author>Daniel Bochen Tan, Murphy Yuezhen Niu and Craig Gidney</author><pubDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18369</guid></item></channel></rss>