<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 12:02:20 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Dynamical codes for hardware with noisy readouts</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07658</link><description>Dynamical stabilizer codes may offer a practical route to large-scale quantum computation. Such codes are defined by a schedule of error-detecting measurements, which allows for flexibility in their construction. In this work, we ask how best to optimise the measurement schedule of dynamically condensed colour codes in various limits of noise bias. We take a particular focus on the setting where measurements introduce more noise than unitary and idling operations - a noise model relevant to some hardware proposals. For measurement-biased noise models, we improve code performance by strategically repeating measurements within the schedule. For unbiased or $Z$-biased noise models, we find repeating measurements offers little improvement - somewhat contrary to our expectations - and investigate why this is. To perform this analysis, we generalise a metric called the teraquop footprint to the teraquop volume. This is the product of the number of qubits and number of rounds of measurements required such that the probability of a spacelike or timelike logical error occurring is less than $10^-12$. In most cases, we find differences in performance are primarily due to the number of rounds of measurements required, rather than the number of qubits - emphasising the importance of using the teraquop volume in the analysis. Additionally, our results provide another example of the importance of making use of correlated errors when decoding, in that using belief matching rather than minimum-weight perfect matching can turn a worst-performing code under a given noise model into a best-performing code.</description><author>Peter-Jan H. S. Derks, Alex Townsend-Teague, Jens Eisert, Markus S. Kesselring, Oscar Higgott and Benjamin J. Brown</author><pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07658</guid></item><item><title>From Fermions to Qubits: A ZX-Calculus Perspective</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06212</link><description>Mapping fermionic systems to qubits on a quantum computer is often the first step for algorithms in quantum chemistry and condensed matter physics. However, it is difficult to reconcile the many different approaches that have been proposed, such as those based on binary matrices, ternary trees, and stabilizer codes. This challenge is further exacerbated by the many ways to describe them -- transformation of Majorana operators, action on Fock states, encoder circuits, and stabilizers of local encodings -- making it challenging to know when the mappings are equivalent. In this work, we present a graphical framework for fermion-to-qubit mappings that streamlines and unifies various representations through the ZX-calculus.   To start, we present the correspondence between linear encodings of the Fock basis and phase-free ZX-diagrams. The commutation rules of scalable ZX-calculus allows us to convert the fermionic operators to Pauli operators under any linear encoding. Next, we give a translation from ternary tree mappings to scalable ZX-diagrams, which not only directly represents the encoder map as a CNOT circuit, but also retains the same structure as the tree. Consequently, we graphically prove that ternary tree transformations are equivalent to linear encodings, a recent result by Chiew et al. The scalable ZX representation moreover enables us to construct an algorithm to directly compute the binary matrix for any ternary tree mapping. Lastly, we present the graphical representation of local fermion-to-qubit encodings. Its encoder ZX-diagram has the same connectivity as the interaction graph of the fermionic Hamiltonian and also allows us to easily identify stabilizers of the encoding.</description><author>Haytham McDowall-Rose, Razin A. Shaikh and Lia Yeh</author><pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06212</guid></item><item><title>Planar fault-tolerant circuits for non-Clifford gates on the 2D color code</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.05175</link><description>We introduce a family of scalable planar fault-tolerant circuits that implement logical non-Clifford operations on a 2D color code, such as a logical $T$ gate or a logical non-Pauli measurement that prepares a magic $|Tångle$ state. The circuits are relatively simple, consisting only of physical $T$ gates, $CX$ gates, and few-qubit measurements. They can be implemented with an array of qubits on a 2D chip with nearest-neighbor couplings, and no wire crossings. The construction is based on a spacetime path integral representation of a non-Abelian 2+1D topological phase, which is related to the 3D color code. We turn the path integral into a circuit by expressing it as a spacetime $ZX$ tensor network, and then traversing it in some chosen time direction. We describe in detail how fault tolerance is achieved using a "just-in-time" decoding strategy, for which we repurpose and extend state-of-the-art color-code matching decoders.</description><author>Andreas Bauer and Julio C. Magdalena de la Fuente</author><pubDate>Thu, 08 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.05175</guid></item><item><title>Engineering CSS surgery: compiling any CNOT in any code</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01370</link><description>We introduce a framework for implementing logic in CSS-style quantum error correction codes, building on the surgery methods of Cowtan and Burton [CB24]. Our approach offers a systematic methodology for designing and analysing surgery protocols. At the physical level, we introduce the concept of subcodes, which encapsulate all the necessary data for performing surgery. At the logical level, leveraging homological algebra, subcodes enable us to track the logical operations induced by any surgery protocol, regardless of the choice of logical operator basis. In particular, we make no assumptions on the structure of the logical operators of the code, thereby eschewing the irreducibility assumption that has been necessary in other formulations of surgery for CSS codes [Coh+22; Cro+24; ZL24]. As a proof of concept, we develop a surgery protocol inspired by lattice surgery that implements a logical CNOT gate between any two logical qubits. Applicable to any CSS code, this protocol is highly versatile and facilitates the process of fault-tolerant design.</description><author>Clément Poirson, Joschka Roffe and Robert I. Booth</author><pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01370</guid></item><item><title>Improved T counts and active volume estimates for high-level arithmetic subroutines</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19626</link><description>Surface code based quantum computers show great promise for fault-tolerant quantum computing, but most architectures needlessly increase the spacetime volume of a computation due to qubits sitting idly during a computation. Active volume architectures, with long-range connectivity, aim to remove idle spacetime volume leaving only the spacetime volume that logically contributes to a computation. In this work we optimise and derive the active volumes for several industry-leading low- and high-level arithmetic subroutines and achieve significant T-count reductions. We discuss a simple method for estimating and optimising active volumes using orientated ZX diagrams. We also demonstrate that circuit structure, beyond gate counts alone, impacts the active volume of a subroutine and therefore should be taken into consideration when designing circuits.</description><author>Sam Heavey</author><pubDate>Mon, 28 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19626</guid></item><item><title>Clifford and Non-Clifford Splitting in Quantum Circuits: Applications and ZX-Calculus Detection Procedure</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16004</link><description>Classical simulation of quantum circuits is a pivotal part of the quantum computing landscape, specially within the NISQ era, where the constraints imposed by available hardware are unavoidable. The Gottesman-Knill theorem further motivates this argument by accentuating the importance of Clifford circuits and their role on this topic of simulation. In this work, we propose and analyze use cases that come from quantum circuits that can be written as product between a Clifford and a Non-Clifford unitary, these ranging from fully classical emulation, hybrid quantum-classical execution or even quantum algorithm simplification. To further complement this analysis, we make use of ZX-Calculus and its assets to detect a limiting border of these circuits that would allow for a separation between a Clifford section and a Non-Clifford section. To achieve this, we present a novel procedure for parsing ZX diagrams, that not only allows for the detection of this border but also simplifies the circuit extraction process.</description><author>Fernando Lima and Arcesio Castañeda Medina</author><pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16004</guid></item><item><title>Rapidly Trainable and Shallow-Compiled Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm for Maximum Likelihood Detection</title><link>https://dx.doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1016/j.physleta.2025.130541</link><description>In multiple-input and multiple-output (MIMO) systems, the maximum likelihood (ML) detection problem is NP-hard and becomes increasingly complex with more transmitting antennas and symbols. The quantum approximate optimization algorithm (QAOA), a leading candidate algorithm running in the noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices, can show quantum advantage for approximately solving combinatorial optimization problems. In this paper, we propose an improved QAOA based maximum likelihood detection. In the proposed scheme, we use ZX-calculus to prove the parameter symmetry in QAOA circuits, which can be used to reduce the search space and accelerate the training process. Moreover, to run QAOA on quantum devices, an improved qubit mapping method with simultaneous gate absorption is proposed, which can compile the quantum circuit of the QAOA to satisfy the connectivity constraints of real quantum devices with fewer CNOT counts. In numerical experiments, our scheme accelerates parameter training by an average of 29.8% and uses fewer CNOT gates and shallower circuit depth during compilation. This demonstrates that our scheme has significant advantages over the traditional scheme.</description><author>Yuxiang Liu, Yinuo Qian, Lu Wang, Zaichen Zhang and Xutao Yu</author><pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0375960125003214</guid></item><item><title>Fault-tolerant protocols through spacetime concatenation</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08918</link><description>We introduce a framework called spacetime concatenation for fault-tolerant compilation of syndrome extraction circuits of stabilizer codes. Spacetime concatenation enables efficient compilation of syndrome extraction circuits into dynamical codes through structured gadget layouts and encoding matrices, facilitating low-weight measurements while preserving logical information. Our framework uses conditions that are sufficient for fault-tolerance of the dynamical code, including not measuring logical operators and preserving the spacetime distance. We construct explicit examples of dynamical codes using this framework, including the dynamical bivariate bicycle code and a dynamical Haah code, while illustrating their fault-tolerant properties. Furthermore, we analyze the classification and resource trade-offs of dynamical codes, demonstrating their adaptability to hardware constraints, including fabrication defects and qubit dropout scenarios.</description><author>Yichen Xu and Arpit Dua</author><pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08918</guid></item><item><title>Optimizing Quantum Circuits via ZX Diagrams using Reinforcement Learning and Graph Neural Networks</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03429</link><description>Quantum computing is currently strongly limited by the impact of noise, in particular introduced by the application of two-qubit gates. For this reason, reducing the number of two-qubit gates is of paramount importance on noisy intermediate-scale quantum hardware. To advance towards more reliable quantum computing, we introduce a framework based on ZX calculus, graph-neural networks and reinforcement learning for quantum circuit optimization. By combining reinforcement learning and tree search, our method addresses the challenge of selecting optimal sequences of ZX calculus rewrite rules. Instead of relying on existing heuristic rules for minimizing circuits, our method trains a novel reinforcement learning policy that directly operates on ZX-graphs, therefore allowing us to search through the space of all possible circuit transformations to find a circuit significantly minimizing the number of CNOT gates. This way we can scale beyond hard-coded rules towards discovering arbitrary optimization rules. We demonstrate our method's competetiveness with state-of-the-art circuit optimizers and generalization capabilities on large sets of diverse random circuits.</description><author>Alexander Mattick, Maniraman Periyasamy, Christian Ufrecht, Abhishek Y. Dubey, Christopher Mutschler, Axel Plinge and Daniel D. Scherer</author><pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03429</guid></item><item><title>Exhaustive Search for Quantum Circuit Optimization using ZX Calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10983</link><description>Quantum computers allow a near-exponential speed-up for specific applications when compared to classical computers. Despite recent advances in the hardware of quantum computers, their practical usage is still severely limited due to a restricted number of available physical qubits and quantum gates, short coherence time, and high error rates. This paper lays the foundation towards a metric independent approach to quantum circuit optimization based on exhaustive search algorithms. This work uses depth-first search and iterative deepening depth-first search. We rely on ZX calculus to represent and optimize quantum circuits through the minimization of a given metric (e.g. the T-gate and edge count). ZX calculus formally guarantees that the semantics of the original circuit is preserved. As ZX calculus is a non-terminating rewriting system, we utilise a novel set of pruning rules to ensure termination while still obtaining high-quality solutions. We provide the first formalization of quantum circuit optimization using ZX calculus and exhaustive search. We extensively benchmark our approach on 100 standard quantum circuits. Finally, our implementation is integrated in the well-known libraries PyZX and Qiskit as a compiler pass to ensure applicability of our results.</description><author>Tobias Fischbach, Pierre Talbot and Pascal Bouvry</author><pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10983</guid></item></channel></rss>