<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 18:01:32 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>TopoLS: Lattice Surgery Compilation via Topological Program Transformations</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.23109</link><description>Fault-tolerant quantum computing with surface codes can be achieved by compiling logical circuits into lattice-surgery instructions. To minimize space-time volume, we present TopoLS, a topological compiler that combines ZX-diagram optimizations with Monte Carlo tree search guided by different operation placements and topology-aware circuit partitioning. Our approach enables scalable exploration of lattice surgery structures and consistently reduces resource overhead. Evaluations of various benchmark algorithms across multiple architectures show that TopoLS achieves an average 33% reduction in space-time volume over prior heuristic-based compilers, while maintaining linear compilation time scaling. Compared to the SAT-solver-based compiler, which provides optimal results only for small circuits before becoming intractable, TopoLS offers an effective and scalable solution for lattice-surgery compilation.</description><author>Junyu Zhou, Yuhao Liu, Ethan Decker, Justin Kalloor, Mathias Weiden, Kean Chen, Costin Iancu and Gushu Li</author><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.23109</guid></item><item><title>Alternating ZX Circuit Extraction for Hardware-Adaptive Compilation</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.20007</link><description>We present a novel quantum circuit extraction scheme that tightly integrates graph-like ZX diagrams with hardware-adaptive routing. The method utilizes the degrees of freedom during the conversion from a ZX diagram to a quantum circuit (extraction). It alternates between generating multiple extraction options and evaluating them based on hardware constraints, allowing the routing algorithm to inform and guide the extraction process. This feedback loop extends existing graph-like ZX extraction and supports modular integration of different extraction algorithms, routing strategies, and target hardware, making it a versatile building block during compilation. To perform numerical evaluations, a reference instance of the scheme is implemented with SWAP-based routing for neutral atom hardware and evaluated using various benchmark collections on small-to mid-scale circuits. The reference code is available as open-source, allowing fast integration of other extraction and/or routing tools to stimulate further research and foster improvements of the proposed scheme.</description><author>Ludwig Schmid, Korbinian Staudacher and Robert Wille</author><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.20007</guid></item><item><title>A dataflow programming framework for linear optical distributed quantum computing</title><link>https://dx.doi.org/10.22331/q-2026-01-19-1972</link><description>Photonic systems offer a promising platform for interconnecting quantum processors and enabling scalable, networked architectures. Designing and verifying such architectures requires a unified formalism that integrates linear algebraic reasoning with probabilistic and control-flow structures. In this work, we introduce a graphical framework for distributed quantum computing that brings together linear optics, the ZX-calculus, and dataflow programming. Our language supports the formal analysis and optimization of distributed protocols involving both qubits and photonic modes, with explicit interfaces for classical control and feedforward, all expressed within a synchronous dataflow model with discrete-time dynamics. Within this setting, we classify entangling photonic fusion measurements, show how their induced Pauli errors can be corrected via a novel flow structure for fusion networks, and establish correctness proofs for new repeat-until-success protocols enabling arbitrary fusions. Layer by layer, we construct qubit architectures incorporating practical optical components such as beam splitters, switches, and photon sources, with graphical proofs that they are deterministic and support universal quantum computation. Together, these results establish a foundation for verifiable compilation and automated optimization in networked quantum computing.</description><author>Giovanni de Felice, Boldizsár Poór, Cole Comfort, Lia Yeh, Mateusz Kupper, William Cashman and Bob Coecke</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08389</guid></item><item><title>Holographic codes seen through ZX-calculus</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04467</link><description>We re-visit the pentagon holographic quantum error correcting code from a ZX-calculus perspective. By expressing the underlying tensors as ZX-diagrams, we study the stabiliser structure of the code via Pauli webs. In addition, we obtain a diagrammatic understanding of its logical operators, encoding isometries, Rényi entropy and toy models of black holes/wormholes. Then, motivated by the pentagon holographic code's ZX-diagram, we introduce a family of codes constructed from ZX-diagrams on its dual hyperbolic tessellations and study their logical error rates using belief propagation decoders.</description><author>Kwok Ho Wan, H. Price and Qing Yao</author><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04467</guid></item><item><title>Computational complexity perspective on graphical calculi for quantum computation</title><link>https://etheses.bham.ac.uk/id/eprint/16910/</link><description>Diagrammatic reasoning via languages such as ZX Calculus is a powerful tool in theoretical quantum computing. However, physical quantum computers do not understand diagrams and require explicit quantum circuits as inputs. Finding a circuit equivalent to the given diagram is known as circuit extraction. Such problems in graphical calculi form a limitation preventing the wider adoption of diagrammatic reasoning.
Computational complexity theory formalises the difficulty of problems. For ZX diagrams, the circuit extraction problem is #P-hard and unlikely to have an efficient algorithm. Therefore, partial solutions are critical. Currently, efficient circuit extraction is only possible for diagrams containing a structure of so-called Pauli flow. This structure is necessary and sufficient for robust determinism in measurement-based quantum computation (MBQC) – a model of quantum computation, an alternative to circuits, where adaptive single-qubit measurements drive computation. Thus, Pauli flow links MBQC, ZX Calculus, and the circuit model. It is known how to find flow structures in polynomial time when they exist; nevertheless, their lengthy and complex definitions often hinder working with them.
In this thesis, I present contributions to two connected topics: the hardness of problems in graphical calculi and Pauli flow as a method for overcoming circuit extraction. First, I show that circuit extraction can be #P-hard for phase-free ZH diagrams, extending the previous result for ZX diagrams. I also establish a relation between phase-free ZH and $\textbfNP^\textbf#P$ class. This involves weakening the oracle, crafting a complete problem, and encoding the problem into phase-free ZH.
My next contribution concerns Pauli flow. I simplify the Pauli flow definition by providing a new algebraic interpretation. This involves defining two matrices arising from the adjacency matrix of the underlying graph. Then, Pauli flow corresponds to the existence of a right-inverse of the first matrix, which, when multiplied by the second matrix, results in a matrix of a directed acyclic graph. Based on the newly defined algebraic interpretation, I obtain $O(n^3)$ algorithms for finding Pauli flow, improving on the previous $O(n^4)$ bounds. I also introduce a lower bound for Pauli flow-finding by linking it to linear algebra problems over $픽_2$. Finally, when given an unlabelled open graph, I show how to find measurement labelling resulting in Pauli flow.</description><author>Piotr Mitosek</author><pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://etheses.bham.ac.uk/id/eprint/16910/</guid></item><item><title>Preserving MWPM Decodability in Fault-Equivalent Rewrites</title><link>https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/schweikart-thesis.pdf</link><description>For the successful application of quantum computers, the suppression of noise has often been dubbed as the most critical problem. Quantum Error Correction (QEC) codes encode the state of logical qubits onto a higher number of physical qubits, adding reduncancy to make limited amounts of noise detectable and correctable in theory. However, computing the right correction for a given syndrome is generally N P-complete. Yet, corrections must be performed at a high frequency to suppress noise successfully. For the surface code, the decoding problem is guaranteed to have a specific structure that enables efficient decoding through the Minimum-Weight Perfect Matching (MWPM) decoder. This property can be lost when constructing implementations for the detector measurements, making the decoding problem hard again. In this work, we take a circuit-centric perspective to define matchability-preserving rewrites. Based on the ZX calculus and the recently introduced fault-equivalent rewrites, we formalise how the decoding problem changes through the application of ZX rewrites to a given diagram and detector basis. This allows us to analyse whether given ZX rewrites preserve the property that enabled efficient MWPM decoding. We demonstrate a set of matchability-preserving rewrites that can be used to build fault-tolerant syndrome measurements for surface codes.</description><author>Maximilian Schweikart</author><pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/schweikart-thesis.pdf</guid></item><item><title>Optyx: A ZX-based Python library for networked quantum architectures</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09648</link><description>Distributed, large-scale quantum computing will need architectures that combine matter-based qubits with photonic links, but today's software stacks target either gate-based chips or linear-optical devices in isolation. We introduce Optyx, an open-source Python framework offering a unified language to program, simulate, and prototype hybrid, networked systems: users create experiments that mix qubit registers, discrete-variable photonic modes, lossy channels, heralded measurements, and real-time feedback; Optyx compiles them via ZX/ZW calculus into optimised tensor-network forms, and executes with state-of-the-art contraction schedulers based on Quimb and Cotengra. Benchmarking on exact multi-photon circuit simulations shows that, versus permanent-based methods, tensor network contraction can deliver speedups of orders of magnitude for low-depth circuits and entangled photon sources, and natively supports loss and distinguishability -- establishing it as both a high-performance simulator and a rapid-prototyping environment for next-generation photonic-network experiments.</description><author>Mateusz Kupper, Richie Yeung, Boldizsár Poór, Alexis Toumi, William Cashman and Giovanni de Felice</author><pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09648</guid></item><item><title>Exploiting Movable Logical Qubits for Lattice Surgery Compilation</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04169</link><description>Lattice surgery with two-dimensional quantum error correcting codes is among the leading schemes for fault-tolerant quantum computation, motivated by superconducting hardware architectures. In conventional lattice surgery compilation schemes, logical circuits are compiled following a place-and-route paradigm, where logical qubits remain statically fixed in space throughout the computation. In this work, we introduce a paradigm shift by exploiting movable logical qubits via teleportation during the logical lattice surgery CNOT gate. Focusing on lattice surgery with the color code, we propose a proof-of-concept compilation scheme that leverages this capability. Numerical simulations show that the proposed approach can substantially reduce the routed circuit depth compared to standard place-and-route compilation techniques. Our results demonstrate that optimizations based on movable logical qubits are not limited to architectures with physically movable qubits, such as neutral atoms or trapped ions - they are also readily applicable to superconducting quantum hardware. An open-source implementation of our method is available on GitHub https://github.com/munich-quantum-toolkit/qecc.</description><author>Laura Herzog, Lucas Berent, Aleksander Kubica and Robert Wille</author><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04169</guid></item><item><title>Weighted Projective Line ZX Calculus: Quantized Orbifold Geometry for Quantum Compilation</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00682</link><description>We develop a unified geometric framework for quantum circuit compilation based on quantized orbifold phases and their diagrammatic semantics. Physical qubit platforms impose heterogeneous phase resolutions, anisotropic Bloch-ball contractions, and hardware-dependent $2π$ winding behavior. We show that these effects admit a natural description on the weighted projective line $ℙ(a,b)$, whose orbifold points encode discrete phase grids and whose monodromy captures winding accumulation under realistic noise channels.   Building on this geometry, we introduce the WPL--ZX calculus, an extension of the standard ZX formalism in which each spider carries a weight--phase--winding triple $(a,α,k)$. We prove soundness of LCM-based fusion and normalization rules, derive curvature predictors for phase-grid compatibility, and present the Weighted ZX Circuit Compression (WZCC) algorithm, which performs geometry-aware optimization on heterogeneous phase lattices.   To connect circuit-level structure with fault-tolerant architectures, we introduce Monodromy-Aware Surface-Code Decoding (MASD), a winding-regularized modification of minimum-weight matching on syndrome graphs. MASD incorporates orbifold-weighted edge costs, producing monotone decoder-risk metrics and improved robustness across phase-quantized noise models.   All results are validated through symbolic and numerical simulations, demonstrating that quantized orbifold geometry provides a coherent and hardware-relevant extension of diagrammatic quantum compilation.</description><author>Gunhee Cho, Jason Cheng and Evelyn Li</author><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00682</guid></item><item><title>High schoolers excel at Oxford quantum course using pictorial mathematics</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00141</link><description>We are at the dawn of the second quantum revolution, where our ability to create and control individual quantum systems is poised to drive transformative advancements in basic science, computation, and everyday life. However, quantum theory has long been conceived as notoriously hard to learn, creating a significant barrier to workforce development, informed decision-making by stakeholders and policymakers, and broader public understanding.   This paper is concerned with Quantum Picturalism, a novel visual mathematical language for quantum physics. Originally developed over two decades ago to explore the foundational structure of quantum theory, this rigorous diagrammatic framework has since been adopted in both academia and industry as a powerful tool for quantum computing research and software development. Here, we demonstrate its potential as a transformative educational methodology.   We report the findings from a pilot study involving 54 UK high school students, randomly selected from a pool of 734 volunteers across the UK. Despite the absence of advanced mathematical prerequisites, these students demonstrated a strong conceptual grasp of key quantum principles and operations. On an assessment comprising university graduate-level exam questions, participants achieved an 82% pass rate, with 48% obtaining a distinction-level grade.   These results pave the way for making quantum more inclusive, lowering traditional cognitive and demographic barriers to quantum learning. This approach has the potential to broaden participation in the field and provide a promising new entry point for stakeholders, future experts, and the general public.</description><author>Bob Coecke, Aleks Kissinger, Stefano Gogioso, Selma Dündar-Coecke, Caterina Puca, Lia Yeh, Muhammad Hamza Waseem, Emmanuel Pothos, Sieglinde Pfaendler, Vincent Wang-Mascianica, Thomas Cervoni, Ferdi Tomassini, Vincent Anandraj, Peter Sigrist and Ilyas Khan</author><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00141</guid></item></channel></rss>