<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 11:03:14 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Speedy Contraction of ZX Diagrams with Triangles via Stabiliser Decompositions</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2307.01803</link><description>Recent advances in classical simulation of Clifford+T circuits make use of the ZX calculus to iteratively decompose and simplify magic states into stabiliser terms. We improve on this method by studying stabiliser decompositions of ZX diagrams involving the triangle operation. We show that this technique greatly speeds up the simulation of quantum circuits involving multi-controlled gates which can be naturally represented using triangles. We implement our approach in the QuiZX library and demonstrate a significant simulation speed-up (up to multiple orders of magnitude) for random circuits and a variation of previously used benchmarking circuits. Furthermore, we use our software to contract diagrams representing the gradient variance of parametrised quantum circuits, which yields a tool for the automatic numerical detection of the barren plateau phenomenon in ansätze used for quantum machine learning. Compared to traditional statistical approaches, our method yields exact values for gradient variances and only requires contracting a single diagram. The performance of this tool is competitive with tensor network approaches, as demonstrated with benchmarks against the quimb library.</description><author>Mark Koch, Richie Yeung and Quanlong Wang</author><pubDate>Tue, 04 Jul 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2307.01803</guid></item><item><title>Three-qubit Deutsch-Jozsa in measurement-based quantum computing</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.13372</link><description>Measurement-based quantum computing (MBQC), an alternate paradigm for formulating quantum algorithms, can lead to potentially more flexible and efficient implementations as well as to theoretical insights on the role of entanglement in a quantum algorithm. Using the recently developed ZX-calculus, we outline a general scheme for reformulating quantum circuits as MBQC implementations. After illustrating the method using the two-qubit Deutsch-Jozsa algorithm, we derive a ZX graph-diagram that encodes a general MBQC implementation for the three-qubit Deutsch-Jozsa algorithm. This graph describes an 11-qubit cluster state on which single-qubit measurements are used to execute the algorithm. Particular sets of choices of the axes for the measurements can be used to implement any realization of the oracle. In addition, we derive an equivalent lattice cluster state for the algorithm.</description><author>M. Schwetz and R. M. Noack</author><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jun 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.13372</guid></item><item><title>The Qupit Stabiliser ZX-travaganza: Simplified Axioms, Normal Forms and Graph-Theoretic Simplification</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.05204</link><description>We present a smorgasbord of results on the stabiliser ZX-calculus for odd prime-dimensional qudits (i.e. qupits). We derive a simplified rule set that closely resembles the original rules of qubit ZX-calculus. Using these rules, we demonstrate analogues of the spider-removing local complementation and pivoting rules. This allows for efficient reduction of diagrams to the affine with phases normal form. We also demonstrate a reduction to a unique form, providing an alternative and simpler proof of completeness. Furthermore, we introduce a different reduction to the graph state with local Cliffords normal form, which leads to a novel layered decomposition for qupit Clifford unitaries. Additionally, we propose a new approach to handle scalars formally, closely reflecting their practical usage. Finally, we have implemented many of these findings in DiZX, a new open-source Python library for qudit ZX-diagrammatic reasoning.</description><author>Boldizsár Poór, Robert I. Booth, Titouan Carette, John van de Wetering and Lia Yeh</author><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.05204</guid></item><item><title>Quantum Circuit Optimization of Arithmetic circuits using ZX Calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.02264</link><description>Quantum computing is an emerging technology in which quantum mechanical properties are suitably utilized to perform certain compute-intensive operations faster than classical computers. Quantum algorithms are designed as a combination of quantum circuits that each require a large number of quantum gates, which is a challenge considering the limited number of qubit resources available in quantum computing systems. Our work proposes a technique to optimize quantum arithmetic algorithms by reducing the hardware resources and the number of qubits based on ZX calculus. We have utilised ZX calculus rewrite rules for the optimization of fault-tolerant quantum multiplier circuits where we are able to achieve a significant reduction in the number of ancilla bits and T-gates as compared to the originally required numbers to achieve fault-tolerance. Our work is the first step in the series of arithmetic circuit optimization using graphical rewrite tools and it paves the way for advancing the optimization of various complex quantum circuits and establishing the potential for new applications of the same.</description><author>Aravind Joshi, Akshara Kairali, Renju Raju, Adithya Athreya, Reena Monica P, Sanjay Vishwakarma and Srinjoy Ganguly</author><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.02264</guid></item><item><title>Light-matter interaction in the ZXW calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.02114</link><description>In this paper, we develop a graphical calculus to rewrite photonic circuits involving light-matter interactions and non-linear optical effects. We introduce the infinite ZW calculus, a graphical language for linear operators on the bosonic Fock space which captures both linear and non-linear photonic circuits. This calculus is obtained by combining the QPath calculus, a diagrammatic language for linear optics, and the recently developed qudit ZXW calculus, a complete axiomatisation of linear maps between qudits. It comes with a 'lifting' theorem allowing to prove equalities between infinite operators by rewriting in the ZXW calculus. We give a method for representing bosonic and fermionic Hamiltonians in the infinite ZW calculus. This allows us to derive their exponentials by diagrammatic reasoning. Examples include phase shifts and beam splitters, as well as non-linear Kerr media and Jaynes-Cummings light-matter interaction.</description><author>Giovanni de Felice, Razin A. Shaikh, Boldizsár Poór, Lia Yeh, Quanlong Wang and Bob Coecke</author><pubDate>Sat, 03 Jun 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.02114</guid></item><item><title>Speeding up quantum circuits simulation using ZX-Calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.02669</link><description>We present a simple and efficient way to reduce the contraction cost of a tensor network to simulate a quantum circuit. We start by interpreting the circuit as a ZX-diagram. We then use simplification and local complementation rules to sparsify it. We find that optimizing graph-like ZX-diagrams improves existing state of the art contraction cost by several order of magnitude. In particular, we demonstrate an average contraction cost 1180 times better for Sycamore circuits of depth 20, and up to 4200 times better at peak performance.</description><author>Tristan Cam and Simon Martiel</author><pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.02669</guid></item><item><title>Scaling W state circuits in the qudit Clifford hierarchy</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.12504</link><description>We identify a novel qudit gate which we call the $\sqrt[d]Z$ gate. This is an alternate generalization of the qutrit $T$ gate to any odd prime dimension $d$, in the $d^\textth$ level of the Clifford hierarchy. Using this gate which is efficiently realizable fault-tolerantly should a certain conjecture hold, we deterministically construct in the Clifford+$\sqrt[d]Z$ gate set, $d$-qubit $W$ states in the qudit $\ |0ångle , |1\n̊gle \$ subspace. For qutrits, this gives deterministic and fault-tolerant constructions for the qubit $W$ state of sizes three with $T$ count 3, six, and powers of three.   Furthermore, we adapt these constructions to recursively scale the $W$ state size to arbitrary size $N$, in $O(N)$ gate count and $O(\textlog N)$ depth. This is moreover deterministic for any size qubit $W$ state, and for any prime $d$-dimensional qudit $W$ state, size a power of $d$.   For these purposes, we devise constructions of the $ |0\rg̊le $-controlled Pauli $X$ gate and the controlled Hadamard gate in any prime qudit dimension. These decompositions, for which exact synthesis is unknown in Clifford+$T$ for $d &gt; 3$, may be of independent interest.</description><author>Lia Yeh</author><pubDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.12504</guid></item><item><title>The Algebra for Stabilizer Codes</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.10584</link><description>There is a bijection between odd prime dimensional qudit pure stabilizer states modulo invertible scalars and affine Lagrangian subspaces of finite dimensional symplectic $픽_p$-vector spaces. In the language of the stabilizer formalism, full rank stabilizer tableaus are exactly the bases for affine Lagrangian subspaces. This correspondence extends to an isomorphism of props where the composition of stabilizer circuits becomes the relational composition of affine subspaces and the tensor product becomes the direct sum. In this paper, we extend this correspondence between stabilizer circuits and tableaus to the mixed setting; by regarding stabilizer codes as affine coisotropic susbspaces (again only in odd prime qudit dimension/for qubit CSS codes). We show that by splitting the projector for a stabilizer code we recover the error detection protocol and the error correction protocol with affine classical processing power.</description><author>Cole Comfort</author><pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.10584</guid></item><item><title>Towards a generic compilation approach for quantum circuits through resynthesis</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.08814</link><description>In this paper, we propose a generic quantum circuit resynthesis approach for compilation. We use an intermediate representation consisting of Paulistrings over Z, I and X, I called a ``mixed ZX-phase polynomial``. From this universal representation, we generate a completely new circuit such that all multi-qubit gates (CNOTs) are satisfying a given quantum architecture. Moreover, we attempt to minimize the amount of generated gates.   The proposed algorithms generate fewer CNOTs than similar previous methods on different connectivity graphs ranging from 5-20 qubits. In most cases, the CNOT counts are also lower than Qiskit's. For large circuits, containing &gt;= 100 Paulistrings, our proposed algorithms even generate fewer CNOTs than the TKET compiler.   Additionally, we give insight into the trade-off between compilation time and final CNOT count.</description><author>Arianne Meijer - van de Griend</author><pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.08814</guid></item><item><title>A ZX-Calculus Approach to Concatenated Graph Codes</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.08363</link><description>Quantum Error-Correcting Codes (QECCs) are vital for ensuring the reliability of quantum computing and quantum communication systems. Among QECCs, stabilizer codes, particularly graph codes, have attracted considerable attention due to their unique properties and potential applications. Concatenated codes, whichcombine multiple layers of quantum codes, offer a powerful technique for achieving high levels of error correction with a relatively low resource overhead. In this paper, we examine the concatenation of graph codes using the powerful and versatile graphical language of ZX-calculus. We establish a correspondence between the encoding map and ZX-diagrams, and provide a simple proof of the equivalence between encoding maps in the Pauli X basis and the graphic operation "generalized local complementation" (GLC) as previously demonstrated in [J. Math. Phys. 52, 022201]. Our analysis reveals that the resulting concatenated code remains a graph code only when the encoding qubits of the same inner code are not directly connected. When they are directly connected, additional Clifford operations are necessary to transform the concatenated code into a graphcode, thus generalizing the results in [J. Math. Phys. 52, 022201]. We further explore concatenated graph codesin different bases, including the examination of holographic codes as concatenated graph codes. Our findings showcase the potential of ZX-calculus in advancing the field of quantum error correction.</description><author>Zipeng Wu, Song Cheng and Bei Zeng</author><pubDate>Mon, 17 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.08363</guid></item></channel></rss>