<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 14:35:09 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Redefining Lexicographical Ordering: Optimizing Pauli String Decompositions for Quantum Compiling</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00354</link><description>In quantum computing, the efficient optimization of Pauli string decompositions is a crucial aspect for the compilation of quantum circuits for many applications, such as chemistry simulations and quantum machine learning. In this paper, we propose a novel algorithm for the synthesis of trotterized time-evolution operators that results in circuits with significantly fewer gates than previous solutions. Our synthesis procedure takes the qubit connectivity of a target quantum computer into account. As a result, the generated quantum circuit does not require routing, and no additional CNOT gates are needed to run the resulting circuit on a target device. We compare our algorithm against Paulihedral and TKET, and show a significant improvement for randomized circuits and different molecular ansatzes. We also investigate the Trotter error introduced by our ordering of the terms in the Hamiltonian versus default ordering and the ordering from the baseline methods and conclude that our method on average does not increase the Trotter error.</description><author>Qunsheng Huang, David Winderl, Arianne Meijer-van de Griend and Richie Yeung</author><pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00354</guid></item><item><title>Qubit-count optimization using ZX-calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10171</link><description>We propose several methods for optimizing the number of qubits in a quantum circuit while preserving the number of non-Clifford gates. One of our approaches consists in reversing, as much as possible, the gadgetization of Hadamard gates, which is a procedure used by some $T$-count optimizers to circumvent Hadamard gates at the expense of additional qubits. We prove the NP-hardness of this problem and we present an algorithm for solving it. We also propose a more general approach to optimize the number of qubits by showing how it relates to the problem of finding a minimal-width path-decomposition of the graph associated with a given ZX-diagram. This approach can be used to optimize the number of qubits for any computational model that can natively be depicted in ZX-calculus, such as the Pauli Fusion computational model which can represent lattice surgery operations. We also show how this method can be used to efficiently optimize the number of qubits in a quantum circuit by using the ZX-calculus as an intermediate representation.</description><author>Vivien Vandaele</author><pubDate>Sun, 14 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10171</guid></item><item><title>The XYZ ruby code: Making a case for a three-colored graphical calculus for quantum error correction in spacetime</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.08566</link><description>Analyzing and developing new quantum error-correcting schemes is one of the most prominent tasks in quantum computing research. In such efforts, introducing time dynamics explicitly in both analysis and design of error-correcting protocols constitutes an important cornerstone. In this work, we present a graphical formalism based on tensor networks to capture the logical action and error-correcting capabilities of any Clifford circuit with Pauli measurements. We showcase the formalism on new Floquet codes derived from topological subsystem codes, which we call XYZ ruby codes. Based on the projective symmetries of the building blocks of the tensor network we develop a framework of Pauli flows. Pauli flows allow for a graphical understanding of all quantities entering an error correction analysis of a circuit, including different types of QEC experiments, such as memory and stability experiments. We lay out how to derive a well-defined decoding problem from the tensor network representation of a protocol and its Pauli flows alone, independent of any stabilizer code or fixed circuit. Importantly, this framework applies to all Clifford protocols and encompasses both measurement- and circuit-based approaches to fault tolerance. We apply our method to our new family of dynamical codes which are in the same topological phase as the 2+1d color code, making them a promising candidate for low-overhead logical gates. In contrast to its static counterpart, the dynamical protocol applies a Z3 automorphism to the logical Pauli group every three timesteps. We highlight some of its topological properties and comment on the anyon physics behind a planar layout. Lastly, we benchmark the performance of the XYZ ruby code on a torus by performing both memory and stability experiments and find competitive circuit-level noise thresholds of 0.18%, comparable with other Floquet codes and 2+1d color codes.</description><author>Julio C. Magdalena de la Fuente, Josias Old, Alex Townsend-Teague, Manuel Rispler, Jens Eisert and Markus Müller</author><pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.08566</guid></item><item><title>Hybrid Quantum-Classical Machine Learning with String Diagrams</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03673</link><description>Central to near-term quantum machine learning is the use of hybrid quantum-classical algorithms. This paper develops a formal framework for describing these algorithms in terms of string diagrams: a key step towards integrating these hybrid algorithms into existing work using string diagrams for machine learning and differentiable programming. A notable feature of our string diagrams is the use of functor boxes, which correspond to a quantum-classical interfaces. The functor used is a lax monoidal functor embedding the quantum systems into classical, and the lax monoidality imposes restrictions on the string diagrams when extracting classical data from quantum systems via measurement. In this way, our framework provides initial steps toward a denotational semantics for hybrid quantum machine learning algorithms that captures important features of quantum-classical interactions.</description><author>Alexander Koziell-Pipe and Aleks Kissinger</author><pubDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03673</guid></item><item><title>Automated reasoning in quantum circuit compilation</title><link>https://spin-web.github.io/SPIN2024/assets/preproceedings/SPIN2024-paper6.pdf</link><description>Automated reasoning techniques have been proven of immense importance in classical applications like formal verification, circuit design and probabilistic inference. The domain of quantum computing poses new challenges of a different nature, such as the compilation of quantum circuits, which involves ``quantum-hard'' tasks such as the simulation, optimization, synthesis, and equivalence checking of quantum circuits. We ask the question of how effective the methods motivated by classical automated reasoning can be for quantum compilation. We assess their current applicability to this new domain by discussing the recent advances. In particular, we focus on three core automated reasoning approaches: decision diagrams, satisfiability and graphical calculus-based methods. In this survey, we explain in a manner accessible to those unfamiliar with quantum computing concepts how these prominent automated reasoning methods have found numerous applications in quantum circuit compilation. We find that surprisingly all considered reasoning methods, while originally developed for classical purposes, can excel at various compilation tasks for even universal quantum circuits.</description><author>Dimitrios Thanos, Alejandro Villoria, Sebastiaan Brand, Arend-Jan Quist, Jingyi Mei, Tim Coopmans and Alfons Laarman</author><pubDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://spin-web.github.io/SPIN2024/assets/preproceedings/SPIN2024-paper6.pdf</guid></item><item><title>Tensor networks for non-invertible symmetries in 3+1d and beyond</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12978</link><description>Tensor networks provide a natural language for non-invertible symmetries in general Hamiltonian lattice models. We use ZX-diagrams, which are tensor network presentations of quantum circuits, to define a non-invertible operator implementing the Wegner duality in 3+1d lattice $ℤ_2$ gauge theory. The non-invertible algebra, which mixes with lattice translations, can be efficiently computed using ZX-calculus. We further deform the $ℤ_2$ gauge theory while preserving the duality and find a model with nine exactly degenerate ground states on a torus, consistent with the Lieb-Schultz-Mattis-type constraint imposed by the symmetry. Finally, we provide a ZX-diagram presentation of the non-invertible duality operators (including non-invertible parity/reflection symmetries) of generalized Ising models based on graphs, encompassing the 1+1d Ising model, the three-spin Ising model, the Ashkin-Teller model, and the 2+1d plaquette Ising model. The mixing (or lack thereof) with spatial symmetries is understood from a unifying perspective based on graph theory.</description><author>Pranay Gorantla, Shu-Heng Shao and Nathanan Tantivasadakarn</author><pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12978</guid></item><item><title>Equivalence Classes of Quantum Error-Correcting Codes</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12083</link><description>Quantum error-correcting codes (QECC's) are needed to combat the inherent noise affecting quantum processes. Using ZX calculus, we represent QECC's in a form called a ZX diagram, consisting of a tensor network. In this paper, we present canonical forms for CSS codes and CSS states (which are CSS codes with 0 inputs), and we show the resulting canonical forms for the toric code and certain surface codes. Next, we introduce the notion of prime code diagrams, ZX diagrams of codes that have a single connected component with the property that no sequence of rewrite rules can split such a diagram into two connected components. We also show the Fundamental Theorem of Clifford Codes, proving the existence and uniqueness of the prime decomposition of Clifford codes. Next, we tabulate equivalence classes of ZX diagrams under a different definition of equivalence that allows output permutations and any local operations on the outputs. Possible representatives of these equivalence classes are analyzed. This work expands on previous works in exploring the canonical forms of QECC's in their ZX diagram representations.</description><author>Andrey Boris Khesin and Alexander Li</author><pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12083</guid></item><item><title>Genons, Double Covers and Fault-tolerant Clifford Gates</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09951</link><description>A great deal of work has been done developing quantum codes with varying overhead and connectivity constraints. However, given the such an abundance of codes, there is a surprising shortage of fault-tolerant logical gates supported therein. We define a construction, such that given an input $[[n,k,d]]$ code, yields a $[[2n,2k,\ge d]]$ symplectic double code with naturally occurring fault-tolerant logical Clifford gates. As applied to 2-dimensional $D(ℤ_2)$-topological codes with genons (twists) and domain walls, we find the symplectic double is genon free, and of possibly higher genus. Braiding of genons on the original code becomes Dehn twists on the symplectic double. Such topological operations are particularly suited for architectures with all-to-all connectivity, and we demonstrate this experimentally on Quantinuum's H1-1 trapped-ion quantum computer.</description><author>Simon Burton, Elijah Durso-Sabina and Natalie C. Brown</author><pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09951</guid></item><item><title>The Focked-up ZX Calculus: Picturing Continuous-Variable Quantum Computation</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02905</link><description>While the ZX and ZW calculi have been effective as graphical reasoning tools for finite-dimensional quantum computation, the possibilities for continuous-variable quantum computation (CVQC) in infinite-dimensional Hilbert space are only beginning to be explored. In this work, we formulate a graphical language for CVQC. Each diagram is an undirected graph made of two types of spiders: the Z spider from the ZX calculus defined on the reals, and the newly introduced Fock spider defined on the natural numbers. The Z and X spiders represent functions in position and momentum space respectively, while the Fock spider represents functions in the discrete Fock basis. In addition to the Fourier transform between Z and X, and the Hermite transform between Z and Fock, we present exciting new graphical rules capturing heftier CVQC interactions.   We ensure this calculus is complete for all of Gaussian CVQC interpreted in infinite-dimensional Hilbert space, by translating the completeness in affine Lagrangian relations by Booth, Carette, and Comfort. Applying our calculus for quantum error correction, we derive graphical representations of the Gottesman-Kitaev-Preskill (GKP) code encoder, syndrome measurement, and magic state distillation of Hadamard eigenstates. Finally, we elucidate Gaussian boson sampling by providing a fully graphical proof that its circuit samples submatrix hafnians.</description><author>Razin A. Shaikh, Lia Yeh and Stefano Gogioso</author><pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02905</guid></item><item><title>The Qudit ZH Calculus for Arbitrary Finite Fields: Universality and Application</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02219</link><description>We propose a generalization of the graphical ZH calculus to qudits of prime-power dimensions $q = p^t$, implementing field arithmetic in arbitrary finite fields. This is an extension of a previous result by Roy which implemented arithmetic of prime-sized fields; and an alternative to a result by de Beaudrap which extended the ZH to implement cyclic ring arithmetic in $\mathbb Z / q\mathbb Z$ rather than field arithmetic in $\mathbb F_q$. We show this generalized ZH calculus to be universal over matrices $\mathbb C^q^n \to \mathbb C^q^m$ with entries in the ring $\mathbb Z[ømega]$ where $ømega$ is a $p$th root of unity. As an illustration of the necessity of such an extension of ZH for field rather than cyclic ring arithmetic, we offer a graphical description and proof for a quantum algorithm for polynomial interpolation. This algorithm relies on the invertibility of multiplication, and therefore can only be described in a graphical language that implements field, rather than ring, multiplication.</description><author>Dichuan Gao</author><pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02219</guid></item></channel></rss>